<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christs gratious message from the throne of grace to all the prisoners of hope by Timothie Batt.</title>
            <author>Batt, Timothy, 1613-1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 252 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 109 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26828</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1146</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24840</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08609435</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08609435</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41463</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26828)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41463)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1246:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christs gratious message from the throne of grace to all the prisoners of hope by Timothie Batt.</title>
                  <author>Batt, Timothy, 1613-1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[21], 202 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A confession of our faith according to the order of the Gospel: p. 187-202.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Priesthood.</term>
               <term>Salvation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41463:1"/>
            <p>CHRISTS Gratious Meſſage from the Throne of GRACE, To all the Priſoners of HOPE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>ZACH. 9.11.</bibl>
               <p>As for thee alſo, by the blood of thy Covenant, I have ſent forth thy Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners out of the pit, where there is no water.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By TIMOTHIE BATT, Phyſitian.</p>
            <p>Printed in the yeere, 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:41463:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41463:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE CHARLES, King of Great Brittaine, France and Ireland, &amp;c. AND TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE THE LORDS and COMMONS aſſembled in the High Court of PARLIAMENT. Grace and Peace bee multiplyed from God the Father, and from Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough it might ſeeme In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravity that the Sprouts in <hi>Libanus</hi> might attinge or touch the tops of the Cedars in
<pb facs="tcp:41463:3"/> 
               <hi>Libanus.</hi> Notwithſtanding, it is the moſt princely dignity, and the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt honour to the higheſt Cedars of <hi>Libanus;</hi> to overſhadow &amp; defend the loweſt ſprouts. Was it honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in King <hi>Agrippa, Felix</hi> and <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> to lend audience to <hi>Paul</hi> a chay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Priſoner? And will it not bee counted an honorable thing to your Highneſſe, and to Your Honorable Lords to countenance the Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of your Priſoner concerning the Priſoners of Hope? Were the gleanings of <hi>Ephraim</hi> better then vintage of <hi>Abiezer?</hi> and is not our Contemplation concerning Chriſts Priſoners, more fruitfull then the Vine with its fulleſt cluſters? the Starres which are obſcured in the preſence of the brighteſt Sunne, are profitable in his abſence, giving their light to the ſublunarie travi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers: Howſoever the light of theſe our Contemplations for the preſent may ſeeme as darkeneſſe, yet if
<pb facs="tcp:41463:3"/> through your Princely favour, and your Honours protections theſe may be allowed; they will give a glimmering light to the pooreſt ſoule, and moſt diſtreſſed ſpirit: It will bee to them as the flowing ſprings of Solace, and as the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant influence from the higheſt ſtarres. How will they ſing of love becauſe of the Fathers deareſt love? how will they ſpeake of glory in Chriſt the prince of glory? when they ſhal underſtand that they are ſet free by the blood of his Covenant out of the pit where in there is no water. <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.11. <hi>As for thee alſo, by the bloud of my Covenant, I have ſent forth thy Priſoners out of the pit, wherein is no water.</hi> When they ſhall finde that their Lord was anoynted to ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> looſe out of the Dungeon of death and darkeneſſe: and that hee was the choſen Redeemer to breake the barres of death, throw upon the gates of hell, and knap in
<pb facs="tcp:41463:4"/> ſunder the chaines of the Devill. Iſa. 61.1, 2, 3. The high and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable are not ignorant, that the greateſt prince under heaven, and the mightieſt Monarch in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunarie world are poore priſoners of hope unto Chriſt mediatour of the covenant, King of his bought &amp; Redeemed. Is the Earth beholding to the watery clouds? and the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt plants to the higheſt planers? &amp; are not all Terren &amp; earthly Princes beholding to Chriſt King of Kings and Lord of Lords for ever. The Priſoners of hope in this ſtate and Kingdom are almoſt infinite in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. How many thouſands lye ſicke at the poole of <hi>Betheſda?</hi> how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands of mourning and drooping hearts waits for Chriſts ſprings of love more then <hi>David</hi> did for the waters of <hi>Bethlehem?</hi> I might ſay, how many Millions wounded in their conſciences, blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in their bloods; lies waiting at
<pb facs="tcp:41463:4"/> this houre before the throne of grace for the ſweete and cleare countenance of God the Father, therefore they ſigh and groane for his aſſurance through his Adoption of children, for his liberty through the Redemption from Eternall bonds, for his righteouſnes through his preſentation glorious, and for his joyes and conſolation through the law of the Spirit of life and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation: as they have found under your Higheſt, Nobleſt and worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt fauours, a gratious defence and loving protection, ſo they doubt not, but that two wings and two ſhadowes will be one wing and one ſhadow for their proſperity &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection: Conſidering, that there is ſuch a neereneſſe of union between the Princely Head, and the Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſhoulders of this Royall ſtate and Kingdome. I with the Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Hope had neither gold nor ſilver, riches nor treaſures, pearles
<pb facs="tcp:41463:5"/> nor jewells to preſent unto His Highneſſe, or to the Honorable Aſſembly; ſave theſe lines of love for acceptation: Not doubting, but our preſent will bee as rich as the Queene of <hi>Shebaes</hi> was in <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> and as <hi>Benjamins</hi> and <hi>Judahs</hi> was in the ſight of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> ſith the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter with the Priſoners of Hope, preſents nothing elſe but a preſent concerning the Love of God the Father, the rich treaſures and the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt Mediator, of the joyes, love and peace concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Spirit of glory our comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: knowing that is not conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for the meaneſt to be offenſive to the higheſt, and the weakeſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome unto the Honorable: We by generall petition, deſire and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt that His Majeſty with your Honours, might honour the pooreſt with your ſhadow and vindication, and we in generall ſhall bee bound by an everlaſting obligation, to wiſh
<pb facs="tcp:41463:5"/> all peace, all unity and concord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene His Majeſty and your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours for ever. Oh that the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> would not only crowne the Lyon with ſtrength and fortitude; but alſo honor his poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Priſoners with peace and ſweet tranquility. Oh that the King of Kings might ſhine gloriouſly upon the head of His Majeſty, and the Prince of Princes might ſhine favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably upon the Nobles of this Kingdome. Oh that the gratious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of him that was in the Buſh, and the deare love of him that was upon the Croſſe might compoſe theſe differences, put an end to theſe great diſtractions, and make two one in this our Native Country. Whilſt we thus deſire and wiſh the welfare, proſperity and dignity of this State and Kingdome; we ſhall waite for His Higheſt and Princely acceptation, and your nobleſt and worthieſt approbation of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe
<pb facs="tcp:41463:6"/> concerning the Priſoners of Hope, ſith it is no leſſe then the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the King of Kings unto a King, an Ambaſſage from the Prince of glory unto Princes: and a Contemplation of the Throne of grace to all that waits for grace in Iſrael. Therefore ſilence ſhall conſtraine us, whileſt we wiſh for the higheſt glory the richeſt mercy, for the deareſt bounty, and for the greateſt love that flowes from the Thron of grace to fall upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, that your dewes may be more ſoft then the dewes upon the tender herbs, that your light may bee more ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous then the ſun in the Meridian, and that the ſtability, firmeneſſe and glory of this State and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth may be faſter fixed then the celeſtiall Orbe. <hi>Amen, Amen, Amen.</hi> Then ſhall the ſonnes of <hi>Sion</hi> ſing a ſong of Melodious, the daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> make a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony victorious, and the pooreſt
<pb facs="tcp:41463:6"/> Priſoners of Hope ſhall ſit under your ſhadows moſt joyous, each gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving glory, praiſe, honour, truth, and thankeſgiving to him that ſitts upon the Throne now and for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more: Recording that ſentence memorable throughout all ages and generations. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 4. laſt. <hi>Thou art worthy, O Lord, to receive glory, and honour, and power: for thou haſt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated all things, and for thy pleaſure they are and were created.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Majeſties moſt humble ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and welwiſher to your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Crowne and dignity; As al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to your Honorable Lords and Commmons, ſate in High Court of <hi>PARLIAMENT. TIMOTHY BATT.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="forward">
            <pb facs="tcp:41463:7"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> An Epiſtle to the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners of Hope, beloved of the Father, and bought by the blood of Chriſt their bleſſed and deare Redeemer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>S the knowledge of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable riches of Chriſt made knowne to the Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of miſerie? and ſhall not I direct my ſpeech to them in the rareſt Elegancie? Are rare things ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken concerning the citie of God? are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent thing ſpoken concerning the ſtreames that make glad the Citie of our God? And are not rare and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent things ſpoken concerning the Priſoners of our God? J had rather my mind ſhould forget its high conceive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, J had rather my affection ſhould looſe it ſweet contentment, then J ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:41463:7"/> forget my ſentence concerning their ſolace and delightment. How ſhould J forget them whom our deareſt Lord hath not forgotten? Why ſhould J not ſet them before mine eyes, whom hee hath preſented in his gratious preſence. For whom was he annoynted? if not for his diſtreſſed flock? For whom was hee wounded? if not for wounded concien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and poore diſtreſſed catives? For whom was his bloody Croſſe, his bitter Agonie? if not for his deareſt ones and Priſoners of great calamity. Will our Lord leade his captives into captivity? No, Will he relinquiſh his gaſping and gronings hearts? No, they are more pretious to him then the rareſt gemms, they are more beautifull in his eyes then the beautifull diadems, and more choiſe to him then the choyſeſt treaſure. Who are written betweene his breaſts? if not they, who are charactered upon his heart? if not they, or who are coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or eſteemed above all Terrene or Earthly treaſures? if not they, For
<pb facs="tcp:41463:8"/> they are beloved of the Father from E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie, they are bought by the Prince of grace and glory, they are ſeale a by the ſpirit of life and liberty: O ye Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners of Hope! are you not as deare to your deareſt Lord in the day of tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as in the day of ſalvation, in the day of temptation, as in the day of recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, in the day of affliction, as in the day of Adoption. J know you have bin wounded by the darts of Satan, bin accuſed by the accuſer of the brethren, you have had warre with the fleſh and corruption, and have been bruiſed like the bruiſed reede, and broken like the Potters veſſell. I know that the ſunne ſhould bee as darkeneſſe, if that you ſhould not behold the Sonne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, that the morning ſtarre ſhould be obſcure, if the morning ſtarre ſhould not appeare in puritie, and the face of ten thouſand Angels ſhould appeare as dimneſſe, if that you ſhould not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the face of the Angell of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in gratiouſneſſe. Hence I am aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured
<pb facs="tcp:41463:8"/> the word of grace, of life, of hope, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f peace, of ſalvation, of reconciliation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f juſtification, and of glorification will be as deare to you as the apple of your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yes, as pretious as your owne lives, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s neare unto you as your owne ſoules; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herefore as the morning ſtarre is to the travellers in the wilderneſſe, as the orientall ſunne to them that ſit in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as the rareſt jewells to them that have no riches: So will this meſſage be to you his bleeding Priſoners. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore J ceaſe to crave acceptation, ſith theſe of you are lovingly accepted, ever wiſhing you grace from your loving Father, bleſſedneſſe and hope from your bleſſed Redeemer, to whom bee given glory and honour in the Churches for ever and ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:41463:9"/>
            <lg>
               <l>VVHen I in blood involved was,</l>
               <l>caſt out to open ſhame:</l>
               <l>His deareſt love did then appeare,</l>
               <l>to everlaſting fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Before I ſaw the Sunne of light,</l>
               <l>the ſunne did ſhine one me;</l>
               <l>Before the morning ſtarre aroſe,</l>
               <l>all darkeneſſe I did ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But when the Sunne and morning ſtar,</l>
               <l>appeared in the day:</l>
               <l>All darkeneſſe vaniſht from my ſight,</l>
               <l>I ſaw a glorious way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of love, of peace, of grace, of hope,</l>
               <l>of reſt and great glory,</l>
               <l>Free from all wrath, debate, and jarres,</l>
               <l>from malice and envie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:41463:9"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n love the Saints doe praiſes ſing,</l>
               <l>unto his glorious name,</l>
               <l>The glorious riches of his grace,</l>
               <l>in joys they doe declaime.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>While they were chain'd in fetters ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</l>
               <l>under the power of hell,</l>
               <l>His riches bountie did appeare,</l>
               <l>free mercy did excell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For he redeemed them from chaines,</l>
               <l>from fetters ſet them free;</l>
               <l>By deareſt love and pretious blood,</l>
               <l>procuring liberty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That they might have acceſſe by faith,</l>
               <l>unto his higheſt grace:</l>
               <l>And live by faith which is in him,</l>
               <l>in his moſt holy place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hence are the gemmes of rareſt worth,</l>
               <l>appearing in his ſight:</l>
               <l>Beholding his moſt glorious face,</l>
               <l>his everlaſting light.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When clouds of darkeneſſe did beſet,</l>
               <l>their ſoules incompaſt round:</l>
               <l>Overwhelm'd were they by helliſh fiends,</l>
               <l>they woe and ſorrow found.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:41463:10"/>
               <l>Then ſhin'd he forth in the ſweet face,</l>
               <l>of Chriſt the Prince of peace:</l>
               <l>When he by death did reconcile,</l>
               <l>all enmitie did ceaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That they might ſtand compleate in robes,</l>
               <l>more pure then the gold;</l>
               <l>More rich then gemmes and pretious ſtones,</l>
               <l>a hundred thouſand fould.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When they were naked and unrob'd,</l>
               <l>impureſt in his ſight:</l>
               <l>In veſtments pure cloth'd he did,</l>
               <l>in them he tooke delight:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sith he preſented them moſt pure,</l>
               <l>compleat in Chriſt to be:</l>
               <l>Whilſt he gave them to be in Chriſt.</l>
               <l>their great felicity.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When they were ſons of wrath &amp; death</l>
               <l>ſhut out of hope moſt ſure:</l>
               <l>He gave to them inheritance,</l>
               <l>amongſt the Saints moſt pure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That they might have a lott and hope,</l>
               <l>amongſt the Saints moſt deare:</l>
               <l>All glorying hearts in praiſes high,</l>
               <l>with Saints that doe in feare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:41463:10"/>
               <l>When they were fare from Chriſt the vine,</l>
               <l>of peace and pretious love:</l>
               <l>His gratious face on them did ſhine,</l>
               <l>his bounty they did prove.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When they were made one with the vine,</l>
               <l>to be in him for aye:</l>
               <l>In-joying ſprings of pretious joyes,</l>
               <l>in the eternall day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When they were priſoners of his hope,</l>
               <l>involv'd in duſt below:</l>
               <l>His throne of freeſt grace imbraſt,</l>
               <l>to hell he did not throw.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Their bleeding hearts and drooping minds,</l>
               <l>involu'd and wrapt in blood:</l>
               <l>By freeſt grace and deareſt love,</l>
               <l>bought to eternall good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That they in love might prayſes ſing,</l>
               <l>unto his glorious name:</l>
               <l>Rich glorious praiſes of his grace,</l>
               <l>they might to Saints declaime.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shall they ſurceaſe exalting praiſe?</l>
               <l>ſinging free grace for ever:</l>
               <l>His bounty will they not record?</l>
               <l>to Saints that faileth never.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:41463:11"/>
               <l>Praiſe, glory, now perpetually,</l>
               <l>from his abundant ſtore:</l>
               <l>Oh honour that moſt glorious name,</l>
               <l>both now and evermore.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:41463:11"/>
            <l>WHilſt that my Muſes,</l>
            <l>upon high object bent,</l>
            <l>High thoughts poſs'd,</l>
            <l>but to what intent;</l>
            <l>Let Priſoners view,</l>
            <l>and theſe ſweet lines peruſe,</l>
            <l>Peruſe in love,</l>
            <l>and faultie lines excuſe,</l>
            <l>The piercing power,</l>
            <l>of my intellect,</l>
            <l>My loweſt thoughts,</l>
            <l>to highest did erect,</l>
            <l>Memory Retaind,</l>
            <l>thought of a ſubject rare,</l>
            <l>Queene will conſenting,</l>
            <l>ſomewhat to declare,</l>
            <l>Affection joynd,</l>
            <l>with thoſe in combination,</l>
            <l>High thoughts conceiv'd,</l>
            <l>in my contemplation.</l>
            <l>And conſcence paralells,</l>
            <l>affection ſtrong,</l>
            <l>Its rareſt plea,</l>
            <l>I muſt my theme prolong,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:41463:12"/>
            <l>Sith that no obiect,</l>
            <l>to the view or ſight,</l>
            <l>Gives ſuch ſweet ſolace,</l>
            <l>to the ſoules delight,</l>
            <l>And graces power,</l>
            <l>grants its free conſent,</l>
            <l>That all my theame,</l>
            <l>of Chriſt was congruent,</l>
            <l>That pen might ſtay,</l>
            <l>and I might ceaſe my verſe,</l>
            <l>Of Chriſt in proſe,</l>
            <l>the more I might rehearſe.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biblical_exegesis">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41463:12"/>
            <head>Chriſts gratious Meſſage from the Throne of Grace, to all the Priſoners of hope.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ROM. 8.1, 2.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>There is therefore now no condemnation to them which are in Christ Jeſus, who walke not after the fleſh; but after the Spirit, For the law of the Spirit of life in Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, hath made me free from the law of ſinne and death.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen we look upon the Sun, Moone and Starres, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the wiſedome, mercy, and power of the Father towards humane generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; it makes us to ſtand amazed, and aſtoniſhed, ſo when wee looke and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the wiſedome, mercy, and power of the Father ſhining forth in Chriſt the morning Starre, the Sonne of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41463:13"/> grace and bounty, it makes us to wonder and admire at that which ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth forth to us in the morning ſtarre, and glorious Sonne of righteouſneſſe. That which ſhineth to us by in and by the Creature, is not comparable to that which ſhineth toward us in and through the Lord Jeſus. What is the brightnes of the morning ſtarre to Chriſt the morning ſtarre? or what is the beauty and glory of the ſunne, to Chriſt the Sun of glorious righteouſneſſe? or what as the beauty of things terrene &amp; earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to things ſublime or heavenly? hence the Apoſtle memorates and records the excellency of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt by the priviledge the Saints received in and by him, according to the Text. <hi>Now then there is no condemnation to them which are in Christ Jeſus, who walke not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh, but after the Spirit, Rom.</hi> 8, 1. Beloved, our manner is by way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition or contemplation; Now then there is no condemnation? They have been caſt out to the open ſhame of their faces, they were not ſwadled in the day of their Nativity, but troden in their blood, and overwhelmed with the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt miſerie, they have beene alienated
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41463:13"/> from the throne of grace, eſtranged from the mercy ſeate, and have lived without God in the world, they have beene in the blacke ſwadle bands of the Devill, under the claves of the roaring Lyon the Devill, and have beene chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath as well as others. The truth of the premiſſes is granted: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, there is no condemnation to them, ſith the being of the Saints in Chriſt frees them from all the gulfes of horrid miſeries whatſoever: They have many ſinnes, many infirmities, iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and tranſgreſſions, they are an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending and erring people out of the way as well as others: they have beene ſilenced before the throne of Juſtice, they have ſinned and ſhot their arrowes below the glory of the Father, the truth of the premiſes is granted: Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, there is no Condemnation to them which are in Chriſt Jeſus, ſith the Father of eternall mercy hath given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them an abſolute Nonimputation of offences in the Lord Jeſus, in whom hee hath reconciled his beloved Saints and peculiar: in the act of Juſtification hee hath given to his Saints a generall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittance, freeing them from ſinne, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41463:14"/> and tranſgreſſion by the blood of the Lord of life and glory, and by the death of him who was the onely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of his boſome; hence comes in thoſe rare ſentences of divine teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods choſen? it is God that juſtifieth, who is it that ſhall condemne? it is Jeſus Chriſt that is dead, yea, rather that is riſen againe, who is at the right hand of God making interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for us.</hi> Rom. 8.33, 34. To them is given the priviledge and dignity of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they are branches to Jeſus Chriſt the bleſſed and fruitfull Vine of his Church. <hi>I am the Vine, ye are the branches,</hi> John 15.5. they are members to Jeſus Chriſt their bleſſed head and reconciler, to wit, Members of his fleſh &amp; of his bones, Eph. 5.30. they are the choiſe pretious and deareſt ſpouſe of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>My beloved is mine, amd I am his; he feedeth among the Lillies,</hi> Cant. 6.3. they are not onely deare to Chriſt becauſe he hath bought them, but they are neere to Chriſt, becauſe they are made one with him; <hi>The glory that thou gaveſt me, I have given to them, that they may be one as we are one.</hi> John 17.22. What Devill therefore ſhall accuſe? the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41463:14"/> accuſer of the Brethren is caſt out of the heavenly places. <hi>And I heard a great voyce out of heaven ſaying, Now is come ſalvation, and ſtrength and the Kingdome of our God, and the power of his Chriſt; for the accuſer of the brethren is caſt downe, which accuſed them before our God day and night,</hi> what hell ſhall terrifie? ſith the Lord Chriſt hath triumphed over hell, death, the devill and all Evills. <hi>O death where is thy ſting, oh grave where is thy victory. The ſting of death is ſinne, and the ſtrength of ſinne is the law. But thankes be to God, which giveth us victory through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55, 56, 57. ſhall the law adjudge us? noe, ſith wee have a gratious Mediatour who ever preſents us glorious in the ſight of his gratious and heavenly Father; hence it is ſpoken by the holy Ghoſt, that Chriſt entred into heaven to appeare in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God for us. <hi>For Chriſt is not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the holy places made with hands, which are the figures of the true, but into heaven it ſelfe; now to appeare in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God for us. Heb.</hi> 9.24. ſhall death amaze or trouble us? no, for by the death of Chriſt wee are delivered from the ſervitude and ſlaverie of death. <hi>That
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41463:15"/> through death he might deſtroy him that had the power of death, that is the Devill, and deliver them who through feare of death, were all their life time ſubject to bondage. Heb.</hi> 2.14, 15. What though the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namous Serpent ſeeke to ſting thee? yet be not thou diſmayed: what though the Law morrall would accuſe, artaigne or condemne thee before the barre of juſtice? yet be not diſcour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ged: what though death with the ſting thereof would amaze thee? yet bee thou not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed, ſith there is no Condemnation to thy ſoule or conſcience, ſith thou art in Chriſt Jeſus, and he pleades thy cauſe at the right hand of the Father ſaying, This my people ſtands righteous before thee in my righteouſneſſe, holy through my holineſſe, and pure through my pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and integrity: am I not their Lord of pure and divine righteouſneſſe? am I not their prince of glory who hath preſented them pure, ſpotleſſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire in thy ſight? Am not I the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of thy everlaſting grace &amp; mercy? who was made not onely unto them wiſedome and redemption, but alſo righteouſneſſe and ſanctification? was
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41463:15"/> not I arraigned at the barre of <hi>Pontious Pilate,</hi> that they might not be arraigned at the barre of juſtice, accuſed of my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive countrymen, that they might bee excuſed in thy preſence, condemned by their injudiciall ſentence to free them from condemnation. I ſtood in the place of <hi>Manaſſeth,</hi> that Idolater, in the roome of <hi>Paul</hi> that Blaſphemer, in the ſtead of <hi>Peter,</hi> that denier, when mine could not beare the heate of thy burning wrath and indignation; I ſtood and beare their iniquities, when they could not tread the winepreſſe of thy fury, I trode the winepreſſe for them, thou laydſt the ſins of mine upon my ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, thou didſt caſt thy darts through my ſides, I was wounded, I was chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, I was broken to peeces for them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made ſinne for them, who being thy ſonne knew no ſinne, that they might bee made the righteouſneſſe of God in mee. <hi>Now there is no condemnation to them which are in Chriſt Jeſus, who walke not after the fleſh but after the Spirit. Rom.</hi> 8.1. I have made death temporall a bed of downe, a place of reſt, and a ſweete paſſage to my glory, did <hi>Iſrael</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:41463:16"/> paſſe through the red ſea and the waters did not overwhelme them? did Judah and Rheuben paſſe through the waters of Jordan &amp; thoſe did not offend them? and ſhall not mine paſſe through the gates of death, and ſhall that deſtroy them? no, I have taken away the death of death ſpiritual, I live in mine by hope, I have made them to caſt Ankor in the throne of my grace and deareſt mercy, <hi>in whom wee have an Ankor of the ſoule, ſafe and firme, entring into that which is within the vaile. Heb.</hi> 6.19. <hi>Which hope we have as an Ankor of the ſoule both ſure and ſteadfaſt, and which entreth into that within the vaile.</hi> I live in them by love, I have made them live in Me by my love: So that there love to me is above treaſures, riches and honours, above Father, Mother, wife and children, above bonds, chaines, and fetters, above temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, anguiſh or tribulation, above the malice of the Divell, the terrours of the law, the horrours of hell, the darts of the world, and the warres of the fleſh. I have made them to leave all thinges terrene and earthly, and to pitch on thoſe things which are high and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41463:16"/> My love to them in their value and eſtimation is above Rubies, Saphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, pretious gemmes, carbuncles and pretious Iewels, ten thouſand moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of gold in their ſight are under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valued. I am the chiefeſt of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, the loves of men and women are diſaccounted, ſith my love to them is above the loves of Jonathan and David. The freeneſſe of my love hath made them love me intirely and freely, and the eternity of my love hath made them love Me eternally, hence have I ſpoken of them. John 17.28. <hi>And I have made knowne to them thy name, and will make it knowne, that the love wherewith thou haſt loved me, may be in them, and I in them.</hi> I have made them live the life of faith, though their faith overcoms the world, <hi>and this is the victory that overcommeth the wold, even your faith.</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.4. though their faith repulſeth the fiery darts of Satan, <hi>above all taking the ſhield of faith, whereby ye ſhall bee able to quench the fiery darts of Satan, Epheſ.</hi> 6.16. Though their faith is more pretious then gold that is tryed in the fire; <hi>That the tryall of your faith being much more pretious then of gold that periſheth, though it bee tryed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41463:17"/> with fire, might bee found unto praiſe and glory at the appearing of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. Notwithſtanding it is mine, I make them to beleeve in my Father, and in my ſelfe whom hee hath ſent. I made them my beloved, injoyers of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, glorie and beatitude. I made them to abide in me by faith, whilſt I abode in them by love, the truth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is witneſſed by my Apoſtle. <hi>I am crucified with Chriſt, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I live, yet not I, but Chriſt liveth in me, and the life that I now live in the fleſh, I live by the faith of the ſonne of God, who loved me, and gave himſelfe for me.</hi> I alſo have taken away death eternall, for I have reconciled mine to the Father by an everlaſting reconciliation; I have brought with mee the everlaſting robes of righteouſneſſe, I have taken away all their ſinnes, iniquities and tranſgreſſions by my blood moſt pretious: I have made them one by union, that they might enjoy a being in Me and in my Father.</p>
               <p>Hence the ſecond death ſhall have no power of them, I my ſelfe have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it. Apoc. 20.6. <hi>Bleſſed and holy is hee
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41463:17"/> that hath part in the firſt reſurrection, on ſuch the ſecond death hath no power, but they ſhall be Prieſts to God, and of Chriſts, and ſhall raigne with him a thouſand yeares.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What hath the world to ſay to my people? true it is, they have beene drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, perſecuters, blaſphemes, they have beene alienated from my glory, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtranged from my love, and without my preſence in the world, but I have waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them in the pureſt fountaine, I have made their ſcarlet die whiter then the ſnow, their bloody crimſon whiter then the wooll; are they defiled like the Menſtruous cloath? no, are they leprous as was Naaman the Aſſirian? no, they are purer then the pureſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarene. What hath the fleſh to pleade againſt mine? true it is; before I came to live in them, their minds were clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with Egyptian darkeneſſe, there wils reſiſted my words of reconciliation, their affections were involved in things terrene and ſublunarie, their hearts har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then the rockes or milſtone; and their conſciences were the habitation of the blacke fiends of darkeneſſe; but ſince I tooke up my reſt in them, I appeared the glorious light of the Goſpel of life
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41463:18"/> and redemption, I have removed their darkeneſſe, I have made them confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to my ſacred and holy wil, I have ſet their affections aloft in the heavenly places, I have ſoftened their obſtinate and obdurate hearts, and have clenſed their conſciences from ſin by my blood moſt pretious. Now old things are paſt away, and all things are become new: now they are my workmanſhip created in Me to good workes, that they ſhould walke in them. Now my peace, my joy, my love, my grace, and my liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dwells in them. Am I not King and Lord commander in the ſoule? Am I not prince and Lord defender of the conſcience? Am I not Maſter and gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the affections? yea, though ſinne is in their fleſh, yet my grace is in their ſpirits, for I am in them both grace and glory; <hi>therefore there is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus, who walke not after the fleſh but after the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What can the world ſay againſt thoſe that are my redeemed and reconciled? They will take away their good name, I ſuffer the Angels of light to beſpot their garments, I permit the legaliſts to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame &amp; to blemiſh their converſations,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41463:18"/> but the ſervant is not greater then his Maſter, nor the Diſciple then his Lord. If they take away their name, I have given them a name which is written in the booke of life, &amp; charectered it upon my breaſt for ever. If they take away their liberty, yet have they alwaies li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to the throne of my hevenly grace and higheſt mercy, if they take away their goods, yet are they enriched by my heavenly grace and treaſure of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; if they take away their veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yet ſtand they cloathed with my garments of everlaſting righteouſneſſe: And if they take away their lives, yet their lives are hid in me &amp; in my Father. <hi>Therefore there is no condemnation to them which are in Chriſt Jeſus, which walke not after the fleſh but after the Spirit, Rom.</hi> 8.1. There is a threefold ground why there is no condemnation to them which are in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>The firſt ground is this, ſith the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall juſtice of the Father is ſatisfied. I argue thus; if the eternall juſtice of the Father in and by Chriſt is ſatisfied, then there is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt: But the Eternall juſtice of the Father is ſatisfied in &amp; by Chriſt,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41463:19"/> therefore there is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt. That the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the Father is ſatisfied in and by Chriſt, is evident: firſt upon denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Chriſt is called the Sonne of the Father, in whom the Father is well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; ſo the holy Ghoſt hath related in the Evangeliſt. Mat. 3. the laſt. <hi>This is my beloved Sonne in whom I am well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> As if the Father ſhould ſpeake thus to his people, Let all my people know that I know of juſtice no more, of wrath no more, of indignation and vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on no more, true, it is my pleaſure to hide my face, my joy, my peace, my reſt, my glory, and the rareneſſe of my communion from mine; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſuch hath beene my divine and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt pleaſure, that my delight alone is in the Sonne of my boſome, my glory in the prince of grace and glory, and my reſt is in him whom I have conſtituted and appointed to bee Mediator of the Covenant of grace and bounty amongſt the Saints triumphant, none are accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to dwell in my preſence but in and through my beloved: amongſt my Saints and warriours Militant, none are welpleaſing in my ſight but in and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41463:19"/> through the Son of my boſome, hee is the ſweet ſmelling ſacrifice moſt grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; acceptable before Me, I my ſelfe have ſpoken it. Eph. 5.2. <hi>And walke in love, as Chriſt hath loved us, and given him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe an offering: a ſacrifice to God for a ſweet ſmelling ſavour.</hi> The Mirhe, the Aloes, and the Caſſia are not ſweet in my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, the ſweeteſt gumes, the frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and pleaſant oyntments are not pleaſant in my noſtrills; nothing is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant before me but the firſt begotten fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead, and prince of the Kings of the earth, I have undervalued al my Angels, reſpecting none but the Angels of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting covenant, though my pleaſure was to give them a ſong of praiſe for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, counting them worthy of the light of my countenance, dignifying them with the honour of meſſengers &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors, notwithſtanding they could not anſwer my purity, nor ſatisfie my juſtice I have diſeſteemed the ſonnes of men, though I made them Lords over my creatures, the nobleſt of my worekman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and gave to them both purity and innocency; notwithſtanding they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not anſwer my demands, nor appeaſe my wrath nor furie. I have diſaccounted
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41463:20"/> of the bodies of bulls, of beaſts, of goats; and I have prepared a body by and for my ſelfe, I my ſelfe have ſpoken it. <hi>Wherefore when he commeth into the World, he ſaith, ſacrifices and burnt offerings thou wouldeſt not, but a body haſt thou prepared. Heb.</hi> 10.5. Hence I have accepted of the body of the Lord of life for my people, of the blood of the prince of glory for the children of death and miſery, of the death of him that is the Mediatour of of the Covenant of life and promiſes, for the curſe and death of my peculiar. <hi>Now then there is no condemnation to them which are in Chriſt Jeſus, which walke not after the fleſh but after the Spirit, Rom.</hi> 8.1.</p>
               <p>The ſecond ground why there is no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation to them who are in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>Becauſe the law is ſatisfied, the law is ſatisfied actively and paſſively, my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved was to preſent my people com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, pure and holy, without ſpot or wrinkle, unblameable, unreproveable and righteous, to make of unrighteous righteous, of unholy holy, of impure and defiled, pure and undefiled, which in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41463:20"/> and by him was performed, when hee fulfilled all righteouſneſſe, when he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered every jot and title of my law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, when hee was made ſinne for mine, that they might bee made the righteouſneſſe of God in him. 2 Cor. 5. the laſt. He anſwered my law paſſively, for he was wounded, bruiſed and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to peeces, who but your Lord was led as a Lambe to the ſlaughter, and as a ſheep before the ſhearer as dumbe? who but your Lord, cried out upon the Croſs, my God my God, why haſt thou forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken me? who but your Lord ſweat wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and blood in the day of his paſſion? beloved, thou cammeſt ſhort of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, yet thy deare Lord bought thee, the prince of glory ſought thee, &amp; the ſhepheard of the covenant came and performed all for thee, hence, he is the end of the law for righteouſneſſe ſake. Rom. 10.4. <hi>Chriſt is the end of the law for righteouſneſſe ſake, to every one that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves; therefore there is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus, who walke not aftert the fleſh but after the Spirit, Rom.</hi> 8.1.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:41463:21"/>
               <p>The third Ground why there is no condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>Becauſe they are united to the Sonne of my love, had they not beene united to the vine of rareſt vertue, the Lord of richeſt wiſedome, the bridegroome of ſweeteſt love, then might they have bin condemned, but becauſe of their union, they injoy communion in him and with him: by their union they injoy a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold voice.</p>
               <p>The firſt is the voice of Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>The ſecond the voice of Adoption.</p>
               <p>The third, the voice of Juſtification and Redemption.</p>
               <p>Of the firſt, to wit concerning the voyce of Atonement or reconciliation, the day hath been that the wall of ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration hath beene betwixt thee and the Father, the hand writing of ordinances againſt the conſcience, the blackneſſe of darkeneſſe had overclouded the ſoule, thy ſinnes, iniquities, and tranſgreſſions had ſeparated between me and thee, and the whole heavens were overcaſt with the miſts of dimneſſe, till I ſpeake of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41463:21"/> rareſt love in the Sonne of my love, till I ſpeake of peace in the reconciler of my Redeemed, till I ſpake of Reſt to all your reſtleſſe ſoules under heaven, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe my Sonne hath reconciled mine through his pure and pretious blood, hence I have nothing againſt them that are waſhed in his blood; becauſe I have made an attonement in and through him who hath beene my choiſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved ſervant: therefore I have no charge againſt them who have beene children of wrath and enemies againſt my Majeſty. As my love, my grace, my peace, my glory reſts in him; ſo my peace abides in him: hence hath he left the Legacie of deareſt and pretious love. <hi>My peace I give unto you, my peace I leave unto you, not as the world giveth, give I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you; Let not your hearts be troubled nor feare. Therefore there is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus, who walke not after the fleſh but after the Spirit. Rom.</hi> 8.1.</p>
               <p>The ſecond voice of Chriſt, is the voice of Adoption; As our Juſtification, our Redemption, our Vnion, our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, our vocation and Glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation are in Chriſt. So our ſonneſhip
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41463:22"/> or Adoption is in Chriſt: If the Father of glorious mercy account thee a branch, it is becauſe thou art in Chriſt the vine, if hee account thee a member, it is becauſe thou art in Chriſt the head, If hee account thee one of the eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, it is becauſe thou art in Chriſt the Bridegroomed, If he account thee a ſon, it is becauſe thou art in his deare and welbeloved Sonne; hence I come to draw thy ſoule to me, I make to thee thy priviledge. According as I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by my ſervant Iohn. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold how great love the Father hath given to us, that we ſhould bee called the Sonnes of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That though thou waſt a ſlave of hell, a veſſell of wrath, a child of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a bondſlave to the law, and under the ridged and ſevere tyranny of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill: notwithſtanding, I have choſen thee to be one of mine by the covenant of my freeſt grace and bounty, I have redeemed thee for my ſelfe, and called thee by my name, I have adopted thee to be one of my ſonnes and children by adoption, when I tooke up my reſt in my beloved: I preached peace to the peaceleſſe, liberty to the bondmen, grace
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41463:22"/> to the graceleſſe, riches to the poore, and aſſurance of ſonſhip to them who are and have not beene my ſonnes by adoption: hence though no creature pitty thee, though Angels ſhut their eyes againſt thee, and all the ſublunarie Creatures ſhould bid thee adew and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, notwithſtanding I come to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace thee, and to love and delight in thee for ever, ſince the day that I adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thee, have I not filled the ſoule with the joyes, comforts and ſolaces of my ſpirit? have not I ſealed thee to the day of Eternall redemption by the ſeale of Adoption? have not I given thee the ſpirit of prayer and ſupplication? have not I given thee the aſſurance of life and ſalvation? <hi>Now then there is no condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to thy ſoule which art in Chriſt Jeſus, for thou walkeſt not after the fleſh but after the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, the voice of God in Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; how in juſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? yea beloved, this is the Admirable worke of the ſpirit of glory, that we are aſſured that we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed by the blood of Chriſt imcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable, that wee are reconciled by the death of Chriſt unſpeakable, &amp; that wee are aſſured that wee are juſtified by the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41463:23"/> righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of Chriſt undeclarable, I being juſtified in Chriſt, how ſhould I injoy any thing but ſalvation? Am I not made compleate in him that is the head of all principalities and powers? Am I not cloathed with the righteouſneſſe of the Sonne of righteouſneſſe? more bright then ten thouſand Sunnes? Am I not waſhed, purified and clenſed in the pureſt, rareſt and moſt pretious foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine which is in the Kingdome of the deare Sonne of God? hence I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the horne of ſalvation the great, free and eternall ſalvation in Chriſt. <hi>Now then there is no condemnation to me that am in Chriſt Jeſus, who walke not after the fleſh but after the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover theſe three things preſerves the Saints from death and condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The love of Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>2. The power of Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>3. The glory of Chriſt.</item>
               </list>
               <p>What ſaid I the Love of Chriſt? yea: ſearch the hights above, ſound the depths beneath, extend thy thoughts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to all the parts of the ſublunarie
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41463:23"/> Orbe, and thou ſhalt finde no love like the love of Chriſt: is the love of a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo deare to her child? is the love of a husband ſo deare to the wife of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome? as Chriſts love is to his Church? no: with the ſame love wherewith the Father hath loved Chriſt, with the ſame love hee hath loved the Church and choſen: the Father loved Chriſt from eternity, Chriſt hath loved the Church from eternity; the Father through his tender love did not leave his beloved in the day of his Croſſe, when he cryed out My God my God why haſt thou forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken me; <hi>Thou wilt not leave my ſoule in grave, neither wilt thou ſuffer thy holy one to ſee corruption. Pſal.</hi> 16.10.</p>
               <p>Loe the Lord Chriſt will not leave his poore ſervants, his deareſt jewels &amp; his pretious Saints in the dayes of greateſt miſerie and calamity. Pſal. 9 10. <hi>The Lord is a refuge to the poore, a refuge in due time, in the day of trouble.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fathers love to the Lord Chriſt was ſo great, that he ſet him above prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, above might, above power, and above all things; that all things in heaven &amp; earth might bow &amp; bend be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him: <hi>Wherefore God hath exalted him,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41463:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> and given him a name, above every name, that at the name of Jeſus every knee ſhould bow, both of things in heaven, of things on earth, and of things under the earth. Phil.</hi> 2.9.10.</p>
               <p>The love of the Lord Chriſt is: ſo deare to his, that hee hath exalted them above all, <hi>to him that overcommeth, I will give to ſit with me in my throne, as I have overcome, and ſit with my Father in his throne. Revel.</hi> 3.21.</p>
               <p>The Father loved Chriſt ſo intirely, that hee filled him with the riches of righteouſneſſe, the treaſures of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the plenitude of all heavenly excellencies; Chriſt loves his Church ſo affectionately, that hee fills her with heavenly joyes, &amp; he enriches her with all ſpirituall and heavenly gifts, <hi>bleſſed be God the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who hath bleſſed us with ſpirituall bleſſings in heavenly things in Chriſt, Eph.</hi> 1.3. <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore through my love there is no condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to mine, they not after the fleſh but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Spirit.</hi> Rom. 8.1.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:41463:24"/>
               <p>Secondly, Becauſe of the power of Chriſt, there is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>His power is not onely the cauſe of our vivification from the dead, of our Collocation in the heavenly places, of our faith in his name, But alſo of our conſervation to eternall life and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. John 17.2. He defends thee by an internall and efficatious power, when thy ſpirit ſays that thou art overcome, the ſpirit ſaith thou art more then a conquerer through him that loved thee, every day thou art a conquerer through his blood, a victoret through his death, a tryumpher through his righteouſnes, neither the darts of hell, the fire bales of the Devill, the ſtrength of the law, the warres of the fleſh, nor the puiſſant ſtrength of the world can vanquiſh thee: for thou art defended by a ſtrength in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible, thou art protected by a power unconquerable, thou art invi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oned by a might inſuperable and thou art garded with a force inexpugnable, Am I not thy Rocke, thy ſhield, thy Buckler, &amp; defender? Am I not thy Sun thy ſhaddow, thy horne of Salvation &amp; deliverer? Am I not he that carries thee
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41463:25"/> above one Eagles wings? that breakes the bow, the ſpeare and ſheild and van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſheth, overcommeth and concul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tateth under my feete all the enemies of thy ſalvation? my ſtrength is above powers, my might above dominions, my glory above principalities, and my Puiſſancie above all the oppoſers of thy life and addoption. Hence there is no condemnation to thee, for thou art kept by my power to ſalvation, not walking after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the glory of Chriſt is the cauſe why there is no condemnation to them which are in Chriſt Jeſus, that walke not after the fleſh but after the Spirit.</p>
               <p>Chriſt ſpeakes after this manner to his Saints. Beloved, I have written your name upon my breaſt, I have in graven them in the booke of life, I have preſented your cauſe in the preſence of my Father by my blood moſt pure, by my death moſt victorious, by my righteouſneſſe moſt acceptable, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for the glory of my grace, I will not leave you. I that am the Lord of life, the welſpring of living waters, that eternall and everlaſting life given of my
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41463:25"/> Father: I have layd up your lives in the throne of my grace, I have treaſured them, up in the throne of my mercy and for the glory of my mercy I will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert you: have I beſtowed ſo great coſt as to adventure my life, bloud, my death, my righteouſneſſe and my glory for thee? did I leave my height of glory to fetch thy Soule from the lowermoſt hell, from the gates and barres of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death, from the black clawes, clutches and ſwadle bands of Sathan? have I given thee communion with my Father, and with my ſelfe in all the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of heavenly righteouſneſſe, and made thee one of my members, one of my branches, one of my eſpouſed and deareſt friends? and ſhall I now forſake thee? I am that faithfull, <hi>Yea and Amen,</hi> and will keepe my promiſe, I will bee with mine to the end of the world. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. verſe laſt. <hi>There is therefore no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation to mine, they walke not after the fleſh but after the ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee proceede to the ſecond part of the text which walke not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit.</p>
               <p>The bleſſed Apoſtle argues by eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41463:26"/> arguments; that there is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation to them which are in Chriſt Jeſus. The firſt Argument is, If that to the Saints victorie over ſinne and death is given to them by Jeſus Chriſt, then is there no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt. But to the Saints victorie over ſin and death is given to them by Jeſus Chriſt, therfore there is no condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to them. Rom. 7. the laſt. <hi>I thanke God through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. So then, with the minde I my ſelfe ſerve the law of God: but with the fleſh the law of ſinne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the law of the Spirit of life hath freed us from the law of ſin and death, then is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus: But the law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus, hath freed us from the Law of ſinne and death, therefore there is no condemnation to them which are in Chriſt Jeſus. Rom. 8.2. <hi>For the Law of the Spirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus hath made me free from the Law of ſinne and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If God hath ſent his Son to redeeme his owne from ſinne, and that ſinne was condemned in the fleſh of Chriſt for there ſakes, then is their no condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them; But God ſent his owne
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41463:26"/> ſonne to Redeeme them, and that ſinne might be condemned in his fleſh, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is no condemnation to them. Rom. 8.3. <hi>For what the Law could not doe, in that it was weake through the fleſh, God ſending his owne Sonne in the likeneſſe of ſinfull fleſh, and for ſinne condemned ſinne in the fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If they who are in Chriſt Jeſus walke not according to the fleſh but according to the Spirit, then there is no condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them; But they that are in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, walke not according to the fleſh, but according to the Spirit, therefore there is no condemnation to them. Rom. 8 1. <hi>There is therefore now no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation to them which are in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, who walke not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe that are in Chriſt Jeſus walk not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit. They live the life of faith, of love, of hope, of peace, of grace, of mercy &amp; conſolation, through their union they live the life of freedome, &amp; liberty in the ſtate of grace, the life of praiſe and prayer to the thron of glory through their Redemption, they live the life of aſſurance, of Mercy, grace and peace, through there Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41463:27"/> they live the life of purity, bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and joy through their juſtification, they live the life of holineſſe, of chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ſobriety through their Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. My branches walk through the ſtrength of ſweetneſſe, my members walke in the power of my wiſedome, my ſpouſes walke in the joyfulneſſe of the light of my Countenance. Since the day that I waſhed them in my blood moſt pure, they will not polute their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſince the time that I gave them aſſurance that they were the ſonnes of God, they doe walke as deare and love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Children: ſince the moment that they have beene fild with my joyes, my comforts, my conſolations, my influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of divine grace and ſolace: they are filled with praiſes, honorings, and praiſings of my holy name: My Spirit leades them into all truth; when the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, of truth ſhall come, he ſhall teach you all truth. <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.26. <hi>He ſhall teach you all things, and bring all things to your remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, whatſoever I have ſaid unto you;</hi> My Spirit leades them into all obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: <hi>For as many as are lead by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, are the ſonnes of God: Rom.</hi> 8.14 My ſpirit leades them not to conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41463:27"/> to backbitings, to ſlanderings, to railings, to whiſperings, to lyings to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachings, to Envie, Malice, hatred co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, Diſdain &amp; Revenge. But to mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, gentlenes, curtiſie, Meeknes &amp; leni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to joy, to peace to love, to gratiouſnes of ſpirit &amp; ſobrietie. Gal. 5.18, 19.20, 21, 22, 23. But if ye are led by the ſpirit, ye are not under the law: <hi>Now the works of the fleſh are manifeſt, which are theſe; Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, Fornicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, uncleannes, laciviouſnes, &amp;c But the fruits of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, long-ſuffering, gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, faith, meekeneſſe, temperance, againſt theſe there is no law.</hi> There is not a prayer from my grace, to the throne of grace, but my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit hath beene the cauſe thereof, there is not a praiſe from the praiſe of my glory, but my ſpirit is the inſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ent ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. If they call my Father their Father, it is by the ſpirit of Adoption, Rom. 8 15. <hi>For ye have not received the Spirit of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage again to feare, but ye have received the ſpirit of Adoption, wherby we cry Abba Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> If mine groanes with ſighes and groanes with unſpeakable and unuttera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, it is by my Spirit of Sanctification. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26, 27. <hi>Likewiſe the Spirit alſo hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth our infirmities, for we know not what we
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41463:28"/> ſhould pray for as we ought, but the Spirit it ſelf make interceſſion for us, with groanings which cannot be uttered, and hee that ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the hearts knoweth what is the minde of the Spirit: becauſe he maketh interceſſion for the Saints according to the will of God.</hi> If mine are conſolated through conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is by Spirit of conſolation. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4, 5. <hi>who comforteth us in at our tribulation, that we may be able to comfort them that are in any trouble, by the comfort wherewith we our ſelves are comforted of God; for as the ſufferings of Chriſt abound in us, ſo our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation alſo aboundeth by Chriſt.</hi> Doe my people incounter with hell, ſinne, the law, death, the Devill and all evills with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my preſence? no, doe my people Navigate upon the mighty ſeas of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie, doe they ſaile over the vaſt Ocean of calamity without my aſſiſtance? no, I am not onely their Lord victorer to triumph over hell by heaven, over death by my life, over ſin by my blood, over the law by the law of the Spirit of life, over the fleſh by my ſpirit, over the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill by my death, over the world by my glorious and triumphous victorie, I am not onely their Lord acquirer of glory by relinquiſhing of my glory, of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41463:28"/> by fulfilling all righteouſneſſe, of peace by the peace of my croſſe, of love by the loſſe of the ſence of love, but I am there Lord conducter and leader to my heavenly glory. What morning ſtarre conducts them to reſt, but I the morning ſtarre? what ſonne of beauty leades them to the light of felicity, but I the ſonne of righteouſneſſe? I am the ſunne by day, and the cloud by night: I am the only captaine of my redeemed and purchaſed; I am the day ſtarre that alwais appeares in the hearts of mine; <hi>Therefore there is no condemnation to them which walke not after the fleſh but after the Spirit. Rom.</hi> 8.1.</p>
               <p>A ſweet Contemplation.</p>
               <p>Oh the depth of the ſweet love and mercy of my Lord that bought Mee! what no condemnation to me? No, I am waſhed in the blood of the lambe immaculate, I am preſented ſpotleſſe in ſpotleſſe robes, I am Redeemed from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the priſoners of no hope, I am united to the ſonne of God, and injoy communion with him. My ſoule who ſhall condemne thee? ſhall death, ſhall hell ſhall the law, ſhall the Devill, ſhall the world, ſhall the fleſh? no, for they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41463:29"/> are not in thy beloved; what though <hi>London England</hi> and the whole world band themſelves againſt thee, what though Legalliſts, the Angells of light, the world and all the rable of hell ſhall beſet thee on every ſide? what though the neareſt and them which ſhould be deareſt to thee, raiſe lies, ſlanders repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, rebukes, ignominies and all evills againſt thee? yet be not diſmayed; for there is no condemnation to them who are in Chriſt; Now thy thoughts ſhall be continually upon thy free redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thy rich juſtification, thy ſollid ſanctification, thy glorious Adoption, thy wonderfull union, and thy eternall glorification; now thy ſpirit is full of love, of praiſe, of glory; ſaying with the Apoſtle, Rom. 8.1, 2. <hi>Now then there is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Ieſus, who walke not after the fleſh but after the ſpirit. For the law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Ieſus, hath made mee free from the law of ſinne and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Philoſopher ſaith, there is a hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and ſecret vertue in the ſtarres and planets; not in conſonant to Scripture: canſt thou reſtraine the ſweet influences of Pleiades? And that there is a hidden
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41463:29"/> vertue in gemms and pretious jewells that none can underſtand but thoſe that are skilfull lapidaries: So there is a hidden and incloſed excellency in Chriſt the Lord of life and Prince of glory, and who can reſtraine the influences of his goodneſſe? or who can underſtand the richnes of his love, but thoſe who have knowne him by experience, who can ſpeake of the glorious robes of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, but thoſe that are cloathed with the glorious robes of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? who can make mention of the rareneſſe of Adoption, but thoſe who have obtained inheritance immortall and immarceſſable? or who can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare concerning the liberty of grace and glory, but thoſe that have acceſſe to the throne of grace by the ſpirit of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? hence came the rare experience the bleſſed Apoſtle found in and through the hand of the Mediator, who delivered him from the law of ſinne and death by the glorious and indiſſoluble Law of life according to the Text. Rom. 8. 2. <hi>For the law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Ieſus, hath made me free from the law of ſinne and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The law in Scripture is taken ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall waies.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:41463:30"/>
               <p>Firſt, Sometimes for the rule of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and peace, becauſe from it the Saints injoy Mercy from the bowels of mercy in God the Father, &amp; from Jeſus Chriſt Mediatour of the Law or Covenant. Gal. 6.16. <hi>As many as walke according to this rule, peace be unto them and mercy, and upon the Iſrael of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, ſometimes it is taken for the law of faith, ſith in and by that wee doe not onely beleeve the pardon of ſins through the blood of Chriſt, the non Recordation of iniquity through the mercy of the Father, and the free injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God to be our God and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father in that Covenant of life peace and Adoption, but alſo becauſe that we by that Covenant are under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Father, the mind and will of the Lord Chriſt the gratious media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of the law of life &amp; reconciliation. Rom. 3.27. <hi>Where is boaſting? excluded, by the law of workes, nay, but by the law of faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Sometimes it is called the New Teſtament, not onely in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the old; but becauſe the Father of deareſt mercies hath beene pleaſed to reveale and teſtifie a more full fruition
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41463:30"/> and Communion of his love in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion or condonation of iniquity in the blood of his deare Sonne, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.20. <hi>Likewiſe alſo he tooke the Cup after Supper, ſaying, this Cup is the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in my blood which is ſhed for you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Sometimes it is tearmed the new Covenant, to denote that high dignity, great Prerogative and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full priviledge that is given to them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Covenant: ſith, in this he becomes their God and bountifull Father, Remembreth their iniquities no more, Writes his law in their hearts, And teacheth them the high and deepe truths of the Goſpel. <hi>Jeremiah.</hi> 31.31, 32, 33, 34. <hi>Behold the dayes come ſaith the Lord, I will make a new Covenant with the houſe of Iſrael, and with the houſe of Judah, Not according to the Covenant that I made with their Fathers, in the day that I took them by the hand to bring them out of the land of Egypt, which my Covenant they breake, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I was an husband unto them ſaith the Lord. But this ſhal be the Covenant that I will make with the houſe of Iſrael after thoſe dayes ſaith the Lord, I will put my law in their inward parts, and write it in their hearts: and will be their God and they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41463:31"/> ſhall be my people. And they ſhall teach no more every man his neighbour, and every man his Brother, ſaying, know the Lord. For they ſhall all know me, from the leaſt of them unto the greateſt of them: ſaith the Lord, for I will forgive their iniquities, and I will remember their ſin no more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, Sometimes the everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, ſith God, doth not only become our God and Father; But our God and Father to eternity. Not only forgiving and pardoning ſinne, but forgiving and pardoning ſinne and iniquitie for ever and evermore: Not only writing the law of life and love in the hearts of his people, but he Characters it in their hearts by a Character that cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leted or extinguiſhed. <hi>Iſay</hi> 55.3. <hi>Incline your eare and come unto me, heare, and your ſoule ſhall live. And I will make an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant with you, even the ſure mercies of David. Iſaiah</hi> 54.10. <hi>For the Mountains ſhall depart, and the Hills ſhall be removed, But my kindneſſe ſhall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from thee, neither ſhall the Covenant of my peace be removed, ſaith the Lord that hath mercy on thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixtly, And in the text it is called the law of the Spirit of life.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:41463:31"/>1. Not only becauſe it gives eternall life to the ſonnes of Adoption.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe that it frees the ſonnes by Adoption from the Law of ſinne and death: But alſo becauſe it is eſtabliſhed in the hand and breaſt of the Lord of life. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. <hi>For the Law of the Spirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus hath made me free from the Law of ſinne and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 Why is it termed the Law?</p>
               <p n="1">1. To anſwer, The truth of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie which hath beene delivered by the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 2.3. <hi>And the people ſhall ſay, come yee, and let us goe up to the Mountaine of the Lord, to the houſe of the God of Jacob: and he will teach us of his waies, and wee will walke in his pathes. For out of Sion ſhall goe forth the Law, and the word of the Lord from Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. To diſtinguiſh it from the Law of Nature, The Law Ceremoniall and the Law Morrall. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33. <hi>But this ſhall be the Covenant that I will make with the houſe of Iſrael after thoſe daies ſaith the Lord, I will put my Law in their inward parts, and write it in their hearts, and will be their God, and they ſhall be my People.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Metaphorically or Reſpectively, as the Lawes in France are not the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41463:32"/> Lawes of Spaine, nor the Lawes of Spaine, the Lawes of England: So the Law of the ſpirit of life is not the Law of Sinne and Death.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To denote that although the Saints are not under the Law of accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, arraignment, execution, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation: Nevertheleſſe they are un-the Law of grace, Faith, Peace, Mercy and Reconciliation. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14. <hi>For ſinne ſhall not have dominion over you, for yee are not under the Law but under grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Why the Law of the Spirit.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Becauſe the Spirit reveales it. <hi>John</hi> 15.14. <hi>He ſhall glorifie me, becauſe he ſhall receive of mine and declare it to you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Becauſe the Spirit of God ingraves it in the hearts of all thoſe that are in Covenant with the Father and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, whom he hath ſent.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Becauſe the promiſe of the Law or Covenant is conſonant to the fruits and workings of the Spirit of life and glory. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. <hi>But the Fruits of the Spirit is Love, Joy, Peace, Longſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, Gentleneſſe, Goodneſſe, Faith, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Temperance, againſt ſuch there is no Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Why in Chriſt Jeſus? Not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41463:32"/> without grave conſideration.</p>
               <p>Firſt, If all heavenly divine and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent bleſſings are in Chriſt Jeſus, then the Covenant or Law of life is in Chriſt Jeſus: but all heavenly divine and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent bleſſings are in Chriſt Jeſus, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Covenant or Law of life is in Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Bleſſed be the God and Fatther of our Lord Jeſus, who hath bleſſed us with all ſpirituall bleſſings in heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. <hi>But of him are yee in Chriſt Jeſus, who of God is made unto us Wiſedome, and Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eouſneſſe, and Sanctification, and Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Is wiſedome without him that is the treaſure of wiſedome? No: Is Righteouſneſſe without the Lord of Righteouſneſſe? No: Is Redemption without our bleſſed and moſt gratious Redeemer? No: Is Sanctification with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him that Sanctifieth his by his blood moſt deare? No: Or is the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace and life without the Lord of life? No: In man there is not only the excellency of memory, the rareneſſe of affection, but alſo the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of underſtanding: in the Sunne there is not only beauty, ſplendor, but rareneſſe of efficacie: So there is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41463:33"/> Redemption, Juſtice, Sanctification, and Wiſedome: But alſo the Covenant and Law of life and mercy.</p>
               <p>Secondly, This Covenant or Law is eſtabliſhed by the death of Chriſt Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator: Therefore it is meet and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient that it ſhould be in Chriſt Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, <hi>Heh.</hi> 9.15. <hi>And for this cauſe hee is Mediatour of the New Covenant or Testament, that by meanes of death for the Redemption of the tranſgreſſions that were under the firſt Teſtament, they which are called might receive the the promiſe of eternall inheritance. Heb.</hi> 12.24. <hi>And to Jeſus the Mediatour of the new Covenant, and to the blood of ſprinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: which ſpeaketh better things then that of Abell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Becauſe that he hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed all that the Morrall Law requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, the Morrall Law required of thee, abſolute compleat and intire Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, it demands of thee exact per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and ſtrickt obedience, it binds thee over that thou ſhalt not ſpeake one word before the barre of Juſtice, that thou ſhoote no arrow below the glory of God, &amp; that thou anſwers eternall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite &amp; equall commands of the Father,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41463:33"/> but thou art come too ſhort of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, thy obedience is not anſwerable to his requires, and thy arrowes are on this ſide the throne of grace and mercy: but the Lord Chriſt became the ſurety, he hath payed all thy debts; though more in number then the ſand upon the Sea ſhore, he hath borne the ſence of anger, of wrath, of heate and juſtice, when thou ſtoodeſt quivering before the barre of juſtice then he anſwered for thee. When Angels ſtood wiſt and ſilent, ſith they could not beare the heate of everlaſting burning, nor anſwer the ſeverity and and purity of infinite and eternall Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, when men were whiſt and ſilent, ſith they were involved in their blood, clothed in old rotten raggs of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe: and could not anſwer the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and Righteouſneſſe of the God of Righteouſneſſe: when all Creatures might give in their voice we have Gold, Silver, Braſſe, Tinne, Lead and Iron: We have Pearles, Jewels, and rare Treaſures; the beautifull Diamonds, the coſtly Rubies, and the richeſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phirs, Yet all theſe cannot redeeme one from the Pitt, Juſtifie one in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, bring one to the riches of Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41463:34"/> or to anſwer thy exact demands or requires: but we all confeſſe the truth of him as it is written of him; and not of us. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 40.7, 8. <hi>Then ſaid I loe I come, in the volume of thy booke it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of me: I delight to doe thy will O God; yea thy law is within my heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, It hath beene expedient that the Law of life ſhould be placed in the Lord of Life: as the old Covenant or the law of Death was placed in the Loines of Adam. It was not convenient that the Law of Faith ſhould be in the Children of Incredulitie, that the Law of love and mercy ſhould be in the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Wrath and Furie, that the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament of life and Reconciliation ſhould be in the Sonnes of Death and Condemnation: had this Covenant beene made with us; as the old Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was made with Adam, we had broken this Covenant as well as Adam. Therefore ſuch hath beene the eternall wiſedome of the Father to eſtabliſh the Covenant in Chriſt ſith he was the ſonne of Mercy, the ſonne of Love, the ſonne of Grace and Bountie: He was he that was able to make us at once with the Father, to naile our ſinnes to the Croſſe,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41463:34"/> to burie them in his grave, to caſt our ſinnes into the Sea of Oblivion, he was he that was able being the mind of the Father to reveale the mind of the father: being the ſonne of the boſome, to make knowne what hath beene in his Fathers boſome, being the treaſures of wiſedome, to manifeſt hidden Knowledge and Wiſedome. Hence the Law of the Spirit of life is ſaid to be in Chriſt, and not in us according to the Text. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. <hi>For the Law of the Spirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus, hath made me free from the Law of ſinne and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, Why freed Me? not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of manifeſtation to the Churches of Chriſt, that he had intereſt in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and Redemption by Jeſus Chriſt, but alſo that he might have great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolaion in the midſt of all ſorrowes and tribulations, as if he had ſaid, though the Law hath made Warre againſt me, hath ſlaine me, hath found me polluted, ſinfull, and defiled: and made me cry out who ſhall deliver me from the body of this death, notwithſtanding, from that I am reſcued and delivered accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the text. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. <hi>For the Law
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41463:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Ieſus, hath made me free from the Law of ſinne and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why ſaith hee from the law of ſinne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>? ſome underſtand this to bee law ceremoniall, but I underſtand this to bee the law morrall; that it is not proper to call the law ceremoniall, the law of ſinne and death, I prove it thus.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That which was the only cauſe of death to the Beaſts, and the figurative impoſition upon them to ſignifie eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life to the redeemed and reconciled, that is not properly called the law of ſin and death to us, but the law ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all was the onely cauſe of death to the beaſts, and the figurative impoſition to ſignifie eternall life to them that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled and Redeemed. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, That which by the Holy Ghoſt is not called the law of ſinne and death, is not the law of ſinne and death, but the holy Ghoſt hath not called the law ceremoniall the law of ſinne and death; therefore it is not the law of ſin nor death: The Holy Ghoſt hath at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed this to the morrall law. Rom. 7.11. <hi>For ſinne taking occaſion by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement deceived me, and by it ſlew mee. Rom.</hi> 3.20, 21. <hi>Therefore by the deeds of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41463:35"/> the law there ſhall no fleſh bee juſtified in his ſight, for by the law is the knowledge of ſinne, but not the righteouſneſſe of God without the law is manifeſt, being witneſſed by the law and the Prophets.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55, 56. <hi>O death where is thy ſting? O grave where is thy victory? the ſting of death is ſinne, and the ſtrength of ſinne is the law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That law which figures out eternall life, Redemption &amp; reconciliation, that cannot bee the law of ſinne and death, but the law ceremoniall figured out eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life Redemption and reconciliation, therefore that cannot bee the law of ſin and death, the ground is this, becauſe the figure really anſwereth to the thing figured, the end of Heave offerings, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified the exaltation of our Lord upon the Croſſe, the peace offerings, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation by Chriſt in the day of his Croſſe, the burnt offerings, the ſatsfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the juſtice of the Father, to witt, the appeaſement of wrath in the time of his croſſe; If I ſhould ſpeake of the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubims, they ſignifie nothing elſe but mercy, in that they were covered with gold deſignes the riches of Chriſt, in that they ſpread their wings one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another, denotes the faith of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41463:36"/> Saints towards the throne of grace and mercy, in that the mercy ſeate was pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced above the arke of preſence, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies that Chriſt the Lord of life and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is exalted above all things, and that his preſence extends it ſelfe to his pooreſt and meaneſt ſervants, in that God anſwered from the mercy ſeat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Cherubims m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes knowne to the Saints Adopted, that they are to receive anſwer of prayers from the breaſt of Chriſt to their poore ſoules.</p>
               <p>The Law.</p>
               <p>The gleanings of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> was better then the vintage of <hi>Abiezer,</hi> the law of life and reconciliation, is better then the law of death and condemnation, the one accuſeth before the barre of Juſtice, the other excuſes before the thron of grace, the one arraignes before the throne of Gods tribunall, the other acquits before the mercy ſeate, the one condemnes the ſoule and conſcience of ſinne, iniquity, and tranſgreſſion, the other frees the ſoule from ſinne, iniquity, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion; the one is the cauſe of curſe and execration, the other the cauſe of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41463:36"/> bliſſe and benediction; the one affrights, amazeth, and conſternateth, the other comforteth, refreſheth and conſolates: one made the children of Iſrael flee from mount <hi>Sina,</hi> the other makes us approach neare to Mount <hi>Sion. Heb.</hi> 12. 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24. <hi>For ye are not come to the mountaine that might be touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that burned with fire, not unto black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and darkeneſſe, and tempeſt; which voyce they that heard, intreated that the word ſhould not be ſpoken to them any more, for they could not indure that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; and if ſo much as a beast touch the mountaine it ſhalbe ſtoned or thruſt through with a dart: And ſo terrible was the ſight, that Moſes ſaid, I exceedingly feare and tremble: But ye are come unto Mount Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and unto the City of the living God, and heavenly Ieruſalem, and to an innumerable company of Angels, to the generall aſſembly, and Church of the firſt borne, which are written in heaven, and God the judge of all, and to ſpirits of juſt men made perfect: and to Ieſus the Mediatour of the new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and to the blood of ſprinkling that ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth better things then that of Abell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O ye priſoners of hope, weigh, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and ponder, whether the Law of ſinne and death, is like to the law of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41463:37"/> peace and life, hath it revealed redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to bondmen? Adoption to ſlaves of hell and children of the devill? re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation to thoſe that ſhooke and quivered in my preſence? juſtification to thoſe that were found unrighteous in my ſight? ſanctification to thoſe who have beene unholy before me? and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification to thoſe that were ſhut out from the bleſſed fruition and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of my Kingdome? what mention hath it made of the death of the Lord of life, and the incomparableneſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, of the blood of my dearely beloved ſonne, and the richneſſe thereof; of the croſſe of the prince of glory, and the conqueſt thereof? If I ſpeake of reſt to my reſtleſſe priſoners, it is by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of Adoption, If I ſpeake of peace to Captives, it is by my word of reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; If I ſpeake of grace to them that are bound in the black chaines of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, it is by my meſſage of grace and &amp; ſalvation. Is the voyce of my ſervant <hi>Moſes,</hi> like the voyce of my beloved ſonne no, he was ſlow of ſpeech, my ſon is ſwift to deliver my minde of grace to my people, he was not eloquent, but my beloved he hath the rareſt ſentences of grace and bounty, <hi>Aaron</hi> his brother
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41463:37"/> ſpake for him to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> but my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved for all in matter of Mediation, and to al in the matter of reconciliation, hee was unwilling to ſpeake to and for my people, but my beloved hath beene willing to ſpeake for my choſen and Adopted. John 17.9. <hi>I pray for them, I pray not for the world, but for them which thou haſt given me. Heb.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Who in the dayes of his fleſh offered up prayers and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications with ſtrong crying and teares unto him that was able to ſave him from death, and was heard in that he feared.</hi> I gave to <hi>Moſes</hi> the law of terrours to terrifie them that are wilfull ſinners, the law of horror to ſmite a horror into them that are incorriggable tranſgreſſors, of ſevere equity to pronounce woe and miſerie to them that live in ſinne and iniquity; I have honoured my ſonne above my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. Heb. 3.5, 6. <hi>And Moſes verily was faithfull in all his houſe as a ſervant; for a teſtimony of thoſe things which were to bee ſpoken after, but Christ as a Sonne over his owne houſe, whoſe houſe are we, if wee hold faſt the confidence and the rejoycing of the hope firme unto the end. Heb.</hi> 5.5. <hi>So alſo Chriſt glorified not himſelfe to be made an high Priest, but he that ſaid to him, thou
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41463:38"/> art my ſon to day have I begotten thee.</hi> The Son by eternall generation is above the ſon by Adoption. I thought non worthy in heaven above, in the earth below, o under the earth worthy to deliver my minde, my will, my pleaſure to my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but him whom I have made king &amp; Lord over my people: there is none fit ot declare the words of eternall life, but the fountaine &amp; welſpring of life, the words of peace Attonement &amp; reconciliation; but he that by his blood hath purchaſed peace, attonement and reconciliation, the words of liberty, freedome and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, but hee that acquired by his death, liberty, freedome &amp; redemption. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 5.9.10. <hi>And they ſung a new ſong, ſaying, thou art worthy to take the booke, and to open the ſeales thereof, for thou waſt ſlaine, and haſt redeemed us to God by thy blood out of every kindred, &amp; tongue, &amp; people, &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and hath made us unto our God, Kings, and Prieſts, &amp; we ſhall raigne on the earth.</hi> The words of protection, juſtification and ſanctification by his death, blood and righteouſneſſe, ſith hee hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected his, juſtified them through righteouſneſſe, and ſanctified them tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough his words. John 17.17. hee hath
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41463:38"/> ſpoken of peace, that procured peace. John 14.26. <hi>But the comforter which is the holy Ghoſt, whom my Father will ſend in my name, he ſhall teach you all things, and bring all things to your remembrance, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever I ſaid unto you. Peace I leave with you, my peace I give unto you, not as the world giveth, give I it unto you, let not your hearts be troubled, neither let it be affraid.</hi> Words of life and victory, that obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned life and victory. Apoc. 1.18. <hi>I am he that liveth, and was dead, and behold I am alive for evermore, Amen; and I have the keyes of hell and death.</hi> Words of joy and conſolation, being the pretious ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and welſpring of conſolation. John 16.22. <hi>And ye now therfore have ſorrow, but I wil ſee you again, &amp; your heart ſhal rejoyce, &amp; your joy no man taketh from you.</hi> Who can ſpeake words of my gratious &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious preſence but <hi>Jmmanuell</hi> my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence? who can ſpeak words of life, but him that is the ſpring of eternall life, and Lord of life by conqueſt from the dead? or who can ſpeak words of liberty, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom &amp; redemption, but him that I have appointed to be the deliverer of my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? the Doctors have wondered at his ſentences, the people admired at his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41463:39"/> ſpeeches, &amp; the Churches delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was in the rarenſs of his voice. <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. the laſt <hi>His mouth is moſt ſweet, yea he is altogether lovely; this is my beloved, and this is my friend, O daughters of Ieruſalem!</hi> If he ſpeake from the throne of my grace and bounty, his words are onely grace and bounty; If hee ſpeake from the throne of mercy and pitty, he ſpeakes nothing but of grace and pitty: is it not thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded. Mat. 12.18, 19, 20. <hi>Behold my ſervant whom I have choſen, my beloved in whom my ſoule is well pleaſed; I will put my ſpirit upon him, and he ſhall ſhew judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto the, Gentiles: he ſhall not ſtrive, nor cry, neither ſhall my man heare his voice in the streets: a bruiſed reede ſhall hee not breake, and ſmoaking flax ſhalhe not quench, till he ſend forth judgement unto victory.</hi> His words are life to the lifeleſſe, grace to the graceleſſe, pitty to the pittileſſe, and truth to the hopeleſſe; his words are freedome to the bound, health to the ſick, healing to the wounded, binding to the broken, and riches to the pooreſt under heaven. The words of <hi>Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel</hi> were like the words of an Oracle. But the words of my beloved are Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles: his words ſurpaſſeth the words of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41463:39"/> 
                  <hi>Solomon,</hi> he ſpake of the nature of trees, of plants, of hearbs, and of all ſubluna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie things from the Cedar in <hi>Lebanon</hi> to the Hyſop upon the walls: The words of Chriſt are of grace, of mercy, of peace, of truth from the higheſt mercy to the deepeſt miſeries: all were happie that might ſtand at the footſteps of <hi>Solomon,</hi> to heare his wiſedome, but they are happie that may ſtand at the feet of Chriſt to heare the wiſedome of Chriſt; the Queene of <hi>Sheba</hi> came from the South to heare the wiſedome of <hi>Solomon;</hi> The Priſoners of Hope de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts from the barre of Juſtice to heare of the riches and glory of Chriſt; <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> was the wonder and admiration of the times becauſe of his wiſedome and diſcretion: Chriſt the wonder and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of his Churches becauſe of his ſpeeches and declaration. My ſoule, he that is thy peace, thy reſt, thy love, thy mercy; he ſhall be thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mander: he that is thy prince of glory, thy Lord of life, he is thy gratious protector, hee that is thy vine, thy head, &amp;c thy bridegroome, he ſhall be thy leader &amp; rule: for grace and peace came by him when the Law came by <hi>Moſes. Ioh.</hi> 1.17. Redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41463:40"/> and Reconciliation came by him when Condemnation adjudica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion came by Moſes, Conſolations com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts joyes and ſprings of ſolace came by him, when terrors, horrors, feares and ſervitude came by Moſes. Therefore thou ſhalt glory and expreſſe the praiſe of glory concerning the words of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and liberty. Rom. 8.2. <hi>For the law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Ieſus hath made me free from the law of ſinne and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The Law of the Spirit of life</p>
               <p>It hath beene ſaid of Paradiſe; that it was the rareſt place in the habitable world: in reſpect of Altitude, in reſpect of Amaenetie, in reſpect of Profunditude, and in reſpect of Jucunditie: the ſame may be ſpoken concerning the Spirit of life and glory; it is extolled in reſpect of Altitude, ſith it is in Chriſt who was placed in the high and heavenly places, of Amaenetie, ſith it is the delight of the beloved Saints and peculiar, of Profun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditude, ſith, it ſoundeth the loweſt and deepeſt miſery, of Jucunditie, ſith it makes the drooping ſoule moſt joyous and chearefull. Therefore the ſame that was the joy and glory of the bleſſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41463:40"/> is the joy and glory of the droo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping ſoule; joying and glorying in the words of the Apoſtle. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. <hi>For the Law of the Spirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus, hath made me free from the Law of ſinne and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Law of the Spirit of life. Pretious are the gifts and graces which come from the Father of everlaſting light, rare are the treaſures which come from the Lord of life and peace, rare and pretious is the Law of life which is from and of the law of the Spirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus. What is ſo jucundious? what is ſo amaenious? or what is ſo joyous? as the ſpirit of Adoption? which ſealeth the ſoule up to the day of eternall Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; or what can be ſo pleaſant, ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightſome or joyfull as the ſpirit that conſolates the ſoule in the midſt of all diſtreſſes? or what can be ſo rare, ſo wonderfull and admirable as the law of of the ſpirit of life? that frees us from the law of ſinne and death, the ſeale of the ſpirit doth rejoyce thee in the day of thy Adoption, the diſconſolated are conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated in the day of Conſolation, the wanting &amp; vacuous are filled with joys in the day of impletion, and the ſoule is
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41463:41"/> filled with all fulneſſe and ſweetneſſe in the day of liberation, hence comes in our joyfullneſſe and fullneſſe; that as we receive our peace from the Prince of peace, our righteouſneſſe from the Lord of righteouſneſſe; ſo we receive the law of life from the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. If thou haſt the revelation of the miſtery of the Kingdome it is by the ſpirit. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.11. <hi>He anſwered and ſaid unto them, becauſe it is given unto you to know the miſteries of the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but to them it is not given.</hi> If to thee is given to know the deep and profound things of God, it is by the ſpirit. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. <hi>But God hath revealed them unto us by his ſpirit, for the ſpirit ſearcheth all things, yea the deep things of God.</hi> If to thee is given to know the mind of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the world was, it is by the ſpirit. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.7. <hi>But to every one of us is given grace according to the gifts of Chriſt. Epheſ.</hi> 3.5. <hi>That to other Generations hath not been known to the ſonnes of men is now revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the Apostles and prophets by the ſpirit.</hi> So if there is a revelation of the miſtery of glory to Babes and Sucklings and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to the learned Doctors and Rabbies of the world it is by the ſpirit. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41463:41"/> 25.26.27. <hi>At that time Jeſus anſwered and ſaid, I thanke thee O Father Lord of Heaven and Earth, becauſe thou haſt hide theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and hast revealed them to Babes, even ſo Father for ſo ſeemed good to thy ſight. All things are delivered unto me of my Father, and no man knoweth the ſonne, but the Father, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knoweth any man the Father but the ſonne, and he to whom ſoever the ſonne will reveale him.</hi> None can write the law of God in the hearts of the Saints but the ſpirit of Chriſt, as none can ſeale to the Conſcience the everlaſting love of God the Father, and the precious treaſures of Jeſus Chriſt, but the ſpirit of glory: as none can give the ſpirit of oration to them that cannot pray, the ſpirit of conſolation, to them that ſit in mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning weeds but the ſpirit of Comfort: ſo none can write the mind of God in the conſcience, or the will of Chriſt in the ſpirit of the Saints, but the ſpirit of aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance or obſignation. Hence it is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Apoſtle. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Yee are our Epiſtles, written in our hearts, which is known and read of all men manifeſt to be the epiſtle of Christ, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame ſpirit that reveales unto
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41463:42"/> the Saints the unſearchable riches of Chriſt, that engraves the heavenly and gracious mind of the Father in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of the Redeemed; the ſame quickens the ſoule by the mighty power of life and vivification, when we lay dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes, when wee were troden in our bloods by the Horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Hell and Death, when we were involved in the depth of the gulfe of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, then by the ſame ſpirit of him who raiſed Jeſus from the dead, we were quickned, therefore not without cauſe is he called the ſpirit of life.</p>
               <p>Firſt, In the reſpect of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>Secondly, In reſpect of the life that the Saints receive through unio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, In reſpect of that life the Saints receive through Faith, Love, and hope by the ſpirit in the act of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
               <p>When our Lord was in the grave, neither hell, nor death, nor law, nor juſtice, nor all the force of the creature could retaine him: for he ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the Lord of life by riſing from the <hi>dead Apoc.</hi> 1.18. <hi>I am he that liveth and was dead, I am alive forever more, Amen, and have the keyes of Hell and death. Lord
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41463:42"/> over ſin by the blood of his croſſe. Col.</hi> 2.14.15 <hi>Blotting out the hand writing of ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which was againſt us, which was contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to us, and tooke it out of the way, nailing it to his croſſe, and having ſpoiled principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and powers, he made a ſhew of them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly, triumphing over them all.</hi> Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer over the Divill by the power of his death. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.24. <hi>For as much then as the children are partakers of fleſh and blood, he alſo himſelfe tooke part of the ſame, that through death he might deſtroy him that had the power of death; that is the Devill.</hi> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorer over the law and over all accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by his interceſſion. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33, 34. <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect? it is God that juſtifieth, who is it that condemneth? It is Chriſt that died, yea ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that is riſen againe; who is even at the right hand of God: who alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth interceſſion for us.</hi> Triumpher o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Captives, and leading captivitie captive by the power of his aſſention. It was impoſſible our Lord ſhould be retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the bonds of death, the barts of hell, and the power of the Devill: not only becauſe it hath beene the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate counſell of the Father, not to leave his ſoule in grave, nor ſuffer his holy one
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41463:43"/> to ſee corruption. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.27 <hi>Becauſe thou wilt not leave my ſoule in hell, neither wilt thou ſuffer thy holy one to ſee corruption.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of that pittie he had to his beloved Spouſe, his deareſt members, &amp; his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der branches; <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.6. <hi>And hath raiſed us up together, &amp; made us ſit together in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly places in Chriſt Jeſus, becauſe of the dignity of himſelfe, being King of his Church Lord of life, &amp; Mediatur of the Covenant Acts</hi> 2.24. <hi>Whom God hath raiſed up; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving glooſed the paines of death becauſe it was not poſſible he ſhould be houlden of it.</hi> But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo becauſe of the mighty and infinite power of the ſpirit of glory, which raiſ'd up our Lord of life &amp; Prince of glory. O my ſoule! conſider, conſider what the ſpirit of life hath done for thy foule! Had not our Lord been raiſed from the dead by the ſpirit of life; ſinne would have cruſht thy conſcience to the loweſt gulfe of miſery; the Devill like a roaring Lion would have devoured thee, the law of terrors would have bound thee to the barre of eternal juſtice to eternitie death would have delivered thee to the ſecond death forevermore, and all evills would have ceaſed upon thy ſpirit for ever and ever. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mighteſt thou have ſaid with
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41463:43"/> the Pſalmiſt, The ſorrowes of death had compaſſed thee, and the evills of hell had found thee, thou foundeſt woe and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row then mighteſt thou have ſpoken with <hi>Hezekiah;</hi> That thou waſt forſaken as a Shepards Tent, that juſtice would have beene as a Lion to breake all thy bones, thou mighteſt have mourned as a Dove, &amp; chattered as a Crain to the dayes of eternity. Saying That thou ſhould'ſt behold his gracious face no more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his gracious countenance no more, but remaine in everlaſting chaines un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der darkeneſſe for evermore.</p>
               <p>Shouldeſt thou have beene ſo happie as <hi>Jonah?</hi> no, he was but in the bellie of the Whale, but thou ſhouldeſt have beene in the bellie of hell, he was in the depth of the ſea, but thou ſhouldeſt have bee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the depth of the bottomleſſe pit, the waves of the ſea and the bellowes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of incompaſſed him, but the waves of greateſt ſorrowes and bellowes of excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding wrath ſhould have incompaſſed thee; he was heard out of the bellie of the Whale and his prayer came into his holy temple, but thy prayer ſhould have beene ſhut out from his glorious preſence and ſhould not have appeared
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:41463:44"/> before the throne of grace, a Goard was provided for him to hide his head from the heate of the Sunne, but no ſhelter nor ſhadow had bee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> provided for thee to hide thy ſoule fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> everlaſting burnings. Where had beene the glorying of the Saints, had our Lord not beene raiſed from the dead? we ſhould have had no cauſe to glory in the blood and death of his croſſe, no cauſe of triumphing in a glorious preſentation, in a hapy recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, in an abſolute abolition of the hand writings which were written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us. Where had been our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from death, and the feare thereof, from the grave and the ſting thereof, from out of the hands of the Devill, and and the ſlavery thereof, from the law and the execration thereof? where had been our royall Robes of Righteouſneſſe? our garments of glorious ſalvation &amp; juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his glorious preſencs? if the holy one had ſeen corruption: the branches of the rareſt vine ſhould have withered, the members to the head of pureſt gold would have periſhed, and the ſpouſes to our bleſſed and deareſt Bridegroome would have been clothed with ſhame &amp; reproah for ever. But bleſſed, thrice bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:41463:44"/> be that name is bleſſed forevermore, ſith, he hath raiſed the head and the members, the branches &amp; the vine, the bridegroome &amp; the ſpouſes together. He that left not our Lord in the grave hath not left the Redeemed of the Lord in the pitt of diſtruction, he that ſuffered not the ſonne of the boſome to ſee cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, will not ſuffer the ſonnes by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption to be ſwallowed up by ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting perdition. Therefore you ſonnes &amp; daughters of men, we will not only glory in Chriſts incarnation, in Chriſts crucifixtion, in his grave, buriall &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious aſſention, but alſo in his victorious &amp; triumphous Reſurrection. The riſſe of the ſon of righteouſneſſe is more to us then the ſun of morning light, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights the eye &amp; ſence of ſublunaries, this the ſoules of diſtreſſed conſciences: that cauſeth the hearbs, plants &amp; trees to riſe out of the earth, this cauſeth the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſpouſes &amp; members of Chriſt to riſe out of the loweſt pitt, that removeth darkneſſe &amp; bringeth in a light Diurnal, this removeth darkeneſſe &amp; bringeth in a light eternall. That is the plenitude a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, and the riches of the earth beneath, this is the riches of the Church Militant, and the plenitude of the Church Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:41463:45"/> Therfore will we glory in the ſpirit of life, according to the Text <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. <hi>For the law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus hath made me free from the law of ſinne and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſpirit of life.</p>
               <p>Sweet and pleaſant is the expreſſion of Job, Will the wilde Aſſe roare when he hath graſſe? or will the Oxe low when he hath fother? or will the dead ſoule mourne for life? when it hath the ſpirit of life? Noe, it will joy it ſelfe in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of joy, and conſolate it ſelfe in the ſpirit of conſolation, triumphing with the Apoſtle, becauſe the ſpirit of life hath freed it from the law of ſinne and death: according to the Text. Rom. 8.2. <hi>For he law of the ſpirit of Life<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in Chriſt Jeſus, hath made me free from the law of ſin and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, It is called the ſpirit of life, ſith that the ſpirit is the cauſe of union with the Lord Jeſus, by which the Saints receive both life ſpiritual and life eternall. My priſoners of Hope, and Bond men to the throne of mercy: know and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that it is not in your powers to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy union with me and Jeſus Chriſt whom I have ſent, the ſpot of your ſin,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:41463:45"/> the blott of your tranſgreſſions, and the impurity of your iniquities hath preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the exactneſſe, rigidneſſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of my law moſt pure hath hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the eternitie, the infinite and the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of my divine juſtice letteth. Could your darkeneſſe bring it ſelfe to my glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious light? I dwell in the light unacceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Who only hath immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, dwelling in the light whom no man hath ſeene, nor can ſee, to whom be honour, and power everlaſting amen.</hi> Can your im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity reach my infinite and eternall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity? I am a God that can behold no ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie. <hi>Haback.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Thou art of pu rer eyes then to behold evill, and canſt not looke on iniquitie; wherefore lookeſt thou upon them that deal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> trechearouſly, and holdeſt thy tongue when the wicked devoureth the man that is more righteous then he.</hi> Can thy death atting and touch my life &amp; being from eternitie to eternitie.</p>
               <p>I am alone the fountaine of living wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.13. <hi>For my people have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted two evills, they have forſaken me the fountaine of living waters, and hewed them out Ciſternes, broken Ciſternes that can hold no water.</hi> Or can your lowneſſe and profunditie: reach the highneſſe of my
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:41463:46"/> ſublimitie? I dwell in the high and the holy place. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 57.15. <hi>For thus ſaith the high and lofty one, that inhabiteth eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, whoſe name is holy; J dwell in the high and holy place, with him alſo that is of a contrite and humble ſpirit, to revive the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the humble, and to revive the heart of the contrite ones.</hi> Could Dives paſſe the gulfe of hell to the boſome of Abraham? No, can a bird without wings reach the hight of the ſunne? No, can a man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out eyes behold the higheſt orbs? No, or can thy ſoule that is involved in the law of horrid iniquitie unite it ſelfe to me? No, this way of union was not found in the habitable world, but in my habitation of glory: this was not found in the depths below, but in the heights a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove: this was not found in thy breaſts and invention, but in my breaſts of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly compaſſion: well ſaith the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>Man knoweth not the price thereof, neither is it found in the land of the living, the depth ſaith it is not in me, and the ſea ſaith it is not in me, God understandeth the way thereof, and he knoweth the place thereof.</hi> Therefore this was my wiſedome to give this Glory to my beloved ſonne, <hi>John</hi> 17 22. <hi>and the glory which thou gaveſt
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:41463:46"/> me, J have given them, that they may be one even as we are one.</hi> That by his blood he might make them which are afarre off nigh to me. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.13. <hi>But now in Chriſt Jeſus, yee who ſometimes were farre off, are made nigh by the blood of Chriſt.</hi> That by the death of his croſſe he might make of two one. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Having aboliſhed in his fleſh the enmitie, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the law of Commandements, contained in Ordinances, for to make in himſelfe of twain one new man: ſo making peace.</hi> And that he might bring them to me that never knew the riches of my grace. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.18. <hi>For through him we both have an acceſſe by one ſpirit unto the father.</hi> Untill I came to live in my people to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation &amp; dwelling place, till I made them habitations of glory for the ſpirit of my glory, they were as farre from me, as my dwelling place is from the loweſt hell, as the cleareſt light is from the greateſt darkeneſſe, and the barre of my Juſtice from the throne of mercy. But my ſpirit gives them a being in the heavenly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, my ſpirit removed all the letts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt me and my people, my ſpirit gives them to injoy a being reall in me and in the deareſt of my breaſt 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Paul
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41463:47"/> and Silvanus and Timotheus to the Church of Theſſalonica, which is in God the Father; and in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: grace be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, and peace from God our Father, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Hence all the branches, receive their life from the vine Chriſt Jeſus; hence alſo the members receive their vitall motion from their head Chriſt Jeſus, hence the ſpouſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth her being from the bridgroome Jeſus Chriſt through and by the ſpirit of life, therefore comes in the glorying and expreſſion of my people according to the text; <hi>For the law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt, hath made me free from the law of ſinne and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, becauſe of the life of Faith, and love, and hope which is given thee by the Spirit of life.</p>
               <p>It was not the ſhadow of <hi>Peter</hi> that healed the ſick and weake, but the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowing grace from the throne of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall mercy: it was not the handker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes and neckcloathes of <hi>Paul</hi> that drave out devills, but the omnipotent power of the eternall mediatour; it was not the water in Baptiſme that waſheth away ſinne, but the blood of Chriſt: ſo it hath not been in the purity &amp; ſtrength
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:41463:47"/> of the ſonnes of death to free themſelves from the Law of ſinne and death; but in the power of the law of life according to the text. Rom. 8.2. <hi>For the Law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Ieſus hath made me from the law of ſinne and death.</hi> You that have been Priſoners without hope, as by the blood of my Teſtament, I have ſent you out of the pit where there is no water, ſo by the law of my life I have freed you from the law of ſin &amp; death. I have made you to live the life of faith, when I hide my face, the light of my deareſt love and gratious countenance, when I covered my ſelfe with darkneſſe, and wrapt my ſelfe in a clowd; when I ſeemed to bid farrwell, as though I would ſee you no more, then I made you to live by faith which was in mee, when as my ſervant <hi>Ionas</hi> was in the depth of the Sea, in the gulfes beneath, invironed in the mighty waters, and in the bellie of the devouring whale, I made him to call upon my name, and to looke towards my holy Temple: when thou waſt in the depths of the ſea of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, in the ocean of miſerable iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, notwithſtanding I have made thee looke to the throne of my grace and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:41463:48"/> bounty, &amp; higheſt mercy: when I ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thee to be mocked, ſcoffed, derided, ſcorned, to be ſtoned, deprived of bread convenient, ſhutt out from amongſt the deareſt and neareſt friends, bringing thee to the gates of deepeſt miſeries, and to the priſon where thou ſhouldeſt have loſt thy liberty; notwithſtanding, I have made thee live by faith which is in mee, I have brought thy faith into Chriſt; there thou liveſt, there thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteſt, there thou reſteſt, there thou dwelleſt, there thou joyeſt, and there abideſt; as the ſeate of the Eagle is upon the rock undervaluing all inferiour pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſo thy habitation is in Chriſt the rocke of righteouſneſſe and thou under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valueſt all ſublunarie and inferiour things. As I have made the promiſes yea and Amen to the praiſe of my glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; ſo I have made thee to reſt upon thoſe promiſes to eternall glory. As I am becom thy moſt benignous and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Father in my Covenant to perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitie, ſo will I make thee live by love through my Covenant to Eternitie. If I have taken up my reſt, my content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, my acquieſcence and complacen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie through atonement: If I have filled
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:41463:48"/> the ſonne of my love with the treaſures of hidden wiſedome and ſcience, the treaſures of pure and unſpotted righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, it is becauſe thou mighteſt live by faith which is in me: at that time thou maieſt anſwer the words of my faithfull Apoſtle. Gal. 2.20. <hi>I am crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Chriſt, nevertheleſſe I live, yet not</hi> I, <hi>but Chriſt liveth in me, and the life which I now live in the fleſh, is by the faith of the ſonne of God, who loved me, and gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thou hadſt beene with <hi>Noah</hi> in the Arke, thou wouldeſt have lived above the waters. If with <hi>Daniel,</hi> in the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onsden, thou would'ſt have lived by the ſtrength of the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah.</hi> If with <hi>Shadrech, Meſhech</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bednego</hi> in the fierie furnace, thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt have lived by the fire of love and by my promiſe of deliverance out of the fire. Iſaiah 43.2. <hi>When thou paſſeſt tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the waters, I will bee with thee, and through the rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee, when thou walkeſt through the fire, thou ſhalt not bee burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee.</hi> Out of the eater comes meate, and out of the ſtrong comes ſweetneſſe: from love comes love to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:41463:49"/> Chriſt againe, <hi>We love him becauſe he loved vs firſt.</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.19. and out of the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt comes the pleaſantneſſe and ſweetneſſe of the Saints. Epheſ. 3.20.21. <hi>Now unto him that is able to doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly and abundantly above all we aske or thinke, according to the power that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in us, unto him be glory in the Church by Chriſt Jeſus throughout all ages world without end Amen.</hi> Hence they are filled with glorious expreſſions, expreſſing the love of Chriſt in their freedome and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration according to the text. Rom 8.2. <hi>For the law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Ieſus, hath made me free from the law of ſin and death.</hi> Till I appeard in the rare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of my love, thou lovedſt the vanities, the treaſures, the glory, the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and power of the Creature before me; till I powred out the ſavour of my ſweet oyntments, and cauſed my fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincence to ſmell in thy noſtrills, thou loveſt thy ſelf above me, till I let my fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers drop the myrhe, the ſweet diſtilling mirhe; thou ſatteſt at reſt and ſoughteſt not after me, but in the day of the effuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my ſweet oyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts I made thee love me. Cant. 1.2, 3. <hi>Let him kiſſe me with the kiſſes of his mohth, for his love is better then
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:41463:49"/> wine, becauſe of the ſavour of thy good oynt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments, thy name is as oyntment poured forth, therefore doe the virgins love thee:</hi> in the time of the diſtillations of my mithe, I made thee ſeeke after me. Cant. 5.4 5, 6. <hi>My beloved put in his hand into the hole of the doore, and my bowells were moved for him. I roſe up to open to my Beloved, and my hands dropped with Myrrh, and my fingers with ſweet ſmelling myrrh upon the handles of the locks. I opened unto my beloved, but my beloved had with-drawne himſelfe and was gone, my ſoule failed when he ſpake, I ſought him, but I could not finde him, I called him, but he gave me no anſwer.</hi> Aſſuredly thou didſt account of the treaſures of the mountaines, above the riches of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly places, the riches of the ſeas, above the riches of the ſea of ſure mercies, thou didſt value the riches of Kingdomes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the riches of my heavely kingdom, and thou didſt prize the earthly jewel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s above the jewell of jewells and the preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous jemmes, above the pretious ſtone, the foundation of my Redeemed, when my love appeared above women, then thou didſt love me above women; when my love appeared to thee above riches, treaſure, honours, kingdomes &amp; provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:41463:50"/> then thou lovedſt mee above King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and provinces, above riches, treaſures and honours, thou waſt not ſick of love till my love made thee ſicke of love. <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.8. <hi>I charge you O daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Ieruſalem, if ye finde my beloved, tell him that I am ſicke of love.</hi> Thou waſt not overpowred with the overpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of my Love, till I overpowred thee with my pretious love; can the waters from below water the fruitfull and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren ſoile without me? or can the raine droppe ſhowers from the clouds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out me? or can the ſoule have the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowings of love without my ſpirit? no. Rom. 5.5. <hi>And hope maketh not aſhamed becauſe the love of God is ſhed abroad in our hearts by the Holy Ghoſt, which is given unto us.</hi> Canſt thou know that ſupereminent love of my ſonne without I ſhew my grace ſupereminent? no. Epheſ. 2.6, 7. <hi>And hath raiſed us up together, and made us ſit together in heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus; that in the ages to come, he might ſhew forth the exceeding riches of his grace, in his kindneſſe towards us through Chriſt Jeſus. Epheſ.</hi> 3.19. <hi>And to know the love of Chriſt, which paſſeth knowledge, that ye might be filled with all the fulneſs of God.</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:41463:50"/> Or couldeſt thou have known the height, the depth, the length or breadth of my deareſt faviour without my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit? No, <hi>Epheſ</hi> 3.16.17, 18. <hi>That he would give you according to the riches of his glory, to be ſtrenghened with might by his ſpirit in the inner man: that Christ may dwell in your hearts by faith that yee being rooted and grounded in love, may be able to comprehend with all ſaints, what is the breadth, and length, and depth and height, and to know the love of Chriſt which paſſeth knowledge.</hi> Hence thy experience wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, that the ſpirit of life is thy life of love and freedome. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. <hi>For the law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus, hath made thee free from the law of ſinne and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is the light of the Candle to the light of the Moone? or the light of of the Moone to the light of the ſonne? or what is the light of the Sunne to Chriſt the ſonne of glorious righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? when by the light of his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous countenance he ſhines upon the ſoule by giving to it the life of faith in God. <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. <hi>To open their eyes, and to turne them from darkeneſſe to light, and from the power of Satan to God, that they
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:41463:51"/> may receive the forgiveneſſe of ſinnes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance amongſt them which are ſanctified, through faith that is in me.</hi> The life of love in Chriſt. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Wherefore I alſo after I heard of your faith in the Lord Jeſus, and love unto all the ſaints.</hi> And the life of hope in the promiſe. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. <hi>For all the promiſes of God in him are yea, and in him Amen: nuto the glory of God by us. Heb.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Now faith is the ſubſtance of things hoped for, and the evidence of things not ſeene.</hi> Hence we glory not only in the ſpirit of life but in the law of the ſpirit of life. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. <hi>For the law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus, hath made me free from the law of ſinne and death.</hi> I gave to thee the life of faith, faith is my guift. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.10.8. <hi>For we are his workemanſhip crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Jeſus Christ unto good workes, which God hath before ordained, that we ſhould walke in them. For by grace are yee ſaved through faith, and that not of your ſelves: it is the gift of God.</hi> I gave to thee the life of love, when I gave the ſonne of love. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16. <hi>for God ſo loved the world that he gave his only begotten ſonne, that whoſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveth one him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting lif.</hi> I gave to thee the life of hope, when I gave to thee the lively hope through the reſurrection from the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:41463:51"/> dead 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Bleſſed be God &amp; the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which according to his abundance mercy, hath begotten us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to a lively hope, by the reſurection of Jeſus Chriſt from the dead.</hi> When I have made mine to walke in ſheepe skins, and Goates skins in dennes and caves of the earth for my names ſake, I gave them hope of everlaſting righteouſneſſe raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by grace unto eternall life. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. laſt. <hi>For as ſinne hath raigned unto death, even ſo might grace raigne through righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe unto eternall life by Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> When I gave them neither favour Love, nor Footſteps in or amongſt the Creature, I have given to them a Citie whoſe maker and builder is my ſelfe. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.16. <hi>But now they deſire a bettter Country, that is an heavenly; wherefore God is not aſhamed to be called their God, for he hath prepared for them a Citie.</hi> When I made them undergoe Shipwracks, Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, Defamie, Reproach, Diſdaine, Contempt, Malice, Wrath, Envie, Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitings, Slanderings, Scornings, by them that under the profeſſion of my praiſe and glory; are enemies to the throne of my praiſe and glory. I gave them hope in the eternall waight of my
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:41463:52"/> glory. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17.18. <hi>For our light afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whcih is but for a moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding &amp; eternal waight of glory, while we looke not one things that are ſeen, but one things that are not ſeen, for the things which are ſeene are tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, but the things which are not ſeen are eternall.</hi> Hence they expect a new hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven &amp; a new earth, in which is righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. <hi>We waite for a new hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and a new earth, in which is Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> Hence they expect the light of my preſence, and pleaſures for evermore <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 16. laſt. <hi>Thou wilt ſhew me the path of life, in thy preſence is fullneſſe of joy, at thy right hand there are pleaſures for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi> Hence they looke for the Crowne of glory, the Crowne of life, and the Crowne of righteouſneſſe. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Hence forth is laid up for me a Crowne of righteouſneſſe, which the Lord the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Iudge ſhall give me at that day, and not to me only, but unto them alſo, that love his appearing.</hi> And not without cauſe, ſith I have not only given unto them my oath and promiſe, but the law of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of my life to free them from the law of ſin and death. Heb. 6.18, 19. <hi>That by two immutable things in which
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:41463:52"/> it was impoſſible for God to lye, we might have a ſtrong conſolation, who have fled for refuge to lay hold upon the hope ſet before us. Which hope wee have as an Ancor of the ſoule, both ſure and ſtedfaſt, and which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth into that within the vaile. Rom.</hi> 8.2. <hi>For the law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus hath freed them from the law of ſin &amp; detah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Father hath given to Chriſt the higheſt ſublimitie, and ſhall I ceaſe to mention ſo great a dignity? as the pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſentence to conceiveme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is miſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, ſo Chriſts kingly dignitie is unutte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, though the rationalls cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Sun with full ſpectation, yet the Sun muſt not hinder them from behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, though of Chriſt the Lord of life we make no full dimention, yet the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of the law of life muſt not hinder us from declaring; hence admirable hath beene the expreſſion of life from the law of life, ſith by that wee are freed from the law of ſinne and death. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. <hi>For the law of the Spirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus, hath made us free from the law of ſinne and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:41463:53"/>
               <p>The law of the Spirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>It was ſaid of <hi>Jonathan</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> that they were lovely and amiable in their lifes, &amp; were not devided in their deaths. It may be ſaid of Chriſt that he was A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable &amp; lovely being the Lord of life, and that his love was not ſeperated from his death; for in his death he aboliſhed ſinne totally, overcame the divell victoriouſly, and ſtopped the mouth of the accuſing law wonderfully, in his life we injoy eternall life, a life ſpirituall in the heavenly places. Rom. 8.2. <hi>For the law of the ſpirit of life in Christ Jeſus hath made us free from the law of ſinne and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The rareneſſe or pretiouſneſſe of the covenant conſiſts in three things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, In the freeneſſe of the Covenant.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in the eternity of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, in the place or collocation of the Covenant.</p>
               <p>The rareneſſe of this Covenant or law of life in Chriſt is in that it is a free covenant or law of life in Chriſt: The effects of my covenant are free, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:41463:53"/> a God freely to mine in covenant. What beauty? what glory? what ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor? what righteouſneſſe? what holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? what performances have I ſeene in them? the beſt of their righteouſnes were menſtruous cloathes and defiled garments. Iſa. 64 6. <hi>But wee are all as an uncleane thing, and all our righteouſneſſe are as filthy ragges, and we all doe fade as a leafe, and our iniquities like the winde have taken us away.</hi> The pureſt of their robes are no better then rattered raggs of the old <hi>Adam,</hi> the rareſt of their purities, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purities, of their righteouſnes, unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and of their godlineſſe, ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe. It was I that waſhed them from their blood in the bloud of my deare ſonne, when they were involved in their blood. Apo. 1.5. <hi>And from Jeſus Christ who is the faithfull witneſſe, and the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of the dead, &amp; the prince of the Kings of the earth, unto him that hath loved us, and waſhed us from our ſinnes in his owne blood.</hi> It was I that cloathed them in the robes of pure righteouſneſſe, when they were caſt out naked to the ſhame of their faces. Ezek. 16.8. <hi>Now when I paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by thee, and looked upon thee, behold thy time was the time of love, and I ſpread my
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:41463:54"/> skirt over thee, and covered thy nakedneſſe, yea I ſweare unto thee, and entred into a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with thee ſaith the Lord God, and thou becameſt mine.</hi> It was I that looked upon mine in the daies of ſhame and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, when neither men nor Angells did regard them. Eze. 16.5.6. <hi>No eye pittied thee to doe any of theſe unto thee, to have compaſſion upon thee, but thou waſt caſt out in the open field to the loathing of thy perſon in the day that thou waſt borne: and when I paſſed by thee, and ſaw thee polluted in thine owne blood, yea I ſaid unto thee when thou waſt in thy blood live;</hi> Had they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained mercy, before I by mercy became their God &amp; Father by covenant? No, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2. <hi>the laſt. And I will ſow her unto me in the earth, and I will have mercy upon her that had not obtained mercy, and I will ſay to them which were not my people, thou art my people, and they ſhall ſay thou art my God,</hi> Were they my people before I ſaid they ſhall be my people? No. Rom. 9.25, 26, <hi>As he ſaith alſo in Oſea, I will call them my people, which were not my people, and her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved which was not beloved, &amp; it ſhall come to paſſe that in the place where it was ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them ye were not my people, there they ſhall be called the Children of the living God.</hi> Or
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:41463:54"/> were they eſpouſed to me for ever, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I eſpouſed them to me for ever. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.19. <hi>And I will betroth thee unto mee in righeouſneſſe, and judgement, and in loving kindneſſe, and in mercy.</hi> Let mine behold the freeneſſe of my love in the pardon of ſinne through the Covenant of grace and mercy. If I had not pardoned their ſinnes, had I not caſt them out of my preſence as I caſt <hi>Adam</hi> out of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe? Had I not caſt them out from the communion of my glory of bleſſednes, as I caſt out my Angells from the fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my glory and happineſſe? Had I not cauſed hell to ſwallow them as the earth did <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram?</hi> when all the fountaines were ſhut, I ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to them a pretious fountaine in the ſides of my deareſt Sonne. I gave the blood of the moſt pure, ſpotleſſe, and undefiled, without ſpot, wrinckle, and unſtained, incomparable, ineſtimable and unutterable, though I judge the worth of his bloud above the worth of a Thouſand worlds, above the price of ten thouſand jewells, above the riches of all the celeſtiall wights, yet I gave that for mine, that they by that might bee clenſed, and I might ſee ſinne no more,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:41463:55"/> that they by that might be re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onciled, and I might remember ſinne no more, hence have I blotted out their ſins &amp; ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities as the thickeſt cloud. Iſay 44.22. <hi>I have blotted as a thick cloud thy tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and as a cloud thy ſins, returne unto me, for I have redeemed thee.</hi> Hence I deleted their tranſgreſſions for my names ſake. Iſay 43.25. <hi>I, even I am he, that blotteth out thy tranſgreſſions for my owne ſake, and I will not remember thy ſinnes.</hi> Hence I caſt all their ſins into the bottom of the ſea. <hi>Micah</hi> 7.18.19. <hi>Who is a God like unto thee, that pardoneth iniquity, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſeth by the tranſgreſſion of the remnant of his heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, he retaineth not his anger for ever, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he delighteth in m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rcy? he will turne againe, he will have compaſſion upon us, hee will ſubdue our iniquities, and thou wilt caſt all their ſinnes into the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th of the Sea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In my Covenant of free grace I have given Chriſt to be mediatour, what is more pretious the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gold? or what is more excellent then light? or what is of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter value then his interceſſion in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of my redeemed Is it a ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the ſon of a King to mediate in the behalfe of trayterous and rebellious ſubjects? or it is a ſmall matter that hee
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:41463:55"/> that is King of Kings ſhould become mediator in the behalfe of poore diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſinres? As I have commended my higheſt love that hee ſhould ſhed his blood for ſinfull wretches. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8. <hi>But God commendeth his love towards us, in that while we were yet ſinners, Chriſt dyed for us.</hi> So I have commended my deareſt love that hee ſhould be mediatour for wofull tranſgreſſions. 1 Tim. 2.5. <hi>For there is one God and one Mediatour betweene God and man, the man Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Whilſt neither Angells Cherubins nor celeſtiall wights were able to preſent my people one how er ſpotleſſe in my ſight &amp; pure preſence, he is able to the dayes of eternity to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent all the priſoners of my hope intire before the light of my countenance, for he hath waſhed them in his blood moſt pure &amp; undefiled. He hath ſet them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mee in the heavenly places, &amp; they are in his breſt without ſpot preſented, I can behold none but the ſon of my love, being the God &amp; father of love. I can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold none but the Lord of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſith I am the God and Father of Righteouſnes: when I looke upon him who was my delight before the world was, how can I chuſe but delight in them
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:41463:56"/> who were ſons of wrath and children of the devill. When I caſt mine eye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him that was the Complacencie of my breaſt &amp; boſome, I cannot chuſe but have effection towards them who have beene diſtant from my boſom. Whilſt I fixe mine eye upon the mediatour of the Covenant, I will not hearken to the clamours of the world, the roarings of the devill, the accuſations of the Law, the terrors and complaints of the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, nor to any evills whatſoever. I will alone hearken to his plea and Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, (he ſaith) my death is ſufficient to redeeme and ranſome mine from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall death, my bloud incomparable to remove all iniquities, my paſſion able to remove thy terrible indignation, had I not made a full and intire reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, had I not obtained the throne of grace and mercy, had I left either ſinne, ſpot, wrinckle, ſtaine, blemiſh, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filement unremoved, had not the value of my blood beene above all bloods, the worth of my death above all deaths, and price of Atonement above all Atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then thy wrath, thy furie, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation might have broken out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my choſen as the inundation of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:41463:56"/> the mighty waters, but now I know thou loveſt mine, whom I have purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and delighteſt in mine whom I have ranſomed. My mediation ſurpaſſeth the mediation of <hi>Aaron,</hi> that was the ſonne of man, this by me the ſonne of God, hence I ſit at the right hand of God to make interceſſion for mine. Rom. 8.34. <hi>Who is he that condemneth, it is Chriſt that dyed, yea rather that is riſen againe, who is even at the right hand of God, who alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth interceſſion for us. Aaron</hi> entred into the holy of holieſt below, but I enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the holy of holieſt into the heavenly places. Heb. 9.24. <hi>But Chriſt is not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the holy places made with hands, which are the figures of the true, but into heaven it ſelfe, now to appeare in the preſence of God for us. Aaron</hi> was annoynted with oyle made with the confection of the Apothicary, but I was annoynted with the oyle of gladneſſe above my fellowes. Heb. 1.9. <hi>Thou haſt loved righteouſneſſe, and hated iniquity, therefore God even thy God hath annointed thee with the oyle of gladneſſe above thy fellowes. Aaron</hi> he on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly killed beaſts for burnt offerings, for peace offerings and heave offerings, but
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:41463:57"/> I was ſlaine for the peace of my people, that I might bring mine to injoy everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting fruition and communion of my Fathers love and glory. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.23. <hi>Him being delivered by the determinate councell and foreknowledge of God, yea have taken, and by wicked hands have crucified and ſlaine. Aaron</hi> dyed and another ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his place, but I live for ever to make attonement and enterceſſion for my reconciled. Heb. 7.2.5. <hi>wherefore he is able to the uttermost to ſave them which come unto God by him, ſeeing he ever liueth to make interceſsion for them. Aaron</hi> neither entred into the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> nor brought others into the land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> But I have entred into my Fathers king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome &amp; provided that for the children of the kingdome. John 14.2, 3. <hi>In my Fathers houſe are many mantions, if it were not ſo I would haue told you, I goe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare a place for you. And if I goe, and prepare a place for you, I will come againe, &amp; receive you unto my ſelfe; that where I am, there you may be alſo. Aaron</hi> had the names of the Children of <hi>Jſrael</hi> ingraven in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſtones, and wore them upon his breaſt that hee might preſent their names and cauſe in the preſence of my
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:41463:57"/> Father I have the names of mine ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven upon my breaſt, that I may ever preſent the cauſe of the Iſrael of God in my Fathers preſence: hence it is ſaid of of me, that I might appeare in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God for mine. Heb. 9.24. <hi>For Chriſt it not entered into the holy places made with hands which are figures of the true, but into Heaven it ſelfe now to appeare in the preſence of God for us. ut ſupra</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, The Father hath given. Chriſt to be the object of Faith through the Covenant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, according to that thy eye beholds, ſo is thy mind affected, according to that the eare heareth, ſo is the ſpirit delighted, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that thou conceiveſt of Chriſt, ſo thy ſoule imbraceth. The loweſt thoughts thou haſt it as heigh as the heavenly mantion, and the heigheſt thought thou haſt is as heigh as Chriſt Lord and Mediatour, thou knoweſt or no mercy, no grace, no bounty, no pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, no love, no joy, no reſt, no hope, no promiſe, no glory, nor no felicitie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt: reſt is no reſt, if Chriſt be not thy reſt, hope is no hope, if Chriſt be not thy hope, felicity ſhould be no fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity, If Chriſt be not thy felicity, and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:41463:58"/> all things are nothing if Chriſt be not all things. If thou injoyeſt light diurnall is it not from the ſun in the midſt of the planets? If thou injoyeſt raine from the clouds, is it not from the raine therein contained? If thou injoyeſt hope, reſt &amp; felicitie, is it not becauſe it is in Chriſt comprehended? all the rivers of the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie wants water, but Chriſts river. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.4. <hi>There is a river, the ſtreames thereof ſhall make glad the Citie of our God.</hi> All the Fountains of the world are empty, but Chriſts Fountain. John 4.14. <hi>But who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever drinketh of the water that I ſhall give him ſhall never thirſt, but the water that I ſhall give him, ſhall be in him a well of water ſpringing up to eternall life.</hi> And all the ſprings upon the earth are vacant or void, but Chriſts overflowing ſprinsg. Pſal. 36.9, 10. <hi>For with thee is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of life, in thy light we ſhall ſee light.</hi> Who from the beginning of the world ever heard of reconciliation, but through him? was not he the Lambe ſlaine from the beginning of the world? who amongſt the priſoners of hope ever heard of deliverie without him? was not he the promiſed deliverer? Iſaiah 59 20. <hi>And the Redeemer ſhall come to Sion, and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:41463:58"/> unto them that turne from tranſgreſſion in Jacob ſaith the Lord.</hi> Who amongſt the poore and bruiſed of the Saints? ever heard of riches and liberty of the Saints without him? is hee not the anoynted of the Lord? <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18. <hi>The ſpirit of the Lord is upon me, becauſe he hath anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me to preach the Goſpel to the poore, hee hath ſent mee to heale the broken hearted to preach deliverance to the Captives, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering of ſight to the blind, to ſet at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty them that are bruiſed.</hi> Did <hi>Moſes</hi> heare of mercy, clemency, bounty, patiencie and of verity in the rocke? and doe not we of the ſame in the rocke Chriſt? yea, he is the rareſt object. Doth the ſunne draw the Comets and Meators from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low above? and the Loadſtone draw the needle diſtant to it? and doth not Chriſt the Sonne of beauty and the pretious ſtone of glory, draw the ſoule in miſery to his higheſt mercies? <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.32. <hi>And I, if I be lifted up from the earth, will draw all men after me. Hoſea</hi> 2.14. <hi>Therefore behold I will allure her, and bring her into the wilderneſſe, and ſpeake comfortably unto her.</hi> Not onely the ſavour of his oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments allures us, not onely his ſweet di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilling Myrrh affects us, but his ſtrength
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:41463:59"/> of operation drawes us. Uertue and ſtrength went from Chriſt, whereby the woman was healed, and the vertue and dignity of Chriſt is that whereby the ſoule is fixed. Hence ſaith the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>John</hi> 1.14. <hi>And the word was made fleſh, and dwelt among us, and wee beheld his glory, the glory as of the only begotten of the Father, full of grace and truth.</hi> Hence, it doth not onely chuſe Chriſt to be its Vine of ſweetneſſe, its ſhepheard becauſe of his tender care and pitty, the Lord its rightouſneſſe becauſe he alone wrought righteouſneſſe, but alſo its object of delight and delectation; ſith he is the only object of delight and delectation. Hence is the Churches de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and delectation. <hi>Oſtende faciem tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, ſonet vox tua in auribus meis: vox e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim tua dulcis, &amp; facies tua decora.</hi> O my ſoule pitch thou alone upon the treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of his wiſedome, the ſtorehouſe of his mercy, the plenitude of heavenly bleſſings, upon his abundant grace truth, righteouſneſſe, goodneſſe, clemency, merit, death, and ſatisfaction, upon his glory, peace, reſt and reciliation, upon his liberty from ſlavery, his freedome from bondage, and everlaſting redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:41463:59"/> upon his hope, bliſſe, felicity and eternall benediction. If thou brayeſt as the hart brayeth after the rivers of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it ſhall be after Chriſt. Pſal. 42.1, 2. <hi>As the heart panteth after the water brookes, ſo panteth my ſoule after thee my God, my ſoule thirſteth for God, after the living God, when ſhall I come and appeare before God.</hi> If thou thirſteth, as the thirſty land it ſhall be after Chriſt. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.1. <hi>O God, thou art my God, early will I ſeeke thee, my ſoule thirſteth for thee, my fleſh longth for thee in a dry and thirsty land where no water is.</hi> If thou wiſheſt after any in heaven above or in the earth below, for him ſhalt thou wiſh. Pſal. 73.24, 25. <hi>Thou ſhalt guide me with thy councell, and afterward receive me to thy glory. Whom have I in heaven but thee, and there is none upon earth that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire beſides thee.</hi> Hee is thy meate, thy drinke, and thy all things, thy water, thy wine, thy fire, and all things, thy being thy welbeing, thy life, and thy althings. Hence ſhalt thou rejoyce in the power of the law of life, ſith Chriſt in that is become thy life. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. <hi>For the law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus, hath made thee free from the law of ſinne and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, The father hath given the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:41463:60"/> Lord Jeſus Chriſt to bee the ſhepheard of his flocke through his Covenant of life and mercy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elkanah</hi> gave to <hi>Penninah</hi> and her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren portions, but to <hi>Hannah</hi> hee gave a double portion, <hi>Abraham</hi> gave to the ſonnes of <hi>Keturah</hi> gifts, but to <hi>Jſaack</hi> he gave the poſſeſſion, though to others the Father gives riches and honours, notwithſtanding he gives to his everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Beatification. Not only in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donation of tranſgreſſion, in peace of conſcience through Chriſts interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but alſo by giving them into the hands of the great ſhepheard of his ſheep, that they might injoy an eternall tuition &amp; protection. All we were wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering ſheepe, we had loſt the image of God, and beare the Image of the devill, deprived of the title of eternall life, being bound with chaines to eternall death, bound to beare the burden of iniquity, to undergoe the dreadfull and terrible ſentence of the morall law, wee were blinde without ſight, naked without cloathing, ſpoiled and bereft of all the rare and noble injoyments which wee injoyed: poore ſillie ſheepe wandering upon the craggie mountaines of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:41463:60"/> the rockes of miſery, the deſert and wilderneſſe of calamity. Was the groat loſt? &amp; not we amonſt the loſt? were the ſheepe gone out of the way, and we not gone aſtray? Notwithſtanding, ſuch hath beene my tender mercy, my ſuperemenent grace, my yearning bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of compaſſion towards you: That I have ſent the great and gratious ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of Iſrael, to ſeeke the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of Iſrael, the Lord of life, to ſeeke the ſons of death, and the ſon of my love, to call and ſeeke the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath. <hi>Eze.</hi> 34.16. <hi>I will ſeeke that which was loſt, and bring againe that which was driven away, and will binde up that which was broken, and will ſtrengthen that which was ſick, but I will deſtroy the fat and the ſtrong, I will feede them with judgement.</hi> Rather then mine ſhould reſt upon the lofty mountaines of impurity, my beloved ſhall ſeeke them up by the word of reconciliation, rather then mine ſhould abide upon the craggie rockes of iniquity, my beloved ſhall ſeek the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> up by the word of great ſalvation. <hi>Rom</hi> 10.7, 8. <hi>But the righteouſneſſe which is of faith, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth on this wiſe, Say not in thine heart who ſhall aſcend up into Heaven, (that is) to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:41463:61"/> bring down Chriſt from above, or who ſhall diſcend into the deep (that is to bring up Chriſt againe from the dead. But what ſaith it? the word is neigh the even in thy mouth and in thy heart, that is the word of faith which wee preach.</hi> Ther is no ſuch Shepheard as the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of Iſrael he loves his ſheep to the death. Hath it been recorded that any King hath layd down his life for rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Subjects? Hath it been inrowled that any Bridegroome hath loſt his life for his Bride? or any Shepheard hath layd down his life for his ſheep? but my beloved, the King of my Church &amp; cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, the Bridegroome to his beloved ſpouſes, and the great ſhepheard of his ſheepe hath layd down his life for his wandring ſheepe. John 10.18. <hi>No man taketh it from me, but I lay it down of my ſelfe, I have power to lay it down, and I have power to take it againe, this commandement have I received of my father.</hi> He is the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhepheard of my flock: neither the heate of the day, nor the cold of the night hindred <hi>Jacobs</hi> care of <hi>Labans</hi> flock: the heate of my wrath, furie and indignation, nor the coldneſſe of the effections of his peculiar, can prevent his
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:41463:61"/> care over my ſcattered and diſpearſed flocke. Were the ſhepheards carefull of their flock in the day of Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming? and will not Iſraels ſhepheard be carefull of his flocke after his comming? he is not only as a father to mine to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie them in his armes. Cant. 2.6 <hi>His left hand is under my head and his right hand doth imbrace me.</hi> As an Eagle that beares them upon his wings. Deut. 32.11.12. <hi>As an Eagle ſtireth up her neſt, fluttereth with her wings, ſpreadeth abroad her wings, taketh them, beares them upon her wings. So the Lord alone did lead him, and their was no ſtrange God with him,</hi> But as a ſhepheard who carries his upon his ſhouldiers to the fould of grace and glory. John 10.16. <hi>And other ſheep I have which are not of this fold, them alſo J muſt bring, and they ſhall heare my voice, and there ſhall be one fold &amp; one ſhepheard.</hi> Whilſt mine are ſubject to chances and all evils, he is their defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whilſt they are ſubject to goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray, he is their gatherer, hence he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth my Commiſſion. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.24. <hi>But he anſwered, and ſaid, J am not ſent, but unto the loſt ſheep of Jſrael.</hi> The pooreſt and meaneſt of his flocke by him are ſuſtained, the ſtrongeſt and fateſt of his
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:41463:62"/> flocke by him are ſupported, he leads them by his precious promiſes, clothes them with his heavenly grace, and gives them a rich inheritance amongſt his Saints. Epheſ. 1.18. <hi>The eyes of your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding being opened, that yee might know what is the hope of his calling, and what the riches of the glory of his inheritance in the ſaints.</hi> If they are ſcorched by the heate of tribulations, he is their cloud of preſervation, if they want light in the darkeſt night, he is their fire by night for conſolation. Iſaiah 4.6. <hi>And there- ſhall be a tabernacle for a ſhadow in the day time from the heate, and a place of refuge, and for a cover from ſtorme and from raine. For thou haſt been a ſtrength to the poore, a ſtrength to the needy in his distreſſe; a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge from the storme, a ſhadow from the heat, when the blaſt of the terrible ones is as a ſtorme againſt the wall.</hi> His ſheep are neere to him through union. John 27.23. <hi>J in them, and thou in me, that they may be made perfect in one: and that the world may know that thou haſt ſent me, and haſt loved them as thou haſt loved me.</hi> They are deare to him through redemption. 1 Pet. 1.18.19. <hi>For as much as yee know that ye were not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed with corruptable things as ſilver and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:41463:62"/> gold from your vaine converſation, received by tradition from your fathers: but with the precious blood of Chriſt, as a Lambe without blemiſh and without ſpot.</hi> They are preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to him through donation. John 17.9.10. <hi>J pray for them, J pray not for the world, but for them which thou haſt given me, for they are thine, and all mine are thine, and thine are mine, and I am glorified in them.</hi> And they are gracious in his ſight and preſence through acceptation. Eheſ. 1.6. <hi>To the praiſe of the glory of his grace, wherein he hath made us accepted in the beloved,</hi> They are precious Jewells in his account and eſtimation, they are his tender flocke in his account and compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, are their deaths precious in his ſight, and are not their lives precious in his preſence? Is the vine tender ever its branches? the King loving to his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects? the ſpouſe acceptable to the bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome? and are not his flocke precious &amp; deare to the great ſhepheard of Iſrael? neither the Foxes by their cunning, the Wolves by their ravening, the Lions by their roaring, the Tigers by their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring ſhall be able to plucke them out of his hand. John 10.28.29. <hi>And I give unto them eternall life, and they ſhall
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:41463:63"/> never periſh, neither ſhall any man plucke them out of my hand, my father which gave them me is greater then all, and no man is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to plucke them out of my fathers hand.</hi> As they have beene acquired by an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall power, purchaſed by an infinite va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, ſo they are conſerved by an eternall power and omnipotencie: to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of bliſſe and felicitie. 1 Pet. 1.5. <hi>Who are kept by the power of God, through faith unto ſalvation, ready to be revealed in the laſt time.</hi> Epheſ. 1.19. <hi>And what is the exceeding greatneſſe of his power, to us ward who beleeve, according to the working of his mighty power.</hi> O my ſoule, be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly aſſured that nothing ſhall befall thee but that which ſhall be good for thee. If death, the ſting of that is remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, if life, thy life is written in the book of life, If perill, conſervation by the hope in Chriſt, If famine, thou haſt the bread of life, if want of water, thou haſt the fountaine of living water, if ſicknes, thou haſt healing to the wings of Chriſt, if temptation, thy faith ſhall be to thee more precious then gold that is tried in the fire, if want of freedome, thou haſt libertie through redemption, if loſſe of the love of the neareſt in thy boſome,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:41463:63"/> thy Lord &amp; ſhepheard is nere and deare to thee, and if want of defence, thy Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour will be thy ſunne and ſheild Pſalme 84.11. <hi>For the Lord God is a ſunne and ſheild, the Lord will give grace and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, no good thing will he with hold from them that walke uprightly. Rom.</hi> 8.28. <hi>And we know that all things worke together for good to them that love God, to them that are the called according to his purpoſe.</hi> Oh! my ſoule if thou glorieſt thou ſhalt glory in ſuch a ſhepheard, is he not the great ſhepheard able to make thee perfect in every good worke? Heb. 13.20.21. <hi>Now the God of peace that brought againe from the dead our Lord Jeſus, that great ſhepheard of the ſheep, through the blood of the everlaſting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: make you perfect in every good worke, to doe his will, working in you that which is well pleaſing to you through Jeſus Chriſt to whom be glory for ever, and ever amen.</hi> Hath he not fountaines above all fountains? ſprings ſurpaſſing all ſprings? and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures more pleaſant then all paſtures Ezek. 34.23. <hi>And I will ſet up one ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard over them, and he ſhall feed them, even my ſervant David. He ſhall feed them, and he ſhall be their ſhepheard,</hi> 14.15. <hi>verſe. I will feed them in a good paſture, and upon the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:41463:64"/> high Mountains of Iſrael Shall their fold be, there ſhall they lie in a good fold, and in a fat paſture ſhall they feed upon the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of Iſrael, I will feed my flocke, and I will cauſe them to ly down ſaith the Lord God.</hi> His voice will I heare, his word will I obey, to his call I will ſubject, I know the difference between his voice and the voice of ſtrangers, they ſet up mans inventions, makeing linſey woolſy garments, and ſet up mans poſts by Chriſts poſts: they advance mans right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, ſet up legall doings and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh performances, they throw the Lord Jeſus Chriſt out of his thron, and plucke him out of his chaire, and ſet up the creature worſe then nothing. But the voice of Chriſt is to ſpeake of the praiſe of his owne righteouſneſſe, of the pretiouſneſſe of his own blood, of the triumph of his owne death, of his love to his beloved Church, of the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that union the ſaints have with his father, and of the pitie he hath to the broken ſpirits. Mat. 11.28. <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour and are heavie laden: and I will give you reſt.</hi> And of the gift of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life to his adopted. John 17.2. <hi>And thou haſt given him power
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:41463:64"/> over all fleſh, that he ſhould give eternall life, to as many as thou haſt given him.</hi> Of the praiſe, of the glory, of the honour, of the dominion, of the power, and of the love of his Father. John 17.23. <hi>I in them, and thou in me, that they may bee made perfect in one, and that the world may know that thou haſt ſent me, and haſt loved them as thou haſt loved me.</hi> Of the revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, teaching, direction, convincement and comfort of the ſpirit. John 15.26. <hi>But when the comforter is come, whom I will ſend unto you from the father, even the ſpirit of truth which proceedeth from the father; he ſhall teſtifie of me.</hi> Therefore as thou giveſt praiſe becauſe hee is thy mediatour, thy King, thy Bridegroome, thy vine, and thy beloved: ſo thou ſhalt give praiſe, ſith hee is become thy eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, carefull, deare and loving ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard: rejoycing in the law and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of life in Chriſt that is bleſſed, yea a thouſand times bleſſed for evermore. Rehearſing the words concerning the Law of life in Chriſt Jeſus. Rom. 8.2. <hi>For the law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, hath made thee free from the law of ſinne and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:41463:65"/>
               <p>Secondly, In reſpect of Eternity.</p>
               <p>The Celeſtiall body is more excellent then other bodies, in foure reſpects.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Becauſe it is a Cauſe Univerſall.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Becauſe it is carried about with a circuler motion.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Becauſe of heavenly light, and fourthly, becauſe it is incorruptible.</p>
               <p>So the Covenant or law of free grace, is not onely excellent, becauſe the light of the fathers countenance ſhines in that Covenant, becauſe it is conferred upon the ſonnes of miſerie and calamity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the cauſe of all divine graces and mercies given to the Saints, but alſo ſith it is everlaſting and eternall. My Covenant is not as the ſmall dew upon the tender hearbs, not as the fading leafe and withering hearb, not as the fraile life of the ſublunarie creatures. I made the firſt Covenant with <hi>Adam,</hi> and it was momentanie, I have made the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond in Chriſt, and it is to perpetuity; when I eſpouſed mine to me to the praiſe of my glory, I eſpouſed them to me for ever through my mercy. Iſa. 54.7, 8. <hi>For a ſmall moment have I forſaken
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:41463:65"/> thee, but with great mercy will I gather thee, in a little wrath I hide my face from thee for a moment, but with everlaſting kindnes will I have mercy upon thee, ſaith the Lord thy Redeemer.</hi> Whence once I become their God, I am their God to eternity, when once I become their Father, I am their Father to perpetuitie, as there is no end of the blood of the covenant of my grace, as there is no end of the death of the Covenant of my peace ſo there is no end of my loving kindneſſe in the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace &amp; peace. Though I have made a covenant it is not l ke the firſt covenant I made in mount <hi>Sinai.</hi> Ier. 31.31. <hi>Behold the day is come ſaith the Lord, that I will make a new covenant with the houſe of Jſrael and with the houſe of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah Not according to that I made with their Fathers, &amp;c.</hi> Hence my people may glory in my Covenant, had I made a Covenant with them to be their God to day, and their enemy to morrow, to blot out their ſinnes to day, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them to morrow, to write my law in their hearts to day, and blot it out to morrow, to give righteouſneſſe, peace, reſt, grace, truth, hope, joy, peace, love, reconciliation, redemption,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:41463:66"/> and Adoption to day, and to take theſe away to morrow, my people ſhould not had cauſe of glorying in the eternity of my favor: but now have they great cauſe of glorying in my covenant: ſith it is as faſt as the day and the night, though all things fade and waxe old as a garment, though the heavens ſhould depart as a ſcroule, though the hills ſhould flee, and the mountaines be removed; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this covenant muſt needs ſtand for ever. <hi>Jſay</hi> 54.10. <hi>For the mountaines ſhall depart, and the hils ſhall be removed, but my kindneſſe ſhall not depart from thee, neither ſhall the Covenant of my peace bee removed ſaith the Lord, that hath m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rcy on thee.</hi> Had I made the Sunne, the Moone, the Starres, the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets like the fading herb, graſſe or trees, where had beene their rareneſſe? If I had made the gold, the gemms, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Jewels like the droſſe of yron: where had beene their richneſſe? If I had made my ſecond covenant of peace, of grace, of love and mercy like the firſt of terrors, of dreads, of horrors and decaying, where had beene the preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe? But my people glory not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe I have made a Covenant, but
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:41463:66"/> becauſe I have made a covenant ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, they glory not onely in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, but in everlaſting righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not only in treaſures, but in eternall treaſures, not onely in life, but in eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, not only in peace but in perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all peace, and attonement. So they glory not only in the covenant of life and peace: but alſo that it is the etarnal cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of life &amp; peace. Hence they glory with the Apoſtle. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. <hi>For the law of the Spirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus, hath made us free from the law of ſinne and of death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Becauſe it is placed in Christ.</p>
               <p>The Sunne is placed in the midſt of the planets, from whence all the planets receive their pureſt lights, the heart is placed in the midſt of man, that all the parts from thence might receive their vitall motion: the law of life and grace is placed in Chriſt Jeſus, that from thence the Churches might receive their happineſſe. Happie, O thrice hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie are the Churches tha they have ſuch a Lord, and ſuch a law, not of ſin and death, but of grace and life. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. <hi>For the Law of the Spirit of life in
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:41463:67"/> Chriſt Jeſus hath made them free from the law of ſinne and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The earth was undecked and undor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, till I adorned the earth with beauty, the heavenly orbs were not beautified, till I beautified them with the Splendor of the Sun, of Moone and Planets. The old law was inglorious by curſe, execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and condemnation; but I have made a new, glorious through life, hope and benediction. In whoſe hand is it bleſſed? if not in the hand of the bleſſed mediatour, in whoſe breaſt is it happi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> if not in the breaſt of him that is a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Redeemer? and in whom can that be glorious? except in him that is King of Kings, and Prince of glory: It would not have ſtood with the glory of my wiſedome, If I ſhould have made my covenant of life with the ſlaves of the devill, bondſlaves to hell, and children of death: it would not have ſtood with the honour of my wiſe diſpoſement, ſhould I have placed my ſecond cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in them that brake my firſt, and have ſhott their arrowes as farre diſtant from the throne of my grace as the higheſt place is from the loweſt hell. I ſhould have loſt the dignity of my
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:41463:67"/> grace, had I made it with Angels who pittied not the priſoners of my hope, neither could they anſwer the require and ſeverity of my Juſtice. As I have placed the pureſt light in the lighteſt Sunne, and the rareſt vertue in the pureſt gemmes, ſo I have placed my law of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and intire purity in the Sonne of my rareſt excellencie. I have made my Covenant to Chriſt. Gal. 3.16. <hi>Now to Abraham and his ſeede were the promiſes made, he ſaith not, and to ſeedes: as of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but as of one, and to thy ſeede which is Chriſt.</hi> I have made my Covenant with Chriſt, ſith none could ſatisfie my ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice or fulfill my righteouſneſſe but him alone. I made my Covenant in Chriſt. 2 Cor. 1.20. <hi>For all the promiſes are in him, yea, and in him Amen, unto the glory of God by us.</hi> I made him the Covenant of life and Salvation. Iſay 42.6, 7. <hi>I the Lord have called thee in righteouſneſſe, and will hold thine hand, and will keepe thee, and give thee for a Covenant of the people, for a light of the Gentils, to open the blinde eyes, to bring out the priſoners from the priſon, and them that ſit in darkeneſſe out of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon houſe.</hi> He was the Character of my perſon, and the effulgencie of my glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:41463:68"/> hee was the appointed King, and the Lord commander of my purchaſed and acquired, the Mediatour to and for my Redeemerd and Reconciled, the prince of the kings of the earth, the firſt begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from the dead, and the only one and beloved of the boſom: therefore my co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is to him, with him, and in him. I tooke up my habitation in him from eternity to eternity, my dwelling and delectation is in him from the beginning to the ending: hence, my Covenant of eternity reſts in the boſome of eternity, from whence ſhould the eſpouſed have their Commands but from their bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome, I have not married them to the law, but to Chriſt. Rom 7.4. <hi>Wherefore my brethren, ye alſo are become dead to the law, by the body of Chriſt, that ye ſhould be married to another, even to him who is raiſed from the dead, that we ſhould bring forth fruit unto God.</hi> From whence ſhould the ſubjects have their ordinance but from their King? I have not made <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> their king, but Chriſt King of his Church. Pſal. 45.11. <hi>So ſhall thy King greatly deſire thy beauty, for hee is thy Lord and worſhip thou him.</hi> From whence ſhould the redeemed of the Lord have
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:41463:68"/> their rules &amp; precepts but from Chriſt? I have not made <hi>Moſes</hi> their Prophet, but Chriſt their Prophet. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.18. <hi>I will raiſe them up a Prophet from among their brethren, like unto thee, &amp;c.</hi> O my ſoule, if I glory, I will not glory in that which is written in tables of ſtone, but in that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is written in the fleſhly tables of thy heart, not in that which is the miniſtry of death, but in that which is the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of life; not in the miniſtry of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, but in that which is the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of ſalvation, not in that which gendreth to bondage, but in that which tendeth to libertie, not in that which hath a vaile and darkeneſſe, but in that which hath light and glory; not in that which diſconſolates and diſcomforts the drooping conſcience, but in that which conſolates &amp; comforts the droo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping ſpirit. Thou glorieſt in the preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of his riches, in the rareneſſe of his promiſes, in the beauty of his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and ſhalt thou not glory in the pretiouſneſſe, rareneſſe &amp; riches of the law of life in Chriſt? did <hi>David</hi> deſire the waters of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> above all wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? did <hi>Abraham</hi> deſire a ſonne above the Land of <hi>Canaan?</hi> and ſhalt thou not
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:41463:69"/> deſire this law of life above all lawes? if others pitch their tents by <hi>Sinai,</hi> thou ſhalt pitch thy tent by <hi>Sion,</hi> if others fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Moſes,</hi> thou ſhalt follow Chriſt, if others delight in that which drives them from God, thou ſhalt delight in that which drawes thee neere to God. The law of ſinne and death hath not freed thee from the law of ſinne and death, the law of curſe or execration, hath not freed thee from the law of death and condemnation, the law of terrours and horrors hath not freed thee from the law of terror &amp; horrour, but the law of life by w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> thou art dead to the law that thou mayeſt live unto God. Gal. 2.19. <hi>For I through the Law am dead to the Law, that I might live unto God.</hi> Hence thou therefore ſhalt hearken to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the Father. Mat. 17.5. <hi>While he yet ſpake, behold a bright cloud overſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed them, and behold a voyce out of the cloud, which ſaid, this is my beloved ſonne in whom I am well pleaſed heare ye him.</hi> Who hath the words of eternall life but he? John 6.68. <hi>Then Simon Peter anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him, Lord, to whom ſhall we goe? thou haſt the words of eternall life.</hi> Into whoſe lips hath grace been infuſed but into his?
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:41463:69"/> Pſalme 45.2. <hi>Thou art fairer then the children of men, grace is powred into thy lyps, therefore God hath bleſſed thee forever.</hi> Or who hath the words of peace and reconciliation but he? Epheſ. 2.17. <hi>And came and preached peace to you which were affarre off, and to them which were nigh,</hi> Hence will I glory in the glorying ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Apoſtle Paul Rom. 8.2. <hi>For the law of the ſpirit of life in Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, hath freed them from the law of ſinne and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hath freed me.</p>
               <p>Iſrael had ten portions in the King, when Judah &amp; Benjamen had but two, but it cannot be ſpoken according to that tenour of the ſaints beloved, for they have a like inheritance in God and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent, ſith they are choſen by one Lord, redeemed by one Chriſt, ſealed by one ſpirit of life, injoying the law of life being freed from the law of ſinne and death. Rom. 8.2. <hi>For the law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, hath freed me from the law of ſinne and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:41463:70"/>
               <p>Chriſt is then operative in the ſoule, when by faith he is particularly applied.</p>
               <p>The tranſcient paſſage of the beauty or ſplendor of an object, is through the eye unto the mind, the paſſing conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble delectation which is in Chriſt, is through a Chriſtians application to the ſoule, in Chriſt are treaſures paſſing the treaſures hid in the ſands, the emenency and ſuperemency of all heavenly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine compaſſions; paſſing the compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of humaine generation, the excelen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, yea, the ſuperexcellency of worth, merit, and value, paſſing all the valuable things which are wrapt up in the breaſt of things terreſtiall. But what are thoſe treaſures paſſing treaſures, the eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, the ſuperemency of thoſe heavenly and divine compaſſions, the excellency the ſuperexcellency of that his merit, worth and value without a ſpeciall or particular applyment. The comfort of the eye is in ſeeing, of the eare in hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, of man in moving, the comfort of the ſoule is in applying. What joy is there to a Rebell to thinke there is a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and yet out of that he ſhall be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed? what comfort is there to a man
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:41463:70"/> to know there are rich treaſures wrapt in our mother earth, and he of thoſe ſhall be deprived? or what joy or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort can come to the ſoule or conſcience though there are all excellencies wrapt within Chriſts boſome, if they of him ſhall not be injoyed? other creatures were before man was created, light over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread the earth, before light in the ſun was placed: but comfort to the faithfull doth not ariſe before that Chriſt by faith is applied. Our ſad houres, our dolefull dayes, our gloomſome times are then removed: when the vertuall efficacy of Chriſt through faiths application is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived: our comfort till we come to heavens City, our joy till we come to heavens felicity, and our ſolid refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment till we come to heavens glory is through faiths applying Chriſt ours all in all. Though the waves of iniquitie doe roare, the floods of tranſgreſſion fall, the wind of bitter affliction blow heard upon us, yet if once by applying we caſt anchor into Chriſt: ſolid joy doth invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron the heart and conſcience, as light doth incompaſſe the body of a rationall, then the terrible, the dreadfull, the i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God againſt ſinne and tranſgreſſion
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:41463:71"/> appeares moſt bounteous, moſt benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, moſt clementious through his marvilous compaſſion, then the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of eternall grace and mercy puts to repulſe the law of death and miſerie, then the worth and merit of Chriſt pleads redemption from the foule black jawes of the Devill, reconciliation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the God of infinite purity, and man who through ſinne hath procured an infinite miſerie, and juſtification in the ſight of our heavenly and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate father. Anchor being caſt in Chriſt, all becomes a Chriſtians his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, his death, his blood, his power, his ſpirit, and his Kingdome. If the Brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome be the Brides by combination: then his lands, his livings, his jewels, his gold, his ſilver, is hers. If Chriſt be ours, then his heavenly benedictions, his ſpirituall bleſſings, his ſuperabundant, and heavenly treaſure are become ours alſo. <hi>All are yours, and yee are Chriſts, and Chriſt is Gods,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. O my ſoule apply whole Chriſt particularly, that thou mayeſt injoy him fully. Was he deprived of all, before Pilate, accuſed of the Souldiers buffited, of the high Prieſts diſdained, and not for thee? he indured
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:41463:71"/> that which thou ſhouldeſt have ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, he ſuffered for that which hadſt deſerved, Oh what did he ſuſtaine? Oh what hath he not ſuſtained? Oh what did he ſuffer? Oh what hath he not ſuffered! did he not undergoe the burthen of thy ſinne which was inſufferable, by a ſtrength and power invincible? at what time the vaile of the temple rented, at that time the heavens opened, at what time the earth trembled, at that time through his ſatisfaction he removed thy trembling eſtate and condition, at what time the light of the ſunne was obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, at that time the merit of thy Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſhined, the glory of the ſunne of righteouſneſſe, and the beauty of the ſunne which is collocated in the midſt of the planets at one time were darkned, in which time Chriſt ſtood in thy place, and for thy ſake hath ſuffered.</p>
               <p>What might I mention concerning Chriſt, the more the mind conceiveth, the more the tongue relateth, the more the ſoule by faith apprehendeth, the more the mind is elevated. The Moone is below the ſunne, the ſunne below Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnee, Saturne below the Primum Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile, the Vegitive creature is be low the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:41463:72"/> ſenſitive, the Senſitive below the Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall, and the Rationall below him that lives by faith in the Lord Jeſus. How divine is ſuch a Chriſtian in contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? how heavenly in Mediation? how rare i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> declaration? how ſweet in converſation? never a ſpeech comes from ſuch a Chriſtian, but it is inflamed with the fire of the Holy Ghoſt, hence all his words are in extolling Chriſts righteouſnes, advancing Chriſts goodneſſe, valuing Chriſt blood, Chriſt hath drawn his mind to a high pitch of conceivement: hath the ſunne the power of exalation, the ſplendor of a Diamond in the drawing of the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; is ther not enough in Chriſt which drawes the Chriſtian to high meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Though thy mind did reſt like the Cocke upon the dunghill of this world, though thy affection was as faſt inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the creature as a mould in the earth, yet from ſo low a condition a Chriſtian is brought, when once Chriſt by his vertue in the conſcience takes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, then not honoures, but Chriſts honour, not riches, but Chriſts riches, not righteouſneſſe but Chriſts righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, alone for a Chriſtians preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:41463:72"/> the eie is diſtant from the ſunne, the eye nevertheleſſe by the light there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is drawn to behold his beauty, though Chriſt is diſtant from a Chriſtian, yet by his efficacy he drawes the eye of faith to behold his glory, what only to behold the glory of his victory tryumphant, the glory of his mediation delectant, and not the glory of his ſeſſion magnificent? applying faith is never below the throne of grace and glory, it is never below the ſeate of Gods eternall mercy, where there is not faiths applycation, death of ſpirit hath domination, our life by Chriſts treaſures of wiſedome, by the vertue of his death and riſing againe from the dead: is through faiths apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Let a Chriſtian obſerve the death of ſpirit in the hearts of Juſticiaries, and inquire the reaſon, why it is ſo? and he ſhal find that it is becauſe they apply not whole Chriſt to their conſciences. Some thing they will have of their own righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe in Juſtification, ſome thing of their owne performances in matter of reconciliation, let us ſpeake of Chriſt freely and bouldly, and they ſtand as people agaſhed, and amazed. I deny n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t that they have a name to live; But as
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:41463:73"/> ſure as the ſunne ſhines in Europe when it is come to the Meridian, ſo ſure are they dead, yea as a tree twice plucked up by the rootes, through the hand of the workeman. He that hath the life of faith, he applies all the excellencies of Chriſt unto himſelfe, what ſaith ſuch a beleeving chriſtian? hath Chriſt redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med others, and not me? reconciled o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and not me? juſtified others, and not me? Surely if any be redeemed, if any juſtified, if any reconciled, then I am one of that number. Through apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faith the ſoule is ſicke of love, at the very ſight of his riches, of his wiſedom, of his righteouſneſſe, of his graces and conſolations, it cries out, O my beloved, my well beloved, where reſts? where re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines? where abides my welbeloved? is the love of a woman ſo to her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, of a father to a child, of a ſubject to his Prince, comparable to that love of the ſoule to Chriſt? who hath found in Chriſt al the kinds of ſweeteſt conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, this applyment of Chriſt makes the ſoule deſire more of Chriſt, he who hath felt the ſweetneſſe of the hony combe, he deſires to taſt of the ſweetneſſe of that againe, he who hath ſeen the light
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:41463:73"/> of the ſunne, deſires to ſee it againe, he that once hath taſted of the ſweetneſſe in Chriſt through application, deſires to taſt thereof againe. Hence are the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries of ſuch beleevers. O that I might feele the vertue of Chriſts blood in my conſcience more efficatiouſly, that doht purge my conſcience from dead workes to ſerve the living God, <hi>The blood of Chriſt, which through the eternall ſpirit was offered without blame to God, ſhal purge your conſciences from dead workes, to ſerve the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God.</hi> Heb. 9.14. O that I might feele more effectually the power of that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation which once upon the croſſe he fully perfected and finiſhed: that he would give me to underſtand more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that I have all my ſinns pardoned and remittted. <hi>Whom God hath ſet forth to be a propitiation by faith in his blood, to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate his righteouſneſſe, by the forgiveneſſe of ſinnes which are paſt through his long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering.</hi> Rom. 3.25. O that I might be more aſſured that Chriſts righteouſneſſe is mine, then ſhould I injoy the ſweeteſt peace of conſcience, ſith I ſhould be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſured that God with me ſhould be well pleaſed, and that I ſhould be found worthy to abide in the City of our God
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:41463:74"/> for ever: there to praiſe and honour him for ever more. <hi>They waſhed and made white their robes in the blood of the lambe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are before the throne of God, and worſhip him day and night.</hi> Apoc. 7.14.15. O that I might be repleniſhed with the fullneſſe of his grace, then ſhould my empty pitcher bee filled with joy, and my mournfull heart with conſolation, and yee are now in heavineſſe. <hi>But I will ſee you againe, and your heart ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and your joy ſhall no man take from you.</hi> John 16.22. O that I might have his ſpirit to dwell in me, then ſhould I be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to call and cry Abba Father, to make my petitions ſtrongly to my heavenly father, to know aſſuredly that I am one of thoſe who are purchaſed with the pretious blood of Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Ye are not in the fleſh, but in the ſpirit, if the ſpirit of God dwell in you, but if any man have not the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt, he is none of his.</hi> Rom. 8.9. O that I might feele the mighty power of the death of my ſaviour and redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, then ſhould I dye to ſinne, and live to righteouſneſſe, as the Phenix by the Sunne is conſumed, and by vertue of the beames thereof is revived: ſo if I feele the power of the death of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:41463:74"/> death ſhall be aboliſhed and the life of righteouſneſſe in me by the life of Chriſt renewed. <hi>Ye are buried by Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me into his death, that like as Chriſt is raiſed from the dead unto the glory of his father, ſo we alſo may walke in the newnes of life. Rom.</hi> 6.4. O that I might feele the mighty o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſts mediatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then ſhould I behold God moſt propitious and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentious, then ſhould my faith cleave faſt to the mercy ſeate for mercy, and to the throne of grace for grace, thereby ſhould I rejoyce abundantly, the ſinging birds would not ſo rejoyce when winter is gone, and ſummer doth approach; as I ſhall rejoyce in receiving delectation from Chriſts mediation: then ſhould I not runne from God with <hi>Adam,</hi> but have acceſſe to God as <hi>Eſter</hi> had to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſhueroſh. By whom alſo through faith, we have acceſſe unto his grace, by which wee ſtand and rejoyce under the hope of the glory of God. Rom.</hi> 5.2. O my ſoule give glory to God thy heavenly Father, and to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt thy gratious Redeemer, and to the holy Spirit who ſealeth unto thee ſure mercies which will never faile thee in the greateſt extreamities. Gods eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall favour in Chriſt eſtabliſhed, the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatiouſneſſe
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:41463:75"/> of Chriſts merits and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, the ſealing thereof is not in thine owne power, but in the power of the holy Spirit. Hee that lookes upon the Creature, he concludes that the Creature made not it ſelfe, but it was made by the hand of the Creator, he that minds how great a matter it is to have the eternall love of God, and the merit of Chriſt to his conſcience ſealed, will conclude it is not of himſelf, but through the work of the Spirit, who is our ſealer; <hi>And ye are ſcaled by the holy ſpirit of promiſe, who is the earneſt of our inheritance, to the obtaining of Redemption unto the praiſe of his glory.</hi> Epheſ. 13.14. but to draw unto a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, leaſt many lines may be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive unto thy patience, Chriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, only chuſe thou Chriſt O my ſoule, that when thy heart failes thee, hee may be thy ſtrength and thy portion for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, is not thy Saviour better then tenne thouſands, all things are valued, but his value is invaluable, all things are eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, yet his worth is ineſtimable, many things are uttered, yet his excellency is unutterable. Am I not raviſhed when he is my contemplation? Am I not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verjoyed when hee is my Meditation?
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:41463:75"/> doth not my valley abound with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure when the vertue of his grace takes in me poſſeſſion? is the morning ſunne ſo joyous to a traviller, as Chriſt is to me: when I thinke of him in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, hee is more to thee O my ſoule then riches, then honours, then gold, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſilver, yea then pretious ſtones? if thou hadſt a kingdom, and waſt not aſſured of his kingdome, what would that profit thee? if thou hadſt a world, if thou hadſt no intereſt in that blood w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> purchaſed the world to come, what would that availe thee? if thou hadſt all the joyes and pleaſures under heaven, if thou hadſt not the joy of his ſpirit, what would that benefit thee? if thou hadſt al the gay apparrell in the world, if thou hadſt not Chriſts righteouſneſſe to defend thee from the wrath of God, what fruit would that bring u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to thee? if thou hadſt all to plead for thee, if thou hadſt not Chriſt to excuſe thee in the day of the Lord, what joy could poſſeſſe thee? it is good for thee to reſt where Chriſt is, ſo ſhall he be to thee a reſting place, it is good for thee to dwell where hee is, for there are joyes for evermore. O my ſoule feare not what man can doe unto thee, if they take away thy name, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:41463:76"/> thy name is ingraved upon his breaſt, he bare thy name upon the croſſe, he beareth thy name now in the ſight of thy gratious Father. Though thy name is extinguiſhed, yet not extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, though not remembred, yet remembred evermore. Let Juſticiaries caſt their Arrowes by day, and their fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie dars by night, yet know that through thy ſaviour thou art able to repulſe the fiery darts of Satan, much more theirs. Let them take away thy life, thy life is hid with Chriſt in God. Col. 3.3. <hi>For ye are dead and your life is hid with Chriſt in God.</hi> Let them conclude that thou art vaine glorious, thy glorying expreſſion ſhall be of Chriſt thy Lord of life and righteouſnes, ſith if any in heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or earth are bought to God by our Lord of life &amp; glory, then thou art one of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, whilſt thou as a poore pilgrim wandereſt towards heavens City, make thou a heavenly dimention of his glory; <hi>Worthy is the Lambe, who was ſlaine to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive power, &amp; riches, and ſtrength, &amp; wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and honour, and glory, and bleſſing, and to him that ſits upon the throne, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lambe, be aſcribed bleſſing, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and glory, and ſtrength for ever and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:41463:76"/> Amen. Revel.</hi> 5.13.13.</p>
               <p>From the law of ſinne and death.</p>
               <p>O my people! what have I done for you? as Reconciliation to God my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through my blood and death is the greateſt mercy, as my Adoption by my Spirit of glory is the higheſt love, ſo my Redemption from the law of ſinne and death by the Law of the Spirit of life is the freeſt bountie. Have you not come ſhort of my glory and the glory of my Father Rom. 3 23. <hi>For all have ſinned &amp; are come ſhort of the glory of God.</hi> Have you not been under the curſe and execration of the morrall law? Gal. 3.10. <hi>For as many as are of the the workes of the law are under the curſe: for it is written, curſed is every one that continueth not in all things which are written in the booke of the Law to do them</hi> Have not your Spirit been ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and your mouthes ſtopt before my Fathers preſence. Rom. 3 .19. <hi>Now wee know that what things ſoever the Law ſaith, it ſaith to them that are under the Law, that every mouth may be ſtopped, and all the world may become guilty before God.</hi> Hath not <hi>Moſes</hi> accuſed you before the barre
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:41463:77" rendition="simple:additions"/> of juſtice? John 5.45. <hi>Doe not thinke that I will accuſe you to the Father, there is one that accuſeth you even Moſes in whom ye truſt.</hi> Was not the ſame Law that was made for ungodly, wicked and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigable ſiners made for you? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. <hi>For whoremongers, for them that defile themſelves with mankind, for men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtealers, for lyers, for perjured perſons, and if there bee any other thing that is contrary to ſound doctrine.</hi> But I have delivered you from the law of Condemnation by the law of Salvation, from the law of execration, by the Law of benediction, from the Law of accuſation, by the law of life and reconciliation, and from the law of adjudication, by the law of hope and Redemption. When that I ſaw that ye were come ſhort of all righteouſnes, fulfilled al righteouſneſs. Rom. 10.4. <hi>For Chriſt is the end of the law for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſake, to every one that beleeveth.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſaw that you were accurſed, I became a curſe for you, having undertaken to die the curſed death of the Croſſe. Gal. 3.13. <hi>Chriſt hath redeemed us from the curſe of the law, being made a curſe for us: for it is written, curſed is every one that hangeth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a tree.</hi> I ſaw that you could not ſtand
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:41463:77"/> juſt in the ſight of my Father, I gave you another righteouſneſſe by faith which is in me. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. <hi>And being found in him, not having mine own righteouſneſſe, which is of the law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, the righteouſnes which is of God by faith.</hi> Now as you are not the ſonnes of death, but children of life, ſo you are under the law of life: Now as you are not the children of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude, and bondage, but the children of liberty and Adoption: &amp; are under my law of liberty and Adoption. Gal. 4.1.2. <hi>Now I ſay that the heire as long as hee is a child, differeth nothing from a ſervant though he is Lord of all, but is under Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours and Governours: untill the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of the Father. Gal.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Stand faſt therefore in the liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made us free, and bee not intangled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the yoake of bondage.</hi> Now are you not children of unbeleefe and diffidence, ſith I dwell in your hearts by faith which is by me. Epheſ. 3.16.17. <hi>That he would grant you according to the riches of his glory, to bee ſtrengthened with might by his ſpirit in the inner man, that Chriſt may dwell in your hearts by faith, being rooted and grounded in love.</hi> Now you are not
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:41463:78" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſlaves of hell and wrath, but the deareſt and choyſeſt ones through my grace and tender compaſſion, therefore you are not under the law, but under grace. Rom. 6.14. <hi>For ſinne ſhall not have domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over you, for ye are not under the law, but under grace.</hi> Therefore you ſhall walke as my deareſt, my choiſeſt and my redeemed, as my peculiar, my jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els and reconciled? Doe I make my branches ſtately through my union? do I make mine fruitfull through my bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Communion? and doe I not make mine ſubjective through the law of life and benedicton? Now they will live the life of faith in me, the life of love through me, the life of obedience by me. I have not given them the rule of mercy and peace; to walke contrary to the rule of mercy and peace. I have not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them the law of faith, to call in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion the faithfulneſſe of my Fathers love, and the pretiouſneſſe of my deareſt blood. So I have not given to them the fruits of the Law of life, that they ſhould walke as a dead people, but that they ſhould live by my fountaines of living waters, by my neareſt union and rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of communion through ſpirit of
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:41463:78"/> life and Adoption; ever triumphing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing and glorying in my law of life; by which they are freed from the law of ſinne and death, according to the text <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. <hi>For the law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus hath freed them from the law of ſinne and death.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>JOHN 16. verſe 22.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And ye now therefore have ſorrow, but I will ſee you againe, and your hearts ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and your joy no man taketh from you.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe ſad complaint of Iſrael, (was) mine eyes runneth down with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, becauſe the Comforter is farre from me, he that ſhould releeve my ſoule will not looke upon me, my bowels are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, the enemy hath prevailed over me: this is the relation of the Iſrael of God, mine eye powreth downe with waters, my comforter is not farre from me, hee that will releeve my ſoule will looke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, my bowels are refreſhed, the chariots of hell hath not prevailed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, therefore though I am poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:41463:79" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:41463:79"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:41463:80"/> with ſorrow, becauſe I poſſeſſe not what I ſhall poſſeſſe; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, <hi>I ſhall ſee his face, my heart ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and my joy ſhall no man take from mee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ye now therefore have ſorrow.</p>
               <p>What the Saints beloved? are they not delivered from the power of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and tranſlated into the kingdome of my deare ſonne? have they not the ſpirit of joy and delightfull ſolace? are they not crowned in Sion with everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting joy upon their heads? doe they not rejoyce in the garments of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and perfect robes of righteouſneſſe? Have they not the oyle of joy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in ſtead of the garments of heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? and ſhall they not ſing praiſe for ever and ever more unto mee which am bleſſed for evermore? notwithſtanding they are invirond with great ſorrow and heavineſſe. Who lives amongſt Tygers, Wolves, Lyons and Beares, if not they? who are counted the baſeſt of the creature, the vileſt of the earth, the terror to the ſonnes of men, and the ſcumme of the world, if not they? who
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:41463:80"/> encounters with the Devill, makes war with the fleſh, fights againſt ſinne and all evills, if not they? if the roaring Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the devill ſeeke to devoure them, doe they not ſeeke to me the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Judah?</hi> if the fleſh doth burthen them, ſay they not with Paul who ſhall deliver them from the power of death? if ſin doth defile them, do they not deſire to be waſhed in my pretious blood? and if the law of terror affright them, doe they not fly to the law of life in Chriſt Jeſus? mine would ſinne no more, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend no more, but praiſe me evermore: Sith I have made them new creatures, formed them according to my Image, and made them conformable to my mind and pleaſure. (True it is) I imbrace them, I love them, and I delight in them to dayes everlaſting: yet my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine pleaſure hath been to hide my face for a moment, to obſcure my ſelfe for the twinckling of an eye, as though I would take my leave or farwel of them: notwithſtanding, I have done it for their conſolation, to ſhew my might and power in conſervation, and my ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peremenent bounty and love in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atitude and glorification. I that hid my
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:41463:81"/> glory, I that gave them not a footſtep for habitation, have given to them my heavenly mantion, and though I depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them of my perſonall preſence, yet my bleſſed preſence ſhall ſhine upon them in my heavenly Citie. What though for a moment they doe not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe me in the fulneſſe of communion, in the bleſſedneſſe of my beatification, in the plenitude of hope and benediction, <hi>Yet I will ſee them againe, their heart ſhall rejoyce, and their joy ſhall no man take from them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I will ſee you againe.</p>
               <p>If I come to mine, who am my Churches King of glory, I will bring her to the habitation of my heavenly glory, if I the loving bridegroome come to my beloved Church and choyſeſt Spouſe, I will make her glad with my heavenly and gratious countenance, I will remove away her teares though thouſands, her forrowes though infinite, and her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations though as the ſands upon the ſea ſhore, then ſhee that was wrapt in the duſt below, ſhall ſing glory and praiſe to me on high, for I that take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:41463:81"/> all teares, will wipe away teares from her face, <hi>For I will ſee her againe, her heart ſhall rejoyce, and her joy ſhall no man take from her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will.</p>
               <p>What I will? it was my pleaſure to excerciſe mine under tribulations, tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and tryalls, afflictions, calamities and miſeries, under penurie, ſhame and reproach, under bonds, fetters and chaines, under ſhipwrack, death and tortures, that their faith might be much more pretious then gould, their love then the pureſt gould, their patience an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer my commmiſſion concerning pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and that they might prize my deliverie and redemption, when I ſhall deliver and redeeme them from tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation. <hi>For I will ſee them againe, their heart ſhall rejoyce, and their joy ſhall no man take from them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will ſee you againe.</p>
               <p>This was Joſephs charge, ſee my face no more unleſſe you bring your yonger brother with you, this was the charge
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:41463:82"/> of David to Abner, thou ſhalt not ſee my face unleſſe thou bringſt with thee Micall Saules daughter: This is the charge of the drooping ſpirits to the watchmen of Iſraell, let us heare your voice no more, let us ſee your face no more, unleſſe you tell us where we may behold the countenance of our beloved: whilſt the watchmen ſaith they ſee him not, Chriſt ſaith he will ſee his own. <hi>I will ſee them againe, their hearts ſhall rejoyce and their joy ſhall no man take from them.</hi> Have I not looked upon you when no eye beheld you? have not I reſpected you when none reſpected you? when neither Levit nor Prieſt had compaſſion on you in the day of your wounds, then I healed you by my death, blood and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. I exalted you by my reſurrection, aſſention and mediation, and I comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted you by my adoption, union and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, as my father beheld his Iſraell in Egyptian tyrannie, to give them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery: So I beheld you in bond-ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie, to give you my richeſt bountie. As I have looked upon you being the morning ſtarre that firſt roſe in your hearts: ſo I will ſhine upon you as the morning ſunne that firſt appeared in
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:41463:82"/> your ſoules. <hi>For I will ſee you againe, your heart ſhall rejoyce, and your joy ſhall no man take from you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will ſee you,</p>
               <p>The face of <hi>Eſau</hi> was deare in the eyes of <hi>Jacob,</hi> he counted it as the face of an Angell, the face of Jeſus Chriſt is deare in the ſight of the ſaints, they count it more gratious then the countenance of all the Angels. was there an acceptation of <hi>Jacobs</hi> preſents, a ſafety of the lambs, the children and the aged through <hi>Eſaus</hi> favour? and is there not an acceptation of the offerings of the Saints, and a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from death and deſtruction by the face and favour of Jeſus Chriſt? there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are raviſhed with the joy of my countenance, ſaying O joy of joyes! O ſolace of ſolaces! O conſolation of conſolations! that flowes from me their deareſt Lord that brought them! when I ſhall ſee them againe, my countenance. will be to them moſt deare and pretious. What ſun like me that am the ſonne of righteouſneſſe? what ſtarre like me that am the morning ſtarre? the ſtarres are darkeneſſe, the ſunne is dimneſſe, the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:41463:83"/> moone is obſcurity, when I appeare in glory, heaven ſhould be no heaven if my countenance ſhould not be in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the celeſtiall places ſhould be a denn of Dragons, if I had not beene in the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall places. If glory be in the ſoule, it is becauſe I am the hope of glory, if glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry be in the heavenly place, it is becauſe I am the prince of glory. What beauty hath the firmament without the ſunne, moone, and ſtarrs? what ornament hath the earth without graſſe, hearbs, trees and plants? or what excellencies hath the ſoule without my gratious counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance? therefore my deareſt ſervants waite for the time of my appearings Is not my countenance more deare to them then the face of <hi>Eſau</hi> was to <hi>Jacob?</hi> ſith in the ſight thereof there are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for evermore, deliverie from the blacke chaines of darkeneſſe, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to eternall life, hope of the fruition of my felicitie, and praiſes from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of my grace unto eternitie, <hi>For I will ſee them againe, and their hearts ſhall rejoyce, and their joy no man ſhall take from them.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:41463:83"/>
               <p>And your hearts ſhall rejoyce.</p>
               <p>In the day of Tyre, it was ſaid of Tyre, that ſhe was the fame and glory of the world, becauſe her delights were the delights of paradice, ſhe walked in the midſt of the ſtones of fire, ſhe had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very precious ſtone as the Topaze, the the Carbuncle, the Saphire, the Onix: in the day of the Churches glory, it may be ſaid of the Church, that her delights ſurpaſſeth the delights of paradice, that ſhe walkes triumphing in the midſt of fierie tribulations, and that Chriſt her precious ſtone is more to her then all pretious ſtones, he that is to her the choyſeſt ſtone of delightment, is to her the ſtreame of rare contentment.</p>
               <p>O what citie like the citie of our God? O what ſtreames are like the ſtreames that refreſh the citie of our God? as the fountaine is only delectable, ſo the ſtreames are abſolutely delightfull, for my joyes are the joyes of my people, my rivers of ſolace their ſole delight, and my fountaine ſurpaſſing all the fountaines under heaven, if they want comfort, I make them rejoyce in the robes of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:41463:84"/> righteouſneſſe. Iſai. 61.10. <hi>I will greatly reioyce in the Lord, my ſoule ſhall be ioyfull in my God, for he hath clothed me with the garments of ſalvation, he hath co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered me with the robes of righteouſneſſe, as a bridegroome decketh himſelfe with orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and as a bride adorneth her ſelfe with her iewels.</hi> If they want ſolace, I make them to injoy the holy Ghoſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, John 16.7. <hi>Nevertheleſſe, I tell you the truth, it is expedient for you that I goe away, for if I goe not away, the comforter will not come unto you; but if I depart, I will, ſend him unto you.</hi> If they are clothed with the garments of heavineſſe, I give to them the oyle of joy &amp; gladneſſe. Iſa. 61.1. <hi>The ſpirit of the Lord is upon me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord hath anoynted me to preach good tydings unto the meeke. To appoint unto them that mourne in Sion, to give unto them beauty for aſhes, the oyle of ioy for mourning, the garments of praiſe for the ſpirit of heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that they might be called the trees of righteouſneſſe, the planting of the Lord, that he might be glorified.</hi> And if they are crowned with ſorrow and lamentation, I cauſe everlaſting joy to ſpring out of the wells of ſalvation, Iſa. 12.3. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with ioy ſhall yee draw water out of the
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:41463:84"/> wells of ſalvation.</hi> Shall my people hang down their heads like bulruſhes, lowre like the Hypocrites, and wear ſackcloth and mourning weeds? No, I would have my people dwell by my fountaines, my waters are not bitter as the waters of <hi>Marah,</hi> I would have mine refreſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with my rivers, my waters paſſe the waters of <hi>Abanah</hi> &amp; <hi>Pharpar</hi> rivers of <hi>Damaſcus.</hi> Have I not left to them the words of full conſolation? John 17.13. <hi>And now I come to thee, and theſe things I ſpeake in the world, that they might have my ioy fulfilled in themſelves,</hi> Have I not removed their feares and perturbations? John 14.1. <hi>Let not your hearts be troubled, yee beleeve in God, beleeve alſo in me.</hi> Have not I wiſhed them to rejoyce through exhortation? Phil. 4.4. <hi>Reioyce in the Lord alway, and againe I ſay reioyce.</hi> What is my bloody croſſe, my victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous death, my comfortable reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and my powerfull mediation But joy to the drooping? what is the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of my freeſt grace, my higheſt love, my richeſt mercy, and tender compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons but comfort to the mourning? What is the ſpirit of adoption whereby mine call my father Father, the ſpirit of
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:41463:85"/> obſignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherby mine injoy an inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance among them which are ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the ſpirit of ſanctification, whereby mine are ſanctified in the day of their Communion with mee their vine and royall bridegroome; but conſolation to the lamenting? as my ſprings of grace are in the throne of my grace, ſo I have filled them with the fruits of my grace, as the fountaine of my love is in the throne of love, ſo have I filled mine with my deareſt love, when I dwell in their hearts by faith which is in mee, when I rule in their conſciences by peace which is from mee, when I ſhall lodge in their ſoules through my ſpirit of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I ſhall change their garments of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation into garments of ſalvation, their mourning weeds into glorying expreſſion, and their ſighes and groanes unutterable into the ſweeteſt oration. <hi>For I will ſee them againe, and their hearts ſhall rejoyce, and their joy ſhall no man take from them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The rivers that flowed from paradice are not comparable to the ſtreames that makes glad the city of our God, thoſe were water, theſe welſprings of living water, thoſe flowed from the earthly
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:41463:85"/> paradice, theſe from the heavenly and celeſtiall paradice, by ſome of them was <hi>Bdelium</hi> and the <hi>Onix</hi> ſtone, in theſe are eternall glory, neareneſſe of union, and the fruition of eternall life and felicitie, thoſe were appointed to water the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of Eden, theſe are ordained to water and refreſh the Church of Chriſt belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, thoſe were placed in paradice by the wiſedome and love of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, theſe were placed and appointed in the Church of Chriſt redeemer: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they admire at the love of God the Father, and the ſuperemenent grace of Chriſt Mediator. Saying they ſhall heare the thing they never heard, they ſhall ſee the things they never ſaw, and they ſhall underſtand the things they never underſtood. Their joy in that day ſhall not be from the influence of the ſtarrs, my influence excelleth the influence of all ſtarrs, they ſhall not injoy the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the Moone, but the comfort of mee whoſe glory is above Sunne and Moone. What ſhall mine injoy in that day? they ſhall fully ſee the throne of grace, fully behold all the hidden, unut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable and unſearchable excellencies that are in me. What ſhall they poſſeſſe,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:41463:86"/> when they ſhall poſſeſſe me that filleth all in all things? what ſhall they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, when they ſhall be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended and invironed with my glorious preſence and the light of my counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance? therefore though the heavens and the earth ſhould bee ſilent, the moutaines and the vallies ſhould be ſtill, yet mine will glory in me their loving prince and effectionate bridegroome. <hi>Sith I will ſee them againe, their hearts ſhall rejoyce, and their joy ſhall no man take from them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And your joy no man taketh from you.</p>
               <p>O the love of our loving and glorious father! O the kindneſſe of our Lord our deare and gratious Redeemer! if mine admire at my love, my love is admirable love, if mine contemplate of my grace, my grace is ſuperemenent grace, when they were in the vaſt and roaring wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, I allured them, and brought them into a wilderneſſe, and there I ſpake comfortably unto them. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.14. <hi>Therefore behold I will allure her, and bring her into the wilderneſſe, and ſpake comfortably unto her.</hi> When mine were
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:41463:86"/> toſſed like a ſhip with the roaring waves, reeling like a drunken man, were welneigh daſhed in peeces by the crag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie rockes and ſhelves, I laid a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for them of pretious Stones and Saphires. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.11. <hi>O thou afflicted, toſſed with tempeſt and not comforted, I will lay thy ſtones with faire colours, and lay thy foundation with Saphirs.</hi> When they wanted joyes, I gave them joyes firmer then the earth upon its center, more fixed then the fixed ſtarres, more ſtable then the ſublunarie creatures. Is my righteouſnes, everlaſting righteouſneſs? &amp; is not my comfort everlaſting? is my deare hearts blood of an eternall value? &amp; is not my conſolations eternall? is my communion and bleſſedneſſe for ever and ever? and are not my joyes for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and ever? If mine have life, their life is hid in me, if mine have peace, then their peace is treaſured in me, if mine have joy, their joy is joy in me. Hath the miſts taken away the light of the Sunne? No: Hath the mortality of the body taken away the immortality of the ſoule? No: Or can any take away the conſolation of my Redeemed? No: Had I not given to my Redeemed ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:41463:87"/> righteouſneſſe, eternall life, an inheritance immutable, then their joy had beene momentanie and tranſitorie: but becauſe I have given them an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting righteouſneſſe. Dan. 9.24. <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty weeks are determined upon thy people, and upon thy holy citie, to finiſh the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and to make an end of ſinnes, and to make reconciliation for iniquity, &amp; to bring in everlaſting righteouſneſſe, and to ſeale up the viſion and propheſie, and to annoynt the moſt holy.</hi> Eternall life. <hi>John</hi> 10.28. <hi>And I give unto them eternall life, &amp; they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver periſh, neither ſhall any man plucke them out of mine hands.</hi> An inheritance immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and immutable. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their joy is not tranſitory and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentanie. After once I bring my redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the inheritance immortall and incontaminate, they ſhall ſing nothing but praiſe, honour, glory, power, might, truth, mercy, ſtrength and thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to my Father bleſſed for ever; and to me bleſſed for ever more. They ſhall know of no ſinne in the fleſh, they ſhall not heare the accuſations of the law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the tribunall ſeate of juſtice, they ſhall not hearken to the temptations of the devill, they ſhall not feele the burden
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:41463:87"/> of ſinne, nor be affrighted at the feares of death and hell, but they ſhall injoy an immediate communion and fruition of my glory to everlaſting. <hi>For I wil take away their heavines, their heart ſhall rejoyce and their joy no man taketh from them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>JOHN 15.12.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>This is my Commandement, that ye love one another as I have loved you.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>RAre is the Sunne in reſpect of beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, light and operation, rare are the pretious jewells in reſpect of richneſſe, vertue and eſtimation: ſo rare is the love of Chriſt to us through gifts, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and communication, as the myrrh and the drops thereof, as the ſweet raine and the ſhowers thereof, as the bedew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dew and the overſpreading thereof, ſo is the influence of Chriſts freeſt grace, and the expreſſion of his deareſt love, according to the text. John 15.12. <hi>This is my Commandement, that ye love one another as I have loved you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nothing is ſo pretious as Chriſts blood, nothing ſo victorious as his death, nothing is ſo pure as his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe;
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:41463:88"/> ſo nothing is ſo tender as the love of our deareſt Lord that bought us; who hath left the higheſt throne of glory for the bondſlaves of miſeries? but the prince of glory? who hath ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene light and darkeneſſe, betwixt heaven and hell, betwixt eternall juſtice, and the children of unrighteouſneſſe: but the Lord our righteouſneſſe? 1 Pet. 3.18. <hi>For Chriſt alſo hath once ſuffered for ſinne, the juſt for the uniuſt, that hee might bring us to God, being put to death in the fleſh, but quickned by the ſpirit.</hi> Who hath beene ſurety for mine in reſpect of the acquirie of Redemption, to make up the breach of union, to anſwer the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe for juſtification, to atchieve glorious communion, beatification, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, felicitie and the fruition of my preſence; but he that ſhall ſtand for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver mediatour and interceſſour in my preſence? or who hath indured that mocking, that buffeting, that ſcorning, that arraigning, that condemning but he in whom there is no condemnation but eternall life and ſalvation. Act. 4.12. <hi>Neither is there Salvation in any other, for there is no other name under heaven given among men whereby we muſt be ſaved.</hi> He
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:41463:88"/> hath laid downe his life for them that were deprived of the hope of life, hee ſpilt his deareſt blood for them that were involved in their blood, hee hath ventured his death for the lives of them that were the children of death, had a child of wrath died for a child of wrath, that ſhould not have been excellent, had a child of death, dyed for a ſon of death that ſhould not have beene ſuperexcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, but for the beloved of the father to die for miſerable catives and captives, that is tranſcendent. The death of mee the Lord of life is more then a thouſand Lords, the death of mee the prince of peace is more then the death of tenne thouſand princes, the death of mee who am King of Kings is more then the death of all the Kings and Monarches under heaven. I looked and behold the Angels hid their faces, all creatures hid their heads: Sith none could make up the breach of union, a glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation in my fathers preſence, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer death through death, overcome the devill through power, blot out im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity through righteouſneſſe, remove ſinne through blood, make peace through atonement, and by grace and
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:41463:89"/> glory bring the poore ſoule to eternall glory. Iſay 59.16. <hi>And he ſaw that there was no man, and wondered that there was no interceſſour, therefore his arme brought ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation unto him, and his righteouſneſſe it ſuſtained him.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>laſt. But wee all with open face, beholding as in a glaſſe the glory of the Lord, are changed into the ſame Image from glory to glory, even as by the Spirit of the Lord.</hi> Out of my love I give rare gifts and graces to my Saints and ſervants. Who hath opened the treaſures of wiſedome and knowledge? if not I; who hath broken open the treaſure-houſe of heaven, opened the throne of grace, unlocked the mercy ſeate? if not I; who hath placed the heavenly minds in the heavenly places, bleſſed the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, delivered from the curſe with ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall bleſſings, and made them that have taſted my love attaine to the height of my love? but I. I powre my water up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the thirſty; I give my bread to the hungry, my cloath of righteouſneſſe to the naked, and my deareſt mercy and love to the loveleſſe. I power out my ſpirit upon my ſervants, ſhew my viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the young, and give my dreames to the old. Acts 2.17. <hi>And it ſhall come
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:41463:89"/> to paſſe in thoſe dayes ſaith the Lord, I will power out my ſpirit upon all fleſh, and your ſonnes and your daughters ſhall propheſie, and your yong men ſhall ſee viſions, and your ould men ſhall dreame dreames.</hi> My gifts are not of gold, but of that which is more pretious then the gold of Ophir, my gifts are not jewels, gemmes, and pretious ſtones. But that which is more rich then jewels, gemmes and pretious ſtones. My gifts are not earthly trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, morrall righteouſneſſe, worldly, wealth, and things terren and ſubluna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: but heavenly treaſures, and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly righteouſneſſe, celeſtiall wealth, and things ſublime, and heavenly. Hence mine receive abundance from me, the the fulneſſe of the Godhead dwelt in me bodily. <hi>Colloſians</hi> 2.6. verſe <hi>For in him dwelleth all the fullneſſe of the Godhead bodily.</hi> Hence mine receive grace and truth from the fulneſſe of grace and truth: as I have ſpoken, and mine confeſſe. John 1.16. <hi>And of his fulneſſe have wee all receiued and grace for grace.</hi> Out of my love, I will not forſake mine in the midſt of all their tribulation and temptations, though the heaven ſhould frowne, and the earth ſhould
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:41463:90"/> lowre, the conſcience ſhould terrifie, juſtice ſhould amaze, death ſhould trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſinne ſhould burden, the Devill ſhould roare, the fleſh ſhould aſſault, all evills ſhould environ: notwithſtanding I will not forſake my peculiar: though principalities, though powers, though death, though famine, though perill, though ſword, though hell, though law, though ſinne, though the grave, and all evills ſhould beſet mine, yet will I not leave them. I love them in wants as if they had abundance, in tribulation as if they were free from tribulation, in temptation as if they were free from temptation, And in ſheep skins and goats skins as if they had cloath of gold beſet with the rareſt jewels. What if they are ſtoned for my name ſake? what if they be baniſhed for my teſtimony? what if they ſhould be wracked for the witneſſe of the word of my truth? what if they had not a hole with the fox nor a neſt with the birds? yet I will not ſhut them out of my preſence. Have I not given a teſtimony concerning them. Heb. 11.36, 37, 38, 39. <hi>And others had triall of cruell mockings and ſcourgings, yea, moreover of bonds and impriſonment, They
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:41463:90"/> were stoned, they were ſawne aſunder, were tempted, were ſlaine with the ſword, they wandered about in ſheep skins, and goats skins, being deſtitute, afflictet, tormented: of whom the world was not worthy. They wandered in the deſarts, and in mountains, and denns and caves of the earth. And all theſe have obtained a good report through faith, receiued not the promiſe.</hi> When <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> my ſervants were in priſon, did I not make them ſing ſongs of my dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt love? When <hi>Peter</hi> was in priſon, was not the Angel of my preſence by him? when my ſervant Steeven was ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, did I not make his face to ſhine as an Angel? and when my ſervants were in the fire furnace, have I not delivered them from the furnace of fiety afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? I am the rock, when there is no rocke, I am the refuge, when there is no refuge, &amp; I am their hope and horne of ſalvation, when there is neither hope nor horne of ſalvation. Hence mine may conclude with my ſervant. Pſal. 18.18. <hi>They prevented me in the day of my calamitie, but the Lord was my stay.</hi> Out of my love I have loved them freely. I regarded neither their righteouſneſſe, their holyneſſe, their performances, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:41463:91" rendition="simple:additions"/> their prayers, their doings, nor their excellencies, neither their purity, their innocency, nor their integritie, I have lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved my redeemed, and my juſtified free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I have reſpected my reconciled free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and I regarded my adopted and my glorified freely.</p>
               <p>Though thouſands ſhould have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to me the vertue of the ſonne the moone and ſtarres, the riches of ſeas of mountaines and of the vallies, or the free will of the freewillers: notwithſtanding I would refuſe it. If I lay downe my life for my ſheep, is it not out of the freeneſſe of my love? John 10.11. <hi>I am the good ſhepheard, the good ſhepheard giveth his life for his ſheep.</hi> If I give my life for my Church, is it not out of my tender and deare affection? Epheſ. 5.25. <hi>Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands love your wives, even as Chriſt alſo loved the Church and gave himſelfe for it.</hi> If I give to mine the riches of hidden trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, the glory of the heavenly manti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the ſure and firme mercies which are treaſured in my breaſts, is it not love of my tendereſt care and love? Hence out of my love, I expreſſe my deareſt &amp; tendereſt love given to mine, which eye cannot ſee, which eare
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:41463:91"/> cannot heare, nor mind conceive. 1 Cor. 2 9 <hi>But as it is written, Eye hath not ſeen, eare heard, neither hath entered into the heart of man, the things which God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them that love him.</hi> I have loved them ſo dearely, that I will be their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in grace, their eternall glory, and their expreſſion of glory, who was their hope and glory. Col. 1.27. <hi>To whom God would make known what is the riches of the glory of this mistery among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils, whsch is Chriſt in you the hope of glory.</hi> Who makes them to rejoyce under the the hope of glory? If not I. Rom. 5.1.2. <hi>Therefore being iuſtified by faith, we have peace with God through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whom alſo we have acceſſe by faith into this grace, wherein we ſtand, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in hope of the glory of God.</hi> Who makes them paſſe one from glory to glory? If not I. 2 Cor. 3. laſt <hi>But we all with open face, behoulding as in a glaſſe, the glory of the Lord, are changed into the ſame Image, from glory to glory: even as by the ſpirit of the Lord.</hi> Am I not their glory and crowne of life? Am I not their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and crowne of righteouſneſſe? Am not I their glory and crowne of mercy. Pſal. 103.3, 4. <hi>Who forgiveth all thine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities,
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:41463:92"/> and healeth all thy diſeaſes, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemeth thy life from deſtruction, who crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thee with loving kindneſſe, and tender mercies.</hi> The glory of my love is tyed to the ſweetneſſe of my peace, the glory of my grace to my acceptation: Epheſ. 1.6. <hi>To the praiſe of the glory of his grace, wherein he hath made us accepted in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved.</hi> The praiſe of my glory to the choiſe of my election. Ephes 1.12. <hi>That we ſhould be to the praiſe of his glory who first truſted in Chriſt.</hi> The aſſurance and ſeale of my redemption to the praiſe of my glory. Epheſ. 1.14. <hi>Which is the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of our inheritance, untill the redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the purchaſed poſſeſſion: unto the praiſe of his glory.</hi> The collocation in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly places to the honour of my ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emenent grace. Epheſ. 2.6.7. <hi>And hath raiſed us up together, and hath made us ſit together in Heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus, that in the ages to come he might ſhew the exceeding riches of his grace in his kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towards us through Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> What beatitude? What communion? What benediction? What frution? What felicitie? Or what glory can any injoy without me the effulgencie, the character and glory of my father? hath
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:41463:92"/> the rivers waters without the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines? No, Hath the ayre light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Sunne? no, or can any poſſeſſe glory without my glory? no. Hence I have tould my choiſe and deareſt ones. John 17.22. <hi>And the glory which thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt me, J have given them, that they may be one even as we are one.</hi> And becauſe I have given them this firſt glory, they ſing of my ſecond glory, worſhipping me that lives for ever, &amp; falling down be fore my throne of glory. Apoc. <hi>And when thoſe beaſts gave glory &amp; honour &amp; thanks to him that ſate on the throne, who liveth for ever and ever. The foure and twenty Elders fall downe before him that ſate on the throne and worſhip him that liveth for ever and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; and caſt their Crownes before the throne, ſaying, Thou art worthy O Lord, to receive glory, and honour, and power, for thou haſt created all things, and for thy pleaſure they are and were created.</hi> And they ſing not onely of my love in word, but alſo in deede. Anſwering my command, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving one another as I have loved them. <hi>John.</hi> 15.12. <hi>This is my Commandement that ye love one another as J have loved you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Philoſopher ſaith, that the firſt
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:41463:93"/> moveable is moved by Angels, and all ſecundarie motions are moved by the firſt motion or moveable, it is affirmed by the ſpirit of glory, that the love of the ſaints to God the Father and of each to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards each other, is from that love the Father hath ſhewed towards them. Joh. 1.4.10.12. <hi>Herein is love, not that we lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved God, but that he loved us: and ſent his ſonne to bee the propiciation for our ſinnes. No man hath ſeene God at any time, if wee love one another, God dwelleth in us, and his love is perfected in us.</hi> If they are deare in affection, is it not through my union? they are deare members, pretious bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and loving ſpouſes, ſith I have joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the members to mee their head, I have ingrafted them into me their vine, and I have eſpouſed them to me their bridegroome, if they injoy fellowſhip one with another, it is not through my Covenant? I have not only given them communion with my Father to injoy fellowſhip with my Father, communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with my ſelfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o injoy an inheritance in my treaſures, but I have given mine communion &amp; fellowſhip one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; that they might have joy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectation each with other. 1 John 1.3.
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:41463:93"/> 
                  <hi>That which wee have ſeene and heard, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare we unto you, that ye alſo may have fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with us, and truly our fellowſhip is with the father, and with his ſonne Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Hath the aire light and not from the ſunne? hath the hand and foot mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and not from life? and hath mine fellowſhip, and not through my fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip? as I have given them the glory of eternall fruition, the honour of perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall conſervation. John 17.11. <hi>And now I am no more in the world, but theſe are in the world, and I come to thee holy father, keepe through thine owne name, thoſe whom thou haſt given me, that they may bee one as we are.</hi> So I have given mine the glory of union, hence I have made them one as I and the father are one. John 17.22. <hi>And the glory which thou gaveſt me, I have given them, that they may be one, even as wee are one.</hi> I am not only glorified in mine by faith that is in mee, by hope which is by mee, by affection towards me, but alſo by their love towards my choiſeſt people. John 17.10. <hi>And all mine are thine, and thine are mine, and I am glorified in them.</hi> When I ſit Lord and King of the conſcience, is there not peace and ſweetneſſe? when I ſit Lord
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:41463:94"/> commander of the will? is there not peace and lowlineſſe? when I ſit onely overſwayer over the affection, is there not the tendereſt and deareſt delectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? ſo when I throw out the black King of death and darkeneſſe, is there not love, delight and delectation? when I raigne king of peace and love in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, I remove envie, hatred, malice, wrath, furie, debate, ſtrife, backbiting, ſlanderings, whiſperings, grudgings, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinings, murmurings, for when I fill mine with joyes above all ſorrow, with loves above all loves, and with my reſt above all reſts, are they not amiable? when they apprehend my death victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, my reſurrection triumphous, my mediation efficatious, and my croſſe glorious: are they not peaceable? my Father dwelleth in them, his love abides in them, and rules in them; doth not his free love remaine in the conſcience? doth not his rich love abide in the heart? and his ſtrong love in the affections? hence comes in the witneſſe of the ſpirit. 1 John 4.17. <hi>Herein is our love made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ct, that wee may have boldneſſe in the day of Judgement? becauſe as hee is, ſo are wee in this world.</hi> Therefore my people are
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:41463:94"/> a quiet people, for they are of the kingdome of my peace and patience. Apoc. 1.9. <hi>I John who alſo am your brother and companion in tribulation, and in the kingdome and patience of Jeſus Chriſt: was in the Iſle that is called Patmos, for the word of God, and for the teſtimonie of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> I turne Lyons into Lambs, Tygers into Sheepe, Woolves into Doves, and Serpents and Ravenous Beaſts into Turtles, therefore they feede together without killing and ſlaying one another. <hi>Iſay</hi> 35.9.10. <hi>No Lyon ſhall bee there, nor no ravenous beast ſhall goe up thereon, it ſhall not be found there, And the ranſomed of the Lord ſhall returne and come to Sion, with ſongs and everlaſting joy upon their heads. They ſhall obtaine joy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſorrow and ſighing ſhall flee away. Iſay</hi> 65.25. <hi>The Wolfe and the Lambe ſhall feede together, and the Lyon ſhall eate ſtraw like the bullocke, and the duſt ſhall bee the Serpents meate, they ſhall not hurt nor deſtoy in all my holy Mountaine, ſaith the Lord.</hi> I will neither admit of wolves, of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, or ravenous beaſts, of Lyons or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring dogges to joyne with my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and peculiar. Mine ſhall not fight with ſword or ſpeare, with ſhield nor
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:41463:95"/> buckler, with Helmet nor Habergion, they ſhall not overcome hell, death, the devill and all evills with the heeles of great horſes: but with my deareſt blood, and the word of my Teſtimony. Apoc. 12.11. <hi>And they overcame him by the blood of the lamb, and by the word of their teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: and they loved not their lives unto the death.</hi> I know the power of my love binds them, the power of my grace con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraines them, the power of my mercy leades them, to learne meekneſſe of me their Lord and maſter. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29. <hi>Take my yoake upon you, and learne of mee, for I am meeke and lowly in heart, and yee ſhall find reſt unto your ſoules.</hi> As my king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is not meate, drinke, or cloth: but joy, &amp; peace, &amp; love by the holy Ghoſt: ſo my people, the inhabitants and dwellers in my kingdome are not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordious, contentious, quarrelous: but loving, peaceable and joyous. Rom. 14.17. <hi>For the kingdome of God is not meate and drinke, but righteouſneſſe, and peace, &amp; joy in the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> I have redeemed them from the earth and made them the firſt fruits to my Father? I have ſet them in the heavenly places, have I taken away all enmitie betwixt my Father &amp; them:
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:41463:95"/> that they ſhould not live in wrath &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention. It is my gratious pleaſure that mine ſhould love one another, as I have loved them. I would have their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſo deere, their loves ſo tender, that they ſhould out of their deareſt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and tendereſt love live one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. What ſhall the Citizens of my heavenly Jeruſalem bee as ſtrangers? what ſhall they that are of my Fathers family be as Alians? or they that bee ſo neare to me as members to the body branches to the vine, as the eſpouſed to the bridegroome, live as a people Alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated and eſtranged? No. Where is their care over each other? where is their glorying in each other? when they neither ſee nor behold the ſweet and gratious diſpoſition of each other? wherein am I glorified whilſt their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections are as farre remote as their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations, and their loves as farre diſtant as their dwellings. What breaches? what diſcontents ariſeth, when the world makes warre, the legaliſts ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and the Angels of light caſts falſe and bitter aſperſions, my love hath been ſo deare and tender towards them, that I have made them temples of the Spirit
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:41463:96"/> of glory, in which I might expreſſe my glory: Did my father fill the Temple with his glory? and doe not I fill mine with my glory? whilſt I in them am the hope of glory. Col. 1.27. <hi>To whom God would make knowne what is the mistery of this glory among the Gentiles, which is Chriſt in you the hope of glory.</hi> I have made them a dwelling place, a habitation of dwelling by my ſpirit. Epheſ. 2.21, 22. <hi>In whom all the building fitly framed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, groweth unto an holy Temple in the Lord, in whom you alſo are builded together for an habitation of God through the Spirit.</hi> I have made them Tabernacles fit for my love and favour. John 17. laſt. <hi>And I have declared unto them thy name, and will declare it, that the love wherewith thou haſt loved me, may bee in them, and I in them:</hi> And ſhall not mine live as my choyſeſt &amp; deareſt ones? what difference between the children of <hi>Sinai,</hi> &amp; the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi> what difference between the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the bondwoman, and the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Jeruſalem? if they live not as my Saints at Jeruſalem? Oh what honour? what glory have mine attained? and grace have they atchieved? whilſt of them in record it is recorded. Acts 2.44.
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:41463:96"/> 
                  <hi>And all that beleeved were together, and had all things common, the laſt verſe. Praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God and having favour with all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: and the Lord added to the church dayly ſuch as ſhould be ſaved.</hi> I have loved mine with an everlaſting love, hence I paſſe by their ſins, their weaknes, their infirmities, and all their evills. Though they were toſſed like the lofty and roaring waves of the ſea: I gave to them a rich and ſure foundation. Iſaiah 54.11.10. <hi>O thou afflicted, toſſed with tempeſt, and not comforted, behold I will lay thy ſtones with faire colours, and lay thy foundations with Saphirs, and I will make thy windowes of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates, and thy gates of Carbuncles, and all thy borders of pretious ſtones.</hi> Though they were left as a widow forſaken, and as a virgin relinquiſt, I have not left them nor forſaken them. Iſay 54.6.7. <hi>For the Lord hath called thee as a woman for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaken, and grieved in ſpirit, and a wife of youth when thou waſt refuſed ſaith thy God, For a ſmall, moment have I forſaken thee but with great mercies will I gather thee,</hi> Though they were not accounted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of a being upon the face of the earth, I have given them a heavenly habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 2 Cor. 5.1. <hi>For we know that if our
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:41463:97"/> earthly houſe of this tabernacle were diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, wee have a building of God, an houſe not made with hands, eternall in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens.</hi> And ſhall not mine love mine for ever? I will not have my bruiſed quaſt, I love the ſmoaking flax, and the bruiſed reed, I will not have my broken diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſteemed, my wounded deſpiſed, my ſicke neglected, my priſoners not viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, my feeble unrefreſhed, my poore begging bread, and my diſtreſſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences uncomforted. To what end doe I commit them to my Churches care, to belie, ſlander, backbite, and ſpeake evill of my people? No, to frowne, lowre, and pet againſt my weake ones? No, that they might breake, bruiſe and tread under foot my weakeſt ſervants? No, but that they ſhould refreſh, comfort, ſolace and refo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilate my weake ones, and my pooreſt ſervants: as their names, their lives, their liberties, their conſciences are deare to me: ſo I will have their names, lives, liberties, and deaths pretious in my peoples ſight.</p>
               <p>What rarer then the influences of my grace from my ſuperemenent grace? Yet that have I beſtowed upon my jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:41463:97"/> what is purer then the garments of my ſalvation? Yet that have I given to my choiſeſt ones? and what more preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then my deareſt blood? yet that I give to my deareſt ſaints. As I cauſe the ſweet influence of the Plejades to reſt upon and in the plants of the feild, ſo I cauſe the ſweet influence of my grace to reſt and abide in my peculiar people, and ſhal not mine diſtribute their goods, make known their gifts, and ſpend their lives each for other? 1 John 4.10.11. <hi>In this was manifeſt the love of God towards us, bacauſe that God ſent his only begotten ſonne into the world, that we might live through him, herein is love, Not that we loved God, but that he loved us, and ſent his ſonne to be the propiciation for our ſinnes, Beloved, if God ſo loved us, we ought alſo to love one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</hi> I have loved mine with a faithfull love, am I not that faithfull witneſſe? I witneſſe faithfully, are my promiſes yea and Amen, and am not I yea and Amen? doe I ſanctifie mine with my truth? and am I not the truth it ſelfe: If mine have infirmities and failings, I tell it not in the gates of <hi>Gath,</hi> nor in the ſtreets of <hi>Aske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> I carrie not the failings of my people from the throne of my grace to the barr
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:41463:98"/> of my juſtice, but I free them from the barr of juſtice, and accquite them before the throne of grace. And ſhall not mine love mine, with a faithfull love, and an intire affection? what in word, in tongue, in lookes, in ſhadowes? No, But in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of ſpirit, and faithfullneſſe of heart, not ſpeaking evill of mine, as <hi>Doeg</hi> did of <hi>David,</hi> not uncovering the ſhame of mine as <hi>Ham</hi> of <hi>Noah,</hi> but ſpeking gratiouſly of mine as <hi>Jonathan</hi> of the Lords anoynted. Anſwering my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. 1 John 3.18 <hi>My little children let us not love in word neither in tongue, but in deed and in truth.</hi> I have loved mine freely. They were veſſells of wrath, bound under the chaines of hell, death and darkeneſſe, under the black clawes of that roaring Lyon the Devill, not withſtanding, I looked upon them in mercy, I regarded not the multitude of their performances, the beauty of their righteouſneſſe, &amp; the excellency of their gifts, I made the beggar to ſit amongſt Princes. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.9. <hi>He raiſeth up the poore out of the duſt, &amp; lifteth up the beggar from the dunghill, to ſet them amongst Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to make them inherite the throne of
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:41463:98"/> glory: For the pillars of the earth are the Lords, and he hath ſet the world upon them,</hi> I make the ofſcurings of the earth through my blood, Kings and Prieſts to God my father, Apoc. 1.5.6. <hi>And from Jeſus Chriſt who is the faithfull witneſſe, and the firſt begotten from the dead, and the Prince of the Kings of the earth unto him that hath loved us, and waſhed us from our ſinnes in his owne blood. And hath made us Kings and Prieſts unto God and his father, to him be glory &amp; dominion, for ever &amp; ever Amen.</hi> I made the diſtreſſed vallies of death and darkeneſſe, to injoy an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance amongſt my ſanctified by faith that is in me. Acts 26.18. <hi>To open their eyes, and to turne them from darkneſſe to light, and from the power of Satan unto God, that they may receive the forgiveneſſe of ſinnes, and inheritance amongſt them that are ſanctified by faith that is in me.</hi> And ſhall mine not love mine? in ſheep skins &amp; goats skins, as if they weare the cloth of gould beſet with Diamonds? if they were upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dunghil, as if they were the greateſt, the honourable the richeſt, and the noble. Shall they not eye the weake, the meaneſt and the poore of my redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:41463:99"/> flocke, as well as the fat, &amp; luſty of my flocke beloved? Jam. 2.3, 4, 5. <hi>And yee have reſpect to him that wearrch the gay cloathing, and ſay unto him ſit thou heare in a good place. And ſay to the poore ſtand thou there, or ſit here under my foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole, are yee not partiall in your ſelves, and are become judgers of evill thoughts. Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken my beloved brethren: hath not God choſen the poore of this world, rich in faith, and heires of the kingdome which he hath promiſed to them that love him.</hi> I have lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved mine ſo dearely, that I have layd down my life for mine, I might have reaſoned and ſaid, theſe are Rebels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my glory, Traytours againſt the throne of my grace, Tranſgreſſours of my divine and pureſt law, they have undervalued my word of gratious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, they have deſpiſed the word of my ſanctification, and they have diſreſpected the doctrine of free and plentious redemption. Who have advanced their owne righteouſneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove my righteouſneſſe? if not they, Who hath ſet their poſts by my poſts? if not they, Who hath diſeſteemed the blood of my covenant? if not they, and
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:41463:99"/> ſhall not mine love mine to the death? yea, if I the great ſhepheard, the tender Bridegroome, the pleaſant vine and King of my Church have layd down my life for my Church, ſhall not the ſheep, the ſpouſe, the branches and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of my kingdome lay downe their lives for each other? O my people, I am the ſearcher of the hearts and tryer of the raines, I walke in the midſt of the golden Candleſticks, to ſee what love is or ſhould be in the midſt of my people. I ſee my ſick not viſited, my poore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed, my naked unclothed, my hung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and thirſty not ſatisfied, my deareſt Jewells ſlandered, my pretious ſervants defamed, and thoſe that ſpeake the truth diſdained. In ſtead of patience, prudence, gentleneſſe, mildneſſe, and gratiouſneſſe of ſpirit, there is backebiting, lying, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſlandering in every corner of the City. But have they not cauſe to tender one another dearly? are they not fellow Citizens and of the houſhould of of my father? Epheſ. 2.19. <hi>Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yee are no more ſtrangers and forreners, but fellow citizens with the ſaints and of the
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:41463:100"/> houſhould of God.</hi> Are they not my <hi>bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches whom I eſteeme moſt deerely. John</hi> 15.5. <hi>I am the vine, ye are the branches, he that abideth in me, and I in him, the ſame brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth forth much fruit, for without me ye can doe nothing.</hi> Are they not they that are called to communion with mee that am their deare Lord and Maſter. 1 Cor. 1.9. <hi>God is faithfull, by whom yee were called unto the fellowſhip of his Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> They are not baſe but noble, all the Kings and Monarches under heaven are not comparable to one of the Kings that I have made to God my Father through my blood moſt pretious. They are Kings of earthly Kingdomes, mine of heavenly and celeſtiall Kingdomes: They are Kings by a Royall progenie, mine are Kings through my blood un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled, they have crownes of pure gold &amp; pretious ſtones, mine have crowns of life and righteouſneſſe, they have guards of men to attend them, mine guards of Angells &amp; the beloved ſaints. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1 laſt. <hi>Are they not all miniſtring Spirits; ſent forth to miniſter for them who ſhall bee hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Salvation.</hi> Their cloth is better
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:41463:100"/> then the cloth of gol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their riches bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the riches of jewells, and their wealth more excellent then the wealth hid in the ſands. Though the devill would devoure them, I will ſave them, though the fleſh make war with them, I will ſupport them, though death would deſtroy them, I will give them my ſalvation. Haback. 3.13. <hi>Thou wen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt forth for the Salvation of the people, even for Salvation with thine anoynted, thou woundest the head out of the houſe of the wicked, by diſcovering the foundation unto the neck Selah.</hi> I am their King, and ſhall not I command them? their Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome, and ſhall not I will them? their loving Mediatour, and ſhall I not wiſh them to love on another? I know, if I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand them to endure bounds, chaines &amp; impriſonments for my ſake, that they will obey me, I know if I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand them to endure poverty for my poore, penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for my diſtreſſed, miſerie for my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, that they will ſubject to me. My voice is as deare to them as heaven, my commands as acceptable as my joyes; and my wiſhes. As my love, my glory
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:41463:101"/> and my righteouſneſſe. Therefore they will anſwere my command of love: as it is recorded. John 15.12. <hi>This is my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, that ye love one another, as I have loved you.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="biblical_exegesis">
            <pb n="187" facs="tcp:41463:101"/>
            <head>A CONFESSION OF OVR FAITH, <hi>According to the Order of</hi> the GOSPEL.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>Firſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WEE beleeve that Jeſus Chriſt is the Eternall Sonne of God, who was with the Father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the world was; Appointed by an Eternall Election Mediatour, Redeemer and Reconciler of all thoſe whom the Father out of his Eternall and free love had ordained unto Eternall Life. John 1.14.</hi> And the word was made fleſh, and dwelt among us, and wee beheld his glory, the glory as of the onely begotten Sonne
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:41463:102"/> of the Father full of grace and truth. John <hi>1.18.</hi> No man hath ſeene God at any time, the onely begotten Son which is in thy boſome of the Father, he hath declared him. John <hi>17.3.</hi> And this is life Eternall, that they might know thee the only true God and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>Secondly.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVE beleeve that it was the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers divine pleaſure to or daine Jeſus Chr ſt to bee King over his Church, &amp; peculiar, and the ſole &amp; only Prophet from which the Church ſhould receive all her treaſures of Divine &amp; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt wiſedome. Epheſ. 1.21, 22, 23.</hi> Far a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all principalitie, and power, and might, and dominion, and every name that is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not only in this world, but alſo in the world to come. And hath put all things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his feet, and gave him to be head over all things to the Church which is his body, the fulneſs of him that filleth all in all. Deut. <hi>18.18.</hi> I will raiſe them up a Prophet from among their brethren like unto thee, and will put my words in his mouth, and he ſhall ſpeak unto them all that I ſhall command him. Col. <hi>1.3.</hi> Wee give thnnkes to God and the
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:41463:102"/> Father of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord praying al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies for you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>Thirdly.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WEE beleeve that the Church of Jeſus Chriſt was freely choſen and ſelected out of the free and eternall love of the Father reſting in the boſome of Jeſus Chriſt: to the end that it might be partaker of all the heavenly treaſures of divine grace and righteouſneſſe, made conformable to the will of God the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father, and to the minde of Jeſus Chriſt the bleſſed and glorious Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Epheſ. 1.4, 5.</hi> According as hee hath choſen us in him before the foundation of the world, that wee ſhould be holy and without blame before him in love, having predeſtinated us unto the Adoption of Sonnes by Jeſus Chriſt to himſelfe, according to the good pleaſure of his will. <hi>2</hi> Pet. <hi>1.4.</hi> Wherby are given unto us exceeding great and preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promiſes, that by theſe you might be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the divine nature, having eſcaped the corruption that is in the world through luſt. Rom. <hi>8.27.</hi> And he that ſearcheth the hearts knoweth what is the mind of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:41463:103"/> becauſe hee maketh interſeſſion for the Saints according to the will of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>Fourthly.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WEE beleeve that Jeſus Chriſt the Lord of life and ſalvation laid downe his life in ſpeciall for her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the abſolute and divine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of the Father, to the intent that hee might confirme upon her the ſupereminent riches of glory, the excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding riches of mercy, and the marvilous diſpenſation of his marvilous Kindneſſe which proceedes alone from his free and divine pleaſure. Acts 20.28.</hi> Take heede therefore unto your ſelves, and to all the flo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke over which the Holy Ghoſt hath made you overſeers, to feede the Church of God, which he hath purchaſed with his own blood. Rom. <hi>8.32.</hi> He that ſpared not his own Son, but delivered him up for us all, how ſhould he not with him freely give us all things? Eph. <hi>5.25.</hi> Husbands love your wives even as Chriſt loved the Church, and gave himſelfe for it. Apoc. <hi>5.9.10.</hi> And they ſang a new ſong, ſaying; thou art worthy to take the booke, and to open the ſeales thereof, for thou wast ſlaine, and haſt redeemed us to
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:41463:103"/> God out of every kindred, tongue, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and nation, and hath made us unto our God Kings and Prieſts, and we ſhall raigne on the earth. Col. <hi>1.27.</hi> To whom God would make knowne what is the riches of the glory of this miſtery among the Gentills which is Chriſt in you the hope of glory. Eph. <hi>2.7.</hi> That in ages to come he might ſhew the exceeding riches of his grace, in his kindneſſe towards us through Christ Jeſus.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>Fiftly.</head>
               <p>WEE beleeve that the Church which hath beene redeemed by the pretious bloud of our Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, that ſhe hath received the ſpirit of Adoption, Glory, Sanctification and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation: to the intent that ſhe might be abſolutely aſſured of everlaſting glory of God the Father, the pretious riches of grace in Jeſus Chriſt, and the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which are in Chriſt yea and Amen. Vnto the praiſe and glory of the Father. Rom. 5.2. <hi>By whom alſo we have acceſſe by faith into this grace, wherein we ſtand and reioyce in hope of the glory of God.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. <hi>But of him are ye in Christ Jeſus who
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:41463:104"/> of God is made unto us wiſedome, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and Sanctification and Redemption.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. <hi>For all the promiſes of God in him are yea, and in him Amen unto the glory of God by us.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>Sixtly.</head>
               <p>WEE beleeve that Jeſus Chriſt having paid an Eternall price and ranſome to his Father in the behalfe of his Church and peculiar, therefore the price in it ſelfe being eternall, infinite and unmeaſurable, doth comprehend in it ſelfe a remedie for the miſeries of All mankinde whatſoever. <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.28. <hi>Even as the ſonne of man came not to bee miniſtred unto, but to mimiſter, and to give a ranſom his life for many.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Who gave himſelfe a ranſome for all to be teſtified in due time.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>Seventhly.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WE beleeve that the Goſpel of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is a Goſpel univerſall, and is to be preached, amongſt all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures whatſoever: to the intent that the
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:41463:104"/> Father of eternall love and mercy might ſingle out his people out of the world, ſhew forth the dignity of his owne Son, manifeſt the marvilous riches of his owne glory, and leave the Creature without excuſe.</hi> Mat. <hi>28.19.</hi> Goe yee therefore and teach all Nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the Holy Ghoſt. Col. <hi>1.23.</hi> If ye continue in the faith, grounded and ſetled and bee not moved away from the hope of the Goſpel which ye have heard, and which was preached to every creature which is under heaven: whereof I am made a Miniſter. Eph. <hi>2.12.</hi> That at that time ye are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt, being Aliens from the common wealth of Iſrael, and ſtrangers from the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace, having no hope. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God in the world. <hi>1</hi> John <hi>5.10.</hi> He that beleeveth me the ſonne of God, hath the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in himſelfe, he that beleeveth not God, hath made him a lier, becauſe hee beleeveth not the record that God gave of his Sonne. John <hi>3.18.19.</hi> Hee that beleeveth one him, is not condemned, but hee that beleeveth not is condemned already, becauſe hee hath not beleeved in the name of the only begotten ſon of God. And this is the condemnation that
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:41463:105"/> light is come into the world, and men loved darkeneſſe more then light, becauſe their deeds were evill.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>Eighthly.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVE beleeve that the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called by the word of life and ſalvation to participate of the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous riches of Chriſt, is bound by an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting bond of love, and favour to yeeld all loyall obedience and ſubjection to Jeſus Chriſt her Lord and Maſter. 1 Cor. 1.9.</hi> God is faithfull, by whom ye were called unto the fellowſhip of his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. Rom. <hi>12.1, 2.</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you therefore brethren by the mercies of God, that ye preſent your bodies a living ſacrifice, holy, acceptable unto God which is your reaſonable ſacrifice, and be not confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to this world, but bee transformed by the renewing of your minde, that ye may prove what is that good and acceptable and perfect will of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>Ninthly.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVEE beleeve that the Church of Jeſus Chriſt is preſented glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:41463:105"/> in the ſight of God her heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through union with Jeſus Chriſt, and her intereſt in her royall robes of righteouſneſſe. Phil. 3.9.</hi> And being found in him, not having mine owne righteouſneſſe which is of the Law, but that which is tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the faith of Chriſt: the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which is of God by faith. Iſay <hi>61.10.</hi> I will greatly reioyce in the Lord, my ſoule ſhall be ioyfull in my God, for hee hath cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed me with he garments of Salvation, hee hath covered me with the robe of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as a bridegrorme decketh himſelfe with ornaments, and as a bride adorneth her ſelfe with her Jewells.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>Tenthly.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVE beleeve that neither ſin, the Law, nor Juſtice is any cauſe of her chaſtiſement; onely the free and deare love of her deere Father; to the end that he might teach her the way to glory, weaken the power of the fleſh, and make her live by faith and love be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him all her dayes.</hi> Heb. <hi>12.6.</hi> For whom the Lord loveth he chaſteneth, and ſcourgeth every ſonne whom hee receiveth. <hi>Apoc. 3.19.</hi> As many as I love, I rebuke
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:41463:106"/> and chaſten, be zealous therefore and repent. Pſal. <hi>119.6, 7.</hi> Then ſhall I not bee aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, when I ſhall have reſpect to all thy commandements: I will praiſe thee with uprightneſſe of heart, when I ſhall have lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thy righteous judgements. <hi>2</hi> Cor. <hi>12.7.</hi> And least I ſhould be exalted above mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure through the abundance of revelations, there was given to me a thorn in the fleſh, the meſſenger of Satan to buffet me, leaſt I ſhould exalted above meaſure. <hi>1</hi> Pet. <hi>1.6, 7.</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ye greatly rejoyce, though now for a ſeaſon if neede be ye are in heavineſſe through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold temptations, that the triall of your faith being much more pretious then of gold that periſheth, though it be tried with fire, might be found unto praiſe, and honour, and glory at the appearing of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <head>Eleventh.</head>
               <p>WE beleeve that although her God and father is in every place, and beholds all things, and by conſequence ſeeth ſin as it is in the fleſh: not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, having preſented her juſt by the act of Reconciliation through the blood of the Sonne of God. Juſtified her through the none imputation of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:41463:106"/> and made her ſtand in Chriſt for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver through union with him; hence ſhe ſtands in his ſight for ever without ſpot or wrinckle. Heb. 4.13. <hi>Neither is there any creature that is not manifeſt in his ſight, but all things are naked and open unto him with whom we have to doe.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Therfore if any man be in Chriſt, he is a new creature. Old things things are paſt away, behold all things are become new. Col.</hi> 1.22. <hi>In the body of his fleſh through death, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you holy, &amp; unblamable, &amp; unreprove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in his ſight. Epheſ.</hi> 5.27. <hi>That he might preſent to himſelfe a glorious Church, not having ſpot or wrinckle or any ſuch thing, but that it ſhould be holy and without ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>Twelfe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVE beleeve, that though in the dayes of</hi> Adam <hi>we with</hi> Adam <hi>ſtood under the old Covenant; yet that Covenant is wholy aboliſhed, and that now injoying the law of faith, mercy &amp; peace; we ſtand for ever under that cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which hath beene propoſed in Chriſt, hence it comes to paſſe, that we are freed abſolutely from the law of ſin and death, and are brought under the
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:41463:107"/> Law of freedome and life. Jer. 31.32.33.</hi> Not according to the Covenant that I made with their Fathers in the day when I tooke them by the hand to bring them out of the land of Egypt, which Covenant they brake, although I was a husband unto them ſaith the Lord. But this ſhall be the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that I will make with the houſe of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el after thoſe dayes ſaith the Lord, I will put my law in their inward parts, and write it in their hearts, and I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people. Heb. <hi>8.6.</hi> But now hath he obtained a more excellent miniſtry, by how much alſo he is the Mediator of a better Covenant which was establiſhed upon better promiſes. Rom. <hi>8.2.</hi> For the law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus hath made me free from the law of ſinne and death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <head>Thirteenth.</head>
               <p>VVE beleeve that the Saints are to be a deare, a tender, and a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving people, from the love that is given them in and through Jeſus Chriſt, and are bound to walke in the bond of Love, to the intent that they may ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves children of light, hold forth the love of Jeſus Chriſt, and the glory of
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:41463:107"/> God their heavenly and deareſt Father. <hi>John.</hi> 15.12. <hi>This is my Commandement that ye love one another as I have loved you. John</hi> 17.22. <hi>And the glory which thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt me, I have given them that they may be one; even as we are one.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <head>Fourteenth.</head>
               <p>VVE beleeve that the expreſſions of this love ſtands not onely in in the communion of gifts, but alſo of goods, inſomuch that is it poſſible they are to live in one body as one common wealth; nothing differing from the ſtate of the Churches in the City of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem. Acts 2.44, 45. <hi>And they that beleeved were together, and had althings common, and ſold their poſſeſſions and goods, and parted them to all men as every man had neede.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <head>Fifteenth.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe Saints are to be a quiet peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and loving people, ſith they are of the Kingdome and patience of Jeſus Chriſt, God hath called them to peace, having given them a command to have
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:41463:108"/> peace with all, and love towards all men.</hi> And he ſhall judge among the nations, and ſhall rebuke many people, and they ſhall beate their ſwords into plowſhares, and their ſpeares into pruning hookes, Nation ſhall not lift up ſwords againſt Nation, neither ſhall they learne warre any more. <hi>Iſay 65.25.</hi> The Wolfe and the Lambe ſhall feede to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and the Lyon ſhall eate ſtraw like the bullock, and duſt ſhall be the ſerpents meate, they ſhal not hurt nor deſtroy in all my moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines ſaith the Lord. Apoc. <hi>13.10.</hi> He that leadeth into captivity ſhall goe into captivity, he that killeth with the ſword, muſt be killed with the ſword; Here is the patience and the faith of the Saints. <hi>Apoc. 12.11.</hi> And they overcame him by the blood of the Lamb, and by the word of their testimony, and they loved not their lives unto the death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <head>Sixteenth.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVEE beleeve that thoſe that are to enter into a Churches eſtate, are to make known to the Church their experience of the Spirit and faith in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, inſomuch that none are to bee admitted into a Churches ſtate but ſuch as are cordiall in their faith, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perementall
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:41463:108"/> through communion with the Lord Jeſus. Acts 8.37.</hi> And <hi>Philip</hi> ſaid, if thou beleeveſt with all thine heart, thou mayest, and he anſwered and ſaid, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that Jeſus Chriſt is the Sonne of God. Acts <hi>10.47.</hi> Can any man forbid water, that theſe ſhould not be baptized which have received the holy Ghoſt as well as we. Acts <hi>9.26, 27.</hi> And when <hi>Saul</hi> was come to <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> hee aſſayed to joyne himſelfe unto the Diſciples, but they were all affraid of him, and beleeved not that he was a Diſciple, but Barnabas tooke him and brought him to the Apoſtles, and declared unto them how he had ſeene thk Lord in the way, and that hee had ſpoken to him, and how he had preached boldly at Damaſcus in the name of Jeſus, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>Seventeenth.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVEE underſtand that although their ought to be an eſpeciall love of the Saints one towards another, notwithſtanding, they are to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves loving, courteous, and gentle to all that are without; not reproaching but praiſing, praying and bleſſing God for all that hate them. Mat. 5.44, 45, 46.</hi> But I ſay unto you, love your Enemies, bleſſe
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:41463:109"/> them that curſe you, doe good to them that hate you, and pray for them which diſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully uſe you, and perſecute you. That ye may be the children of your Father which is in Heaven: for he maketh his Sun to riſe on the evill, and on the good, and ſendeth raine on the juſt, and on the unjuſt. For if ye love them which love you, what reward have ye? Doe not even the Publicans the ſame?</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <p>TRuſt ye not in a friend, put ye not confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in a guide: keepe the doores of thy mouth from her that lieth in thy boſom. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will look unto the Lord: I will waite for the God of my ſalvation, my God will heare me. Iſa. <hi>50.6, 7.</hi> I gave my backe to the ſmiters, and my cheekes to them that plucked off the haire: I hid not my face from ſhame and ſpitting. For the Lord will helpe mee, therefore ſhall I not be confounded: therefore have I ſet my face like a flint, and I know that I ſhall not be aſhamed.</p>
            <p>VVE judge no man. If any man is contrary minded, God ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale it according to his Divine Love and rareſt Mercy in the beloved.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41463:109"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
